<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mikrokosmographa. A description of the little-world, or, body of man, exactly delineating all the parts according to the best anatomists. With the severall diseases thereof. Also their particular and most approved cures. / by R.T. doctor of physick.</title>
            <author>Turner, Robert, fl. 1654-1665.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 224 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 94 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B10213</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC"> 80924904</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T3330</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R185799</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">80924904</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 80924904</idno>
            <idno type="VID">192126</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B10213)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 192126)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; 1641-1700 ; 2900:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Mikrokosmographa. A description of the little-world, or, body of man, exactly delineating all the parts according to the best anatomists. With the severall diseases thereof. Also their particular and most approved cures. / by R.T. doctor of physick.</title>
                  <author>Turner, Robert, fl. 1654-1665.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 172 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Edward Archer ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London,:</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>First word of the title and caption title are transliterated from the Greek.</note>
                  <note>Includes index.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Human anatomy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Body, Human --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Diseases --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:192126:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:192126:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ΜΙΚΡΟΚΟΣΜΟΓΡΑΦΑ. A Deſcription of the <hi>Little-World,</hi> OR, Body of Man, Exactly delineating all the parts according to the beſt Anatomiſts.</p>
            <p>With the ſeverall diſeaſes thereof.</p>
            <p>Alſo their particular and moſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved Cures.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> R. T. Doctor of Phyſick.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Edward Archer,</hi> and are to be ſold at the ſign of the <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> in <hi>Little-Brittain,</hi> neer the Church. 1654</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:192126:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Modern bookplate</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:192126:2"/>
            <head>TO THE NOBLE, VERTUOUS, AND RELIGIOUS LADY, THE LADY <hi>THOROWGOOD,</hi> VVife to the Right VVorſhipfull, Sir <hi>John Thorowgood</hi> of <hi>Kenſington,</hi> Knight.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honoured Madam:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>EE pleaſed to pardon my boldneſſe in this, and command me in what li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beral Service you pleaſe: After many yeares ſpecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation,
<pb facs="tcp:192126:3"/>and peruſall of many Maps hereof, I preſent Your Ladiſhip with an Epitome, or Compendious Diſcourſe of the <hi>Little World, MAN;</hi> not that I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to informe you in any thing you know not; I am too ſenſible of my owne defects to conceive ſuch an impoſſibility; my owne experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of your Ladiſhips Judgement here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, teſtifies the contrary; but the many Ingagements and Obligations, whereby I am bound to your Ladiſhip for your ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold and extraordinary favours and cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſies exhibited towards me, both in ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and in health, (having no other means to give any recompenee for them) imboldens me to preſent this ſmall paper to your Ladiſhip, which I earneſtly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat you to accept into your moſt worthy Patronage, that I may thereby be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curely armed againſt the envious Crit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, and encouraged hereafter, if God enable me to preferre ſome more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Worke to your protection; beyond
<pb facs="tcp:192126:3"/>which I have no ambition, but to expreſs my true and ſincere ſervice to your Ladi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and the right Worſhipfull, your Husband, whom I beſeech the Almighty to accumulate with all bleſſings and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe, preſent and future, taking the boldneſſe to ſubſcribe my ſelfe,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your humble Servant, ROBERT TURNER.</signed>
               <dateline>London <date>29. Octob. 1653.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:192126:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:192126:4"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T being the nature of all men to deſire and ſeeke after knowledge; I have therefore given thee a breife charac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or epitome of the body of man, the little world; whereby thou mayſt attaine to the moſt neceſsary externall knowledge of thy ſelfe; which being knowne, if any cauſuallty happen, thou maiſt the more properly apply a remedy, for which there are many excellent and approved medicines, heere in this enſuing Treatiſe ſet downe: and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the nature and cure of wounds, made by Gunpowder, and Gunſhot; but if any one more curious, in ſenſuring what is done for a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon good, rather then ſtudious to promote
<pb facs="tcp:192126:5"/>it, ſhould grumble at me for this my paines, I might anſwer him in his owne kind by way of queſtion, as, <hi>Menedemus</hi> anſwered <hi>Chre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes</hi> finding fault with him, <hi>Tantum ne abs re tua eſt otii tibi, aliena ut cures, eaque nihil quae ad te attinent?</hi> haſt thou ſo much leaſure as to meddle with that which ſo little con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns thee? yet to ſatiſfie thee [gentle Reader] who intendeſt [I know] to gather hony with the Bee out of this Garden, and not poyſon with the Spider; I have implored the aid of <hi>Apollo</hi> and <hi>Hypocrates,</hi> to compoſe thee ſome <hi>Hypnoticon</hi> or <hi>Diacodion;</hi> not a medicine for one diſeaſe alone; but fitting ſome receipt or other for all Ages, and all capacities to apply them; and for all Complexions and Conditions, parts, and places, a medicine Preſervative, Curative, and Reſtorative; heere are Antidotes or dictamum againſt the Plague and peſtilentiall Ayres; many of the receipts I have not Engliſhed, but leaving them in their proper names which cannot be very well taken from them, neither was I willing to deprive them of it, knowing that at any Apothecaries you may readily bee
<pb facs="tcp:192126:5"/>furniſhed with them; others of more eaſiy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition and moſt obvious to the vulgar uſe, I have written in words at large, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the moſt part, compounded of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Engliſh hearbs, wherewith almoſt every one can ſpeedily furniſh themſelves; Take therfore in good part [Reader] the fruits of this labour, and as <hi>Robera parentum liberi re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferunt,</hi> as the growth of the child argues the ſtrength of the parent; ſo when I ſhall attaine to riper age, this firſt borne may have a ſecond generation; books have an immortality above their Authors, for when they grew of full age, they can be againe retaken into the wombe that bred them and receive with a new life, a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter portion of youth and glory which is to them another being, and that alwayes may and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten doth, bring with them an addition of ſtrength, and lovelineſs, uſhering them to a more vigorous perfection.</p>
            <p>Thus have I layd before thee a little map of thy ſelfe or a deſcription of the microcoſmos or little world, Man, equally endeavoring thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and profit, <hi>Quoniam variant animi va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riabamus
<pb facs="tcp:192126:6"/>artes, mille mali ſpecies, mille ſalutis erunt:</hi> A modeſt cenſure hereof I gladly would entertaine; as I am not ambitious of applauſe, ſo not affraid of cenſure; give me leave to flatter my paines in theſe words, <hi>Hic interim liber, aut laudatus erit, aut ſaltem excuſatus;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All I deſire is but encourragment to ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther worke, if any thing herein ſhall redound to thy profit; let me petition thee to give God the Glory who hath enabled mee to performe it, which are the hearty wiſhes of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy aſſured freind, <hi>Ro: Turner.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>London,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>29. Octob. 1653.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="authors_cited">
            <pb facs="tcp:192126:6"/>
            <head>Authours uſed in this Booke.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Ariſtotle.</item>
               <item>Avicenna.</item>
               <item>Ipocras.</item>
               <item>Pliny.</item>
               <item>Haly.</item>
               <item>Galen.</item>
               <item>Guido.</item>
               <item>Turner.</item>
               <item>Hypocrates.</item>
               <item>Dioſcorides.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="list_of_abbreviations">
            <pb facs="tcp:192126:7"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:192126:7"/>
            <head>Characters for brevity uſed heerein.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <abbr>lb.</abbr> a pound.</item>
               <item>℥. an ounce.</item>
               <item>
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>. a drachm.</item>
               <item>gr. a graine.</item>
               <item>℈. a ſcruple.</item>
               <item>Q ſ. quantity ſufficient.</item>
               <item>M. a handfull.</item>
               <item>ſs. halfe.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>ana.</hi> each.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:192126:8"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:192126:8"/>
            <head>
               <hi>ΜΙΚΡΟΚΟΣΜΟΣ,</hi> A Deſcription of the little World.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Shewing the Definition of Chyrurgery, the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications of a Chyrurgion, and Anatomy of the ſimple Members.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hyrurgery is derived, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which is as much as to ſay a hand working; ſo that Chyrurgery is a work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the hand in the body of man, in cutting or opening thoſe parts that be whole, in healing thoſe parts that be broken or cut, and in taking away that which is ſuperfluous, as Warts, Wens, Scurfula's, and the like: To the cure of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very diſeaſe belongeth four things; the firſt and principall is God, the ſecond the Chyrurgion, the third the Medicine and fourth the Patient: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Chyrurgion ought to be Religious. Inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:192126:9"/>Learned, and Expert, both in Theorick and in Practick; he muſt be skilfull in the Anatonay, elſe he will be like a blind man to carve an Image; he muſt be ſecret and private, as a Confeſſour to his Patient, not diſcouraging any, nor ſetting a certain day of his recovery, as Mountebanks doe, for that is not in their power, <hi>oportet ſeipſum non ſolum,</hi> neither let them backbite others nor vaunt and praiſe themſelves, that will redound more to their ſhame then credit, for their own workes will get credit enough.</p>
               <p>Of the ſimple members there be 11. and 2. ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluities, <hi>viz.</hi> Bones, Cartilages, Nerves, Pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicles, Ligaments, Cords, Arteries, Veynes, fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, fleſh, and skin; the ſuperfluities be haires and nailes; the bones be the foundation and hardeſt member of the body; it is a <hi>conſimile</hi> member, ſimple and ſpermatick, cold and dry of complexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, inſenſible and inflexible, and hath divers formes in mans body, for the ſeverall operations thereof, and diverſity of helpings; the griſtle is a member ſimple and ſpermatick, next in hardneſſe to the bone and is of complexion cold and dry, and inſenſible.</p>
               <p>The Ligament is a member conſimple, ſimple, and ſpermatick, next in hardneſſe to the griſtle, and of complexion cold and dry, flexible and ſenſible, and binds the bones together.</p>
               <p>The ſinew is a <hi>conſimile</hi> member, ſimple and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:192126:9"/>ſpermatick, mean between hard and ſoft, ſtrong and tough, having his beginning from the braine, or from <hi>minuca,</hi> which is the marrow of the back, and from the braine cometh ſeven paire of Nerves ſentative, and from <hi>minuca</hi> cometh ſeven pair of Nerves motive, and one that is by himſelfe that ſpringeth from the laſt ſpondell.</p>
               <p>A Cord or Tendon is an officiall member com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds and ſpermatick, ſinowy, ſtrong, and tough, meanly between hardneſſe and ſoftneſſe, and ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and flexible, cold and dry.</p>
               <p>An Arterie is a member ſimple and ſpermatick, hollow and ſinowy, having his beginning from the heart, and bringeth from the heart to every member, ſpirit, and life, it is of complexion cold and dry; and all theſe Arteries have two coates, except one that goeth to the lungs, and he hath but one coat, that ſpreadeth abroad in the lungs, and bringeth to the lungs bloud and ſpirit of life, and ſendeth from thence ayre to temper the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous heat that is in the heart: A veyne is a ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple member, in complexion cold and dry, and ſpermatick like to the Arterie, having his begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning from the liver, nutritive bloud to nouriſh eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry member of the body with; and the Arterie is a veſſell of bloud ſpirituall or vitall, and a veyne a veſſell of bloud nutrimentall; the fleſh is a ſimple member not ſpermatick, ingendred of bloud, in complexion hot and moiſt: There is three kindes
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:192126:10"/>of fleſh, the one ſoft and pure, the ſecond <hi>muſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus,</hi> hard or brawny, the third is <hi>grandulus,</hi> knot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry or kurnelly: Next is fatneſſe, whereof likewiſe is three kindes, <hi>pinguedo,</hi> which is made of a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till portion of bloud, congealed by cold; it is cold and moiſt, inſenſible and intermedled amongſt the parts of the fleſh; the ſecond is <hi>adeppes,</hi> of the ſame kind as the other, but is parted from the fleſh beſides the skin, and is as an oyle healing the skin, and moiſtning it; the third is <hi>au xingia,</hi> parted from the fleſh about the kidneys and entrails.</p>
               <p>The skin is a member officiall, partly ſperma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick, ſtrong and tough, flexible and ſenſible, thin and temperate, one covereth the outward mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, and the other the inward, which is called a pannicle.</p>
               <p>The haires are ſuperfluities made of the groſſe fume or ſmoake paſſing out of the viſcous matter, and thickned to the form of hair.</p>
               <p>The nailes likewiſe are ſuperfluous humours, engendred of earthly fume, waxing through the naturall heat of humours to the extremity of the fingers and toes, in complexion cold and dry, and is ſofter then the bone and harder then the fleſh, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:192126:10"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Of the compound members: <hi>1.</hi> Of the head.</head>
               <p>THe head is the habitation or dwelling place of the reaſonable ſoule of man, as, <hi>homini ſublime dedit;</hi> it is raiſed up by God as a watch tower over all the body; it is compoſed of hair, skin, fleſh, veines, Pannicles, and bones; the hair defendeth the braine from too much heat, and too much cold, it beautifieth and adorneth the head and face, and by it the fumoſity of the braine are purged; the skin of the head is more <hi>lazartus</hi> and thicker then any other of the body, defendeth the braine, and keepeth it warme, and bindeth and keepeth the bones of the head faſt together; the fleſh is <hi>muſculus</hi> or <hi>lazartus</hi> lying upon <hi>pericrani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um</hi> without means.</p>
               <p>Next followeth <hi>pericranium,</hi> or the covering of the bones of the head, between the fleſh, and which paſſeth a veine and an arteir, that nouriſheth the utter part of the head, paſſeth through the skul and nouriſheth the pannicles of the braine, and hereof is made <hi>dura mater,</hi> which is nearer the braine then <hi>pericranium,</hi> and under the skull.</p>
               <p>Next is the bone or pot of the head, whereof there be ſeven in number in the pan or skull; the firſt is the Coronall Bone, in which is the holes of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:192126:11"/>the eyes, and reacheth from the browes to the midſt of the head, where it meeteth with a ſecond bone of the hinder part of the head called the nod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dell of the head, which two bones be divided by the comiſſaries in the midſt of the head; the third and fourth bones be called <hi>Parietales,</hi> and they be divided by the comiſſaries from the two former; the fifth and ſixth be called <hi>Petroſa</hi> or <hi>mendoſa,</hi> on each ſide of the head one, wherein are the holes of the eares; the ſeventh and laſt is called Paxillary or Bazillary, which bone as a wedge doth faſten the reſt together. Theſe are the parts of the head containing, next followeth the parts contained: The firſt is <hi>dura mater,</hi> then <hi>pia mater,</hi> then the ſubſtance of the brain, <hi>vermi formes &amp; rete mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bile;</hi> the Pannicle <hi>dura mater</hi> is made of the vein &amp; arterie ſpoken of before, which paſſeth through the ſeames of the head, which <hi>dura mater</hi> is ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from the bone of the skull, the better to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the <hi>pia mater;</hi> the next is the pannicle called <hi>pia mater,</hi> which is tender and ſoft over the brain and in it are contained a great number of veines and arteries, giving unto the brain both ſpirit and life, from the heart and from the liver nutriment; this pannicle circumvolveth all the ſubſtance, and there the ſpirit is made animall; theſe pannicles be cold and dry, ſpermatick; next unto this pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicle is the brain it ſelfe, which is divided into three ventricles, the formoſt which is moſt, the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:192126:11"/>middlemoſt leſſe, and the hindmoſt which is leaſt, and from each to other be iſſues and paſſages con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veying ſpirit of life; and every ventricle is divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into two parts: in the formoſt ventricle God hath placed the common ſenſes, in the one part thereof is contained the fanſie, in the other part the imaginative vertue, which receiveth the forme of ſenſible things, repreſenting them to the memory: in the middle ſell or ventrickle there is placed the contemplative or cogitative virtue; and in the third or laſt the virtue memorative, out of whoſe lower parts ſpringeth <hi>Mynuca,</hi> or marrow of the Spondels: Further, from the formoſt ventrickle there ſprings ſeven paire of ſinewes, produced to the eyes, ears, the noſe, the tongue, and the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack, and to divers other parts of the body: A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the middle ventrickle is the place of <hi>vermi formis,</hi> with curnelly fleſh that filleth, and <hi>rete mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabile,</hi> that wonderfull net or caule under the pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicles of ſmall arteries only comming from the heart, and there the ſpirit of feeling hath his firſt creation, and from thence paſſeth to other mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers; the brain is a member cold and moiſt, thin and meanly viſcous and ſpermatick, continually moving and ruling all other members of the body, giving them feeling and moving: And Ariſtotle ſaith, that it followeth the courſe of the Moon; in the waxing of the Moon it followeth upwards and in the wane of the Moon it diſcends down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:192126:12"/>and is leſſe in ſubſtance of virtue, and is not ſo obedient to the ſpirit of feeling, as it appears in lunaticks, and ſuch as have the falling ſickneſſe, who are moſt grieved in the beginning of the new Moon, and in the wane of the Moon; therefore if the brain be either too dry or too moiſt, it cannot worke its kind, whereby the ſpirits of life melt and art ſolve away, and then followeth ſickneſſe and feebleneſſe of the wits and other members, and in the end death, and thus much of the head.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Of the face.</head>
               <p>THe firſt part on the face is the forehead, which containeth skin and <hi>muſculus</hi> fleſh, the pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicle under it is of <hi>pericranium,</hi> and the bone Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronall, which paſſeth from one eare to another with a muſckle, which keepeth up the eye brows which are called <hi>ſupercilium,</hi> and under them is the eye lids called <hi>cilium,</hi> which defend the eyes from annoyances, and are ſet and adorned with haires; the eares are griftly, the organ or inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of hearing cold and dry, the ſinews whereof ſpring from the brain, and through them is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the ſound, and conveyed to the common wits: The eyes be next of nature unto the ſoule wherein is ſeen the paſſions of the ſoule, as joy gladneſs, love, wrath, &amp;c. They are the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of ſight compounded of ſeven tunicles o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:192126:12"/>roles, and three humours, and theſe ſinewes be hollow as a reed, that thereby the viſible things might paſſe to the ſight; now theſe ſinews go out from the ſubſtance of the brain, paſſing through <hi>pia mater,</hi> where he taketh a pannickle, and theſe are called <hi>nervi optici,</hi> and are joyned in one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they come into the eye, that if any diſeaſe happen in one eye the other ſhould receive the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible ſpirit, and that one ſinew might ſtay and help the other: Now the three humours are pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in the middle of the eyes, the firſt is the vitriall humour like glaſſe, liquid and thin, and is inner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt next to the brain, and he compaſſeth the chriſtalline humour, untill he meeteth the humour <hi>Albuginus,</hi> which is ſet in the uppermoſt part of the eye, and in the midſt of theſe humours is placed the chriſtaline humour, in which is the principall fight of the eye; and theſe humours be involved with the pannicles, between every humour a pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicle, and thus is the eye made; the next un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoken of in order is the noſe; from the braine cometh two ſinews to the holes of the brain pan, where doth begin the concavity of the noſe, and theſe two be the organs or inſtruments of ſmell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, they have heads like teats or paps, and receive the ſmelling conveying it to the common ſenſes; over theſe two is <hi>colatorium,</hi> the noſthrils between the eyes, and through them paſſeth the ſpirit of ſmelling unto the inſtrument of ſmelling, and by
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:192126:13"/>them the ſuperfluities of the brain are cleanſed, and from his concavity there paſſeth two holes down into the mouth, whereby ayre paſſeth too and free into the lungs, and when theſe are ſtopped then one is ſayd to ſpeak in his noſe; it is made of skin and <hi>lazartus</hi> fleſh, and of two bones ſtanding tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angle wiſe, joyned to the coronall bone, and it hath two griſtles that hold up the noſe, and two muskles to help the working of his office: The cheekes are the ſideling parts of the face, and they containe in them <hi>muſculous</hi> fleſh with veines and arteries; about theſe parts be many muskles, <hi>Guido</hi> ſaith ſeven about the cheekes and upper lip, and <hi>Haly Abbas,</hi> that there be twelve that move the nether jaw in opening and ſhutting, that paſſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the bones of the temples, they are called tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porals, and they be ſenſitive, and whoſe hurt is dangerous: Then there be alſo other muskles for to grinde and to chew, and to all theſe muskles cometh nerves from the brain, and there cometh unto them many arteries and veins, and chiefly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the temples, the angles or corners of the eyes and the lips; in the checks is the chiefe beauty, thereby the complexion is moſt known, and (as <hi>Avicen</hi> ſaith) they ſhew alſo the affections and paſſions of the heart, waxing pale or red at the ſuddain joy or dread of the heart: of the face be two bones, two of the noſe outwardly two of the upper mandible, one of the nether, three of the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:192126:13"/>noſe within, in all ten. The parts of the mouth are five, the lips, the teeth, the tongue, the <hi>uvula,</hi> and pallat of the mouth; and firſt the lips are members official of <hi>muſculous</hi> fleſh, ſerving to the mouth as doores to an houſe, and helping the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounciation of the ſpeech; the teeth are likewiſe officiall, the hardeſt of all members, and are faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the cheek bones, ſerving to chew the meat and helping the pronountiation of the ſpeech: They that have the whole number have two and thirty; the tongue is a <hi>carnous</hi> member, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound, of many nerves, ligaments, veines and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries, receiveth the taſt, and pronounceth every ſpeech, the fleſh of the tongue is white, and hath in him nine muskles, the root of him is <hi>glandulous,</hi> wherein are two wels containing ſpettle to tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and keep moiſt the tongue; the <hi>uvula</hi> is of ſpongeous fleſh, hanging down from the end of the pallate over the gutter of the throat, and is cold and dry, and oftentimes when there falleth raw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe or much moiſtneſſe into it from the head, then it hangeth down into the throat, and letteth a man to ſwallow; it helpeth the ſound of the ſpeech, the prolation of vomits, and tempereth the ayre that paſſeth to the lungs, and guideth the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſluities of the brain, which come from the cole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of the noſe.</p>
               <p>The pallate of the month is a carnous pannicle, and the bones that be underneath it have two di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:192126:14"/>one along the pallate, from the diviſion of the noſe, and from the opening of the other man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible, under the neither end of the pallate, lack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing halfe an inch, and there it divideth overthwart and the firſt diviſion is of the mandible, and the ſecond is of the bone called Paxillary or Bazillary, that ſuſtains and bindeth all the other bones of the head together; the skin of the pallate of the mouth is of the inner part of the ſtomack, and of <hi>Myre</hi> and <hi>Iſofagus,</hi> that is the way of the meat unto the ſtomack; alſo in the mouth is ended the upper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt extremity of the Weſand, which is called <hi>Mire</hi> or <hi>Iſofagus;</hi> and with him is contained <hi>Trachia Arteria, viz.</hi> the paſſage of the ayre or breath, whoſe holes be covered with a lap like un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a tongue, and is griſtly, that the meat and drink might ſlide over him into <hi>Iſofagus,</hi> which is rear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up when a man ſpeaketh and covereth the way of the meat, and when a man ſwalloweth, then it covereth the way of the ayre, ſo that when one is open the other is covered; and thus much ſhall ſuffice for the Anatomy of the head and face, which is under the celeſtiall ſigne <hi>Aries.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:192126:14"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Of the Neck.</head>
               <p>THe neck followeth next to be ſpoken of, which is contained between the head and the ſhoulders, and between the chin and the breaſt; in the neck be ſeven ſpondels, the firſt joyned un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the lower part of the head, and every ſpondell in like manner, the laſt of the ſeven is joyned unto the ridge of the back, and the ligaments that keep theſe ſpondels together are not ſo hard and tough as the ligaments of the back, but more feeble and ſubtle, becauſe of the often moving of the neck; out of theſe ſeven ſpondels there ſpring ſeven pair of ſinews, which be divided into the head, the ſhoulders and the armes: The muskles of the neck (as <hi>Gallen</hi> ſaith) are twenty, moving the head and the neck; the third part of the neck is called <hi>gut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> which is the ſtanding out of the throat bell, the fourth part <hi>gula,</hi> and the hinder part <hi>cernix</hi> ſo called, becauſe of the marrow that commeth to the ridge bones, and it is (as it were) a ſervant to the brain, and receiveth of the brain the virtue of moving, and ſendeth it by ſinews to all the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the body: Here alſo obſerve, that the way through which the meat paſſeth, or <hi>Iſofagus</hi> ſtretcheth from the mouth to the ſtomack, and is
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:192126:15"/>faſtned to the ſpondels of the neck untill he come to the firſt ſpondell, and extendeth forward to the breaſt, and endeth at the mouth of the ſtomack; this we ſand is compound, conſiſting of two tuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles or coats, the inner and the outer; the outer tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicle is ſimple, the inner is compound of <hi>muſculous</hi> longitudinall will, whereby he draweth the meat into the ſtomack; alſo it is to be underſtood that the great veins which paſſe by the ſides of the neck, to the upper part of the head, are called <hi>vena organices,</hi> of which the inciſion is dangerous; thus you ſee the neck is compoſed of skinny fleſh, ligaments, and bones, and is under the dominion of the ſign <hi>Taurus.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Of the Armes and Shoulders.</head>
               <p>IN the ſhoulder there be two bones, the ſhoulder bone and the cannell bone, the firſt is <hi>os ſpatula,</hi> or blade bone of the ſhoulder, whoſe hinder part declineth toward the chin, and in that end it is broad and thin, and in the upper part it is round; wherein in a concavity, called the box or coope of the ſhoulder, and which entereth the adjutor bones of the armes, and they are bound together with ſtrong flexible ſinews, and are contained faſt
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:192126:15"/>with <hi>clauicula,</hi> or the cannell bone, which bone extendeth to both the ſhoulders, one end to one ſhoulder, and another to the other, and there they make the compoſition of the ſhoulders; the bones of the armes from the ſhoulder to the fingers ends be thirty; the firſt is the adjutor bone of the arm, the upper end whereof entereth into the box of the ſhoulder bone, it is hollow and full of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and extendeth to the elbow, where it hath two knobs in the juncture of the elbow, entering into a concavity proportioned, in the uppermoſt ends of the two foſell bones, the leſſe whereof go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth from the elbow to the thumb, by the upper part of the arme, and the greater neathermoſt from the elbow to the little finger; and theſe bones be joyned and bound together with the adjutor bone with ſtrong ligaments, and likewiſe with the bones of the hand; the bones of the hand are eight, four uppermoſt and four neathermoſt, and in the palme of the hand five called <hi>oſſa patinis,</hi> unto them are joyned the bones of the fingers and thumbes, in every finger three bones, and in the thumbe two; ſo that there is in the fingers and thumbe of every hand fourteen bones called <hi>oſſa digitorum,</hi> in the palme of the hand five called <hi>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinis,</hi> and between the hand and the wriſt eight, and from the wriſt to the ſhoulder three bones, which in the whole numbred together are thirty, in each hand and arme, likewiſe there cometh from
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:192126:16"/>
                  <hi>Minuca,</hi> and the ſpondels of the neck four ſinews, one cometh along the upper part of the arm, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther paſſeth under the arme, one in the inner ſide, and another in the outer ſide of the arme, which bring unto the armes feeling and moving from the brain and <hi>minuca;</hi> now to ſpeak of the veins and arteries of the arme, from <hi>venakelis</hi> ſpringeth two branches, one runneth to one arme pit, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to another, and there the branch is divided into two parts, or other branches, one goeth along the innerſide of the arme, untill it commeth to the bought of the arme, and there it is called <hi>Bazillica</hi> or <hi>Epatica,</hi> and then goeth down the arme, till it come to the wriſt, where it turneth to the back of the hand, and goeth between the little finger and the next, and there is called <hi>ſalvatella;</hi> the other branch in the arme hole ſpreadeth to the utter ſide of the ſhoulder, where he divideth in two, the one goeth up ſpreading in the carnous part of the head and paſſeth through the bone into the veine; the other branch runneth along the outward ſide of the arme, and there is divided into two alſo, the one part endeth at the hand, the other part foldeth about the arme, and in the bouget of the arme is called <hi>Sephalica,</hi> from thence it goeth to the back of the hand, appeareth between the thumbe and the forefinger, and is there called <hi>Sephaelica occula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio;</hi> there are in the arme five principall veines from each of the two branches that I ſpeak of,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:192126:16"/>which bee divided in the hinder part of the ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, ſpringeth one vein, and thoſe two meet toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the bought of the arme, and there is called <hi>Mediana,</hi> or <hi>Cordialis,</hi> or <hi>Commine,</hi> and of <hi>vena Sephalica</hi> ſpringeth <hi>vena oculoris,</hi> and of <hi>vena Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zilita</hi> ariſeth <hi>vena Salvatella,</hi> and of the two veins that meet there ſpringeth <hi>vena mediana;</hi> and from theſe five principall veins there ſpring innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble other ſmall veins, but of them the Chyrurgion hath not ſo great charge; further you ſhall under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that whereſoever there is found a vein, there is an Artery under him, if it be a great vein, there is a great Artery; and contrariwiſe, a little vein a little Artery, for whereſoever there goeth a vein to carry nutrimentall bloud, there alſo goeth an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, conveying the ſpirit of life. Therefore the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries lye deeper in the fleſh then the veins do, and carry in them more pure and precious bloud, therefore he is further from outward danger then the veine, and is covered with two coats, the vein only with one: and thus much for the arms and ſhoulders, which are governed by the ſigne <hi>Gemini.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> Of the Breaſt, Heart, and Back.</head>
               <p>THe Breaſt or <hi>Thorax</hi> is the Ark or Cheſt of the ſpirituall members, where there are four parts
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:192126:17"/>containing, and eight contained; the foure con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining are the skin, muſculous fleſh, the paps, and bones; the parts contained are, the Heart, the Lungs, Panicles, Ligaments, Nervs, Veins, Arteries, Myre, or <hi>Iſophagus.</hi> Of the skin and the fleſh its ſpoken of before, but you muſt obſerve that the fleſh of the paps differeth from the other fleſh of the body, for it is white, glandulus, and ſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous; and there is in them both Nerves, veins, and Arteries, &amp; by them they have Coligaves with the heart, the liver, and brain, and the generative members. Alſo there is in the breaſt 80 or 90 Muckles, ſome of them common to the neck, ſome to the ſhoulders, ſome to the Midriffe; ſome to the Ribs, ſome to the Back, and ſome to the Breaſt it ſelfe; and in man the paps defend the ſpirituals from outward annoyance; and by their thickneſſe they comfort the naturall heat; and in women there is the generation of milk, which commeth from the matrix to their breaſts through many veins, that bring into them menſtrual bloud, which is turned (by the digeſtive virtue) from red into white, like the colour of the paps, even as the ſtones turn the bloud into ſperme of the ſame na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and colour of themſelves ſo is the chile com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming from the ſtomack to the Liver turned into the colour of the Liver: Now the bones of the breaſt are ſaid to be triple or threefold, and they be numbred, ſeven in the breaſt before, and their
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:192126:17"/>length is according to the breadth of the breaſt, and their ends be griſtly, as the ribs be, and at the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per end of <hi>Thorax,</hi> is a hole or Concavity in which is ſet the foot of the Cannell bone, and at the lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer end of <hi>Thorax</hi> againſt the mouth of the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack, is a griſtle called <hi>Enſi-forme,</hi> which defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the ſtomack from outward hurt; and giveth place to it in time of fulneſſe when need requireth. Now to ſpeak of the parts of the back behind, there are twelve ſpondels, through whom paſſeth <hi>minu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca,</hi> of whom ſpringeth 12 paire of Nerves, which bring feeling end moving to the muskles of the breaſt, and in each ſide there be twelve Ribs, ſeven true, and five falſe, which five are ſhorter then the other ſeven; and therefore called falſe Ribs. Of the parts that be inward, the heart is the principal, firſt, and beginner of life, he is the <hi>primum vivens, &amp; ultimum moriens,</hi> and he is ſeated ſeverally by himſelfe, in the midſt of the breaſt as Lord and King over all the members, and all the members receive their bloud of life from the heart; the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the heart is as it were Lazartus fleſh, an officiall member ſpermatick, ſending forth to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Member ſpirit of breath and heat, by his moving and ſtirring. The heart hath the ſhape and forme of a Pine-apple, the broad end thereof is upwards, and the ſharp end downwards, depending a little towards the left ſide. Alſo the heort hath bloud in his ſubſtance, wheras all other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers have it but
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:192126:18"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:192126:18"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:192126:19"/>in their veins and Arteries; and the heart is bound with certaine Ligaments to the backe part of the breaſt, but they touch not the ſubſtance of the heart, but in the overpart they ſpring out of him, and is faſtned as aforeſaid; further the heart hath two ventricles, or concavities, and the left is higher then the right, and in this hollowneſſe he keepeth the bloud for his nouriſhing, and the ayre to abate and temper the great heat he is in; likewiſe here obſerve, that to the right ventricle of the heart commeth a vein from <hi>venakelis</hi> that receiveth all the ſubſtance of bloud from the Liver to nouriſt the heart with, and the reſidue of it is made ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till through the vertue of the heart and then it paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth through the Concavity of the heart, and ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is made hot and pure, and then it paſſeth into th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> left ventricle, and there is ingendred in it a ſpirit that is cleare, bright, and ſubtile, and a meane be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the body and the ſoule; further it is to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> noter, that from the left ventrickle of the hear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſpringeth two Arteries, the one having but on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Coat, and is called <hi>Arteria venalis,</hi> which Arter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> carrieth bloud from the heart to the Lungs to giv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> them nutriment, and bringeth ayre from the Lung<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to the heart to refreſh him with. The other Arter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hath two Coats and is called <hi>vena Arterialis,</hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of him ſpringeth all other Arteries that ſpread <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> every member of the body; and the ſpirit that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> retained in them is the Inſtrument or treaſure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:192126:19"/>the ſoule, and at the braine he receiveth a further digeſtion, and there is made animall, and at the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver nutrimentall, and at the teſticles or ſtones ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerative, and this Artery is alſo called the pulſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive vein, or the beating veine. Alſo there is in the heart three pellicks, opening and cloſing the going in of the heart, bloud, and ſpirit; the heart hath likewiſe two little ears through whom paſſeth the ayre from the Lungs: The heart is alſo covered with a ſtrong pannicle called <hi>Pericordium,</hi> unto which commeth nerves, as unto the other mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, and this pannicle ſpringeth of the upper pan-pannicle of the midriffe. And from him ſpringeth another pannicle which parteth the breaſt in the middle, and is called <hi>Mediaſtricum,</hi> and keepeth the Lungs that they fall not over the heart; there is alſo another Pannicle that covereth the Ribs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly of whom the midriffe hath his beginning. And thus much of the Breaſt and Heart, which are under the ſignes <hi>Cancer</hi> and <hi>Leo.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> Of the Lungs, Bowels, and Belly.</head>
               <p>THe Lungs is a member Spermatick of his firſt Creation, in his naturall complexion coid and dry, and accidentally cold and moyſt, lapped in a
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:192126:20"/>nervous pannicle, that it might gather together the ſofter ſubſtance of the Lungs; In the Lungs is three kinds of ſubſtance, one is a veine comming from the Liver, bringing the crude or raw part of the chile to feed the Lungs; another is <hi>arteria venalis</hi> comming from the heart, bringing with him the ſpirit of life to nouriſh him with; the third is, <hi>Trachia arteria,</hi> that bringeth in ayre to the Lungs.</p>
               <p>The Lungs is alſo divided into five Lobs, or Pellicles, viz. three on the right ſide, and two on the left; ſo that if there fell any hurt to one, the other might ſupply his Office; ſo that the Lungs as a paire of Bellows draw cold winde and refreſh the heart, change alter, and purifie the Ayre, and do receive from the heart the ſuperfluities which he putteth forth by his breathing. Behind the Lungs paſſeth <hi>Iſofagus</hi> of whom its ſpoken before, and there paſſeth alſo veins and Arteries, and all theſe with <hi>trachia arteria</hi> do make a ſtoke repleat unto the gullet, with Pannicles, ſtrong Ligaments, and <hi>glandulus</hi> fleſh to fulfill the voyd places. And laſt of all is the Midriffe, which is an officiall mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber made of two Pannicles, and Lazartus fleſh, and is placed in the midſt of the body overthwart un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the region of the ſpirituall members, parting them from the matrix; and it divideth the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als from the nutrales, and keepeth the malicious fumes from aſcending upwards to annoy the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuals
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:192126:20"/>or vitall. Next followeth the womb which is the Region of all the intrailes, and reacheth from the midriffe down to the ſhare inwardly, and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly from the reines or kidneyes downe to the bone <hi>Pecten,</hi> about the privy parts; and this wound is compound made of two things, <hi>viz</hi> of <hi>Syfac</hi> and <hi>Myrac: Syfac</hi> is a member ſpermatick, officiall, ſenſible, ſinnowy, cold and dry, and hath his beginning at the inner Pannicle of the Midriff, and it containeth and bindeth together all the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trails, defendeth the muſculus, ſo that he oppreſs not the naturall members: <hi>Myrac</hi> is compound, and made of foure things, <hi>viz</hi> of skin outwardly, of fatneſſe, of a carnous Pannicle and of muſculus fleſh, and all the whole from <hi>Syfac</hi> outward is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Myrac,</hi> and in this <hi>Myrac,</hi> or outer part of the womb, there is noted eight Muskles, two lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitudinals, proceeding from the ſhield of the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack unto <hi>os pecten,</hi> two Longitudinalls com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming from the backwards to the womb, and four tranſverſe, two whereof ſpring from the ribs on the right ſide, and go to the left ſide to the bones of the Haunches, or of <hi>pecten;</hi> and the other two ſpring from the ribs on the left, and come over the womb to the right parts. Here note, that by the muſculus longitudinall, is made perfect the virtue attractive, and by the muſculus tranſverſe, the vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue retentive, and by the muſculus latitudinall the virtue expulſive, and by the virtue attractive is
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:192126:21"/>drawn downe to the intrailes all the ſuperfluities, both water, winde, and dirt; by the virtue reten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive all things are holden and kept untill nature hath wrought his kinde; and by the vertue expul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive is put forth all things when nature provoketh any thing to be done. Now to come to the parts contained within: firſt that which appeareth next under the <hi>Syfac</hi> is <hi>omentum</hi> or <hi>Zirbus,</hi> which is a pannicle covering the ſtomack and intrails, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planted with many veins and arteries, and fatneſſe to keep moyſt the inward parts. This <hi>Zirbus</hi> is an officiall member, and is compound of a veine and an Artery, which entreth and maketh a line of the utter tunicle of the ſtomack, unto which tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicle hangeth the <hi>Zirbus</hi> and covereth all the guts down to the ſhare; next to <hi>Zirbus</hi> appeareth the intrails or guts, which convey the droſſe of the meat and drink, and cleanſe the body of their ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluities: There be ſix portions of one whole gut, which beginneth at the neither mouth of the ſtomack, and continueth to the end of the funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: nevertheleſſe he hath divers ſhapes and formes, divers operations, and divers names. And as the ſtomack hath two tunicles, ſo have all the guts two tunicles; the firſt portion of the guts is called <hi>Duodenum,</hi> he is twelve inches of length, and covereth the neither part of the ſtomack, and receiveth all the droſſe of the ſtomack: the ſecond is called <hi>Jejunium,</hi> for he is evermore empty, for
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:192126:21"/>to him lyeth the cheſt of the gall, and beateth him ſore, and draweth all the droſſe out of him, and cleanſeth him: the third is called <hi>Yleon,</hi> or ſmall gut, and is in length fifteen or ſixteen Cubits; in this gut oftentimes falleth a diſeaſe called <hi>Yleaca paſſio:</hi> the fourth gut is called <hi>Monoculus,</hi> or blind gut, and ſeemeth to have but one hole or mouth, one neare unto the other, for by the one all things go in, and by the other they go out again; the firſt is called <hi>Colon,</hi> and receiveth all the droſſe comming from all profitableneſſe, and there com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth not to him any veins miſeraices as to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: the ſixth and laſt is called <hi>rectum</hi> or <hi>longam,</hi> and endeth in the fundament, and hath in his ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther end foure muſcles, to hold, to open, to ſhut, and to put out, &amp;c. Next to be noted is <hi>Miſente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium,</hi> which is a texture of innumerable veines miſeraices, ramefied of one veine called <hi>Porta E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pates,</hi> covered and defended of pannicles and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaments comming to the intrails, with the backe full of Ligaments, and grandulus fleſh.</p>
               <p>The ſtomack is compound and ſpermatick, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowy and ſenſible, and therein is made the firſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion of Chile; for if it faile in his working, all the members of the body ſhall corrupt; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Gallen</hi> ſaith, that the ſtomack ſhould be to all the members of the body as the earth is to all that are ingendred of the earth, <hi>viz.</hi> that it ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire meat for all the body, and that it ſhould be as
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:192126:22"/>a ſack or cheſt to all the body for meat, and as a Cooke to all the members of the body; it is made of two pannicles, the inner is nervous, and the outer carnous; this inner pannicle hath muſculus longitudinals that ſtretcheth along from the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack to the mouth, whereby he draweth meat and drink to him as it were with hands; and he hath tranſverſe will to with-hold or make retenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and the outer pannicle hath latitudinall will to expulſe and put out, and by his heat helpeth the digeſtive virtue of the ſtomack, and by other heats given him of his neighbour, as the Liver on the right ſide, chaſing, and heating him with his lobs or figures, the ſpleene on the left ſide ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to him melancholly to excerciſe his appetites, and about him is the heart quickening him with his Arteries; alſo the braine, ſending to him a branch of nerves, to give him feeling; and he hath on the hinder part deſcending of the parts of the back many ligaments, with the which he is bound to the ſpondels of the back.</p>
               <p>The forme of the ſtomack is in likeneſſe of a Gourd, crooked; both holes be in the upper part of the body of it, becauſe there ſhould be no going out unadviſedly of thoſe things that be received in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it. The ſtomack is ſubject to many paſſions, and the nether mouth thereof is narrower then the upper for three cauſes. 1. Becauſe the upper receiveth meat great in ſubſtance, and there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:192126:22"/>ſine and ſubtill, paſieth eaſier into the nether, 2. By it paſſeth all the chiloſity of the meat from the ſtomack to the Liver. And 3 through him paſſeth all the droſſe of the ſtomack into the guts. And thus much for the ſtomack which is likewiſe under the ſigne <hi>Cancer,</hi> and the Bowels under <hi>Virgo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Next followeth the Liver to be ſpoken of, which is a principall member, officiall, ſpermatick, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat in quantity of bloud, of himſelfe inſenſible, but ſenſible by accidents, and in him is made the ſecond concoction; he is incloſed in a ſinnewy pannicle, and cruded, turneth the chile, that run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth from the ſtomack to the Liver, into the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of bloud. In the Liver is ingendred all nutri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall: the ſeat of the Liver is under the falſe Ribs in the right ſide; the form thereof is bunchy in the backſide, and it is ſomewhat hollow like the inſide of an hand plyable to the ſtomack as an hand is to an apple, and doth comfort the digeſtion thereof, heating the ſtomack as a fire doth a pot or Chauldron that hangeth over it: like wiſe the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver is bound with Pellicles and ſtrong Ligaments to <hi>Diafragma</hi> or the Midriffe; alſo he hath Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligaves with the ſtomack, intrails, with the heart, reigns, teſticles, and other members; and in him are ſive pellicles like ſive fingers: <hi>Gallen</hi> calleth the Liver <hi>Meſaſanguinaria</hi> and here are the places of the foure Humours, <hi>viz</hi> Bloud, or ſanguine in
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:192126:23"/>the Liver, Choller in the Gall, Melancholly in the Spleen, and Flegme in the Lungs; the watry ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluities to the Reins and theſe four humours are thus diſtributed, from the ſpermatick matter of the Liver are ingendred two great veins, the greateſt is called <hi>Porta,</hi> of whom ſpringeth the miſeraick veins, which are to <hi>vena Porta,</hi> as the branches of a tree are to the tree it ſelfe, ſome of them be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained with <hi>Duodenum,</hi> ſome with <hi>Jejunium,</hi> ſome with <hi>Yleon,</hi> ſome with <hi>Monoculus,</hi> or <hi>Saccus;</hi> and from all theſe guts they bring to <hi>vena porta</hi> the ſuccoſity of chile, going to the ſtomack, diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it to the ſubſtance of the Liver, and in theſe miſeraick, veins are begun the ſecond concoction, which is ended in the Liver So that this <hi>vena por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta,</hi> ſpreading it ſefe through the gibbous part of the Liver, meet all in one, and there maketh the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond great veine called <hi>Concava,</hi> or <hi>vena Ramoſa,</hi> and he with his branches draweth all the bloud in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendred from the Liver, and with his branches conveys it to all the members of the body, wherein is made perfect the third concoction. Now to ſpeake of the Cheſt or Gall, it is an officiall mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, ſpermatick and ſinowy, as a purſe or panni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culer veſicke, in the holowneſſe of the Liver, about the middle pericle or lob, ordained to receive the cholerick ſuperfluities ingendred in the Liver: and in the purſe or bag of the Gall are contained three holes, the firſt receiveth the Cholerick ſubſtance
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:192126:23"/>of the bloud, that the bloud be not hurt by the cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler; the ſecond ſendeth Choler to the bottome of the ſtomack to further the digeſtion; and by the third neck he ſendeth to the guts choler to cleanſe them of their ſuperfluities and droſſe; next is the Spleen, or the milt, which is ſpermatick, and is the receptacle of the melancholy ſuperfluities ingen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred in the Liver; he is placed on the left ſide tranſverſely linked to the ſtomack, he is thin of ſubſtance, and purifieth the nutritive bloud from the droſſe of melancholy.</p>
               <p>And next it is to be obſerved, that within the Region of the Nutrites, backwards, the kidneys are ordained, to cleanſe the bloud from the watry ſuperfluities, they have in each of them two paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, by the one is drawne the water from <hi>Venake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis,</hi> by two veins, called <hi>vena emulgentes,</hi> by the other the ſame water is conveyed to the bladder, and is called <hi>poros urithides.</hi> The ſubſtance of the Kidneys is <hi>Lazartus,</hi> longitudinall, placed behind on each ſide of the ſpondels, they are two in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, the right Kidney lying higher then the left, and are bound to the back with Ligaments, they are full of hard concavities, therefore the ſores of them are difficult to cure; there commeth alſo from the Heart to the Kidneys an Artery bringing with him bloud, heat, ſpirit and life; and a vein from the Liver, bringing bloud nutrimentall to nouriſh them withall.</p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:192126:24"/>
               <p>The fat of the Kidneys is made or congealed of thin bloud of gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t quantity, ſerving to temper the heat of the Kidneys, which they have by the ſharpneſſe of the Urine. And thus much ſufficeth to ſpeake of the Reins and Bowels, the one being ruled by the ſigne <hi>Libra,</hi> the other under the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion of <hi>Virgo.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> Of the Buttocks, Haunches, and Secret-Members.</head>
               <p>THeſe are the lower parts of the Womb or Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and are adjoyning to the Thighs and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Members. Herein is to be noted the parts containing, the parts contained, and the parts pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding outwards; the pacts containing are <hi>My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rac, Syfac, Zarbus,</hi> and Bones; the parts contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed are the <hi>Veſick</hi> or Bladder, the ſpermatick veſſels, the <hi>Matrix,</hi> and <hi>Vulva</hi> in Women; the <hi>Longoan,</hi> the Yard, Teſticles, or Stones and Cods in men, Nerves, Veines, and Arteries, deſcending down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, the Buttocks and Muſcles deſcending to the Thighes: of which in order.</p>
               <p>Firſt of the parts containing, as <hi>Myrac, Syfac,</hi> and <hi>Zirbus,</hi> of which it is ſpoken already; but as for the bones of the Haunches, there be of the parts
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:192126:24"/>of the back three ſpondels of <hi>oſſaſacri,</hi> or the Haun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; and three <hi>Cartaliginis</hi> ſpondels of <hi>oſſa cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dt,</hi> or the Tayle bone: Thus there is in every man thirty ſpondels, <hi>viz.</hi> in the neck ſeven, in the ridge twelve, in the reins five, in the Haunches ſix; and every ſpondell is hollow in the midſt, through which ſpondell paſſeth <hi>Nuca</hi> from the braine, or the marrow of the back, and each of theſe ſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels are bound faſt one with another, ſo that one of them may not well be named without another: And all theſe ſpondels together contained one by another, is called the ridge bone, which is the foundation of the ſhape of the body. They bee joyned to the bones of the haunches, and be the upholders of all the ſpondels; and theſe bones bee ſmall towards the Tayle bone, and broad towards the Haunches, and before they are joyned and make <hi>os pectenis,</hi> each of theſe two bones towards the Liver, hath a great round hole, into which is received the bone called <hi>vertebra,</hi> or the whirle bone: alſo beſides that place, there is a great hole or way, through which paſſeth from above muſculus veins and Arteries, and goe into the thighs. And thus of this bone <hi>Pecten,</hi> and of <hi>vertebra,</hi> is formed the Juncture of the thigh.</p>
               <p>Now concerning the parts contained, the firſt is the bladder a member officiall compound of two nervous pannicles, in complexion cold and dry;
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:192126:25"/>the neck of the bladder is carnons, and hath muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles to with-hold, and to let goe, and in man it is long, contained with the yard, paſſing through <hi>peritonium,</hi> but in women it is ſhorter, and is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained within the <hi>vulva.</hi> It is placed in men be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the bone of the ſhare and <hi>longoan,</hi> and in women between the ſaid bone and the matrix; and in it are implanted two long veſſels comming from the kidneys, called <hi>porri, urickides,</hi> bringing with them the urine or water from the kidneys to the bladder, which privily entreth into the holes of the pannicles of the bladder, by a naturall mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eing between Tunicle and Tunicle, and there the urine findeth the hole of the nether Tunicle, and there it entreth privily into the holes of the conca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity of the bladder, and the more the bladder is filled with the urine, the ſtraighter the holes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of be compriſed together: and the holes of the Tunicles be not one even againſt another, therefore if the bladder be never ſo full, there can none goe back againe: The forme of it is round, in ſome bigger, and in ſome leſſe.</p>
               <p>There is alſo two other veſſels called <hi>Vaſa ſemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaria,</hi> or the ſpermatick veſſels, and they come from <hi>Venakelis,</hi> bringing bloud to the Teſticles, aſwell in man as in women, which by the further digeſtion of the Stones or Teſticles is made Sperm or Nature: In men they be put outward, for their Teſticles hang without, and in women they be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:192126:25"/>for their Teſticles ſtand within. Next fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth the matrix in women, which is an officiall member, compound and nervous, cold and dry in complexion, it is the field of mans generation, it is an inſtrument ſuſceptive, that is receiving or taking, for as the Adamant draweth or attracteth the Iron, ſo the matrix draweth in the ſeed of man, and <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> maketh mention of a Maid that ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in a Bath where ſome ſeed of man had been ſpilt, drew it unto her and conceived thereby; her proper place is between the Bladder and <hi>Longoan,</hi> the ſimilitude or likeneſs of it, as it were a yard reverſed or turned inward, having Teſticles like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe within as aforeſaid, and is outwardly adorned with haires, in them that be of ripe age; it hath two concavities or Cells, it alſo hath a long neck like a Urinall, and in every neck it hath a mouth, one within, and another without; the inner in the time of conception is ſhut, and the outer open as it was before; it hath in the midſt a Lazartus pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicle called <hi>Tengito,</hi> wherein is two utilities, the firſt is, by it goeth forth the urine which elſe would be ſhed throughout all the <hi>vulva.</hi> 2. By it the Ayre that commeth to the matrix is altered and the heat tempered.</p>
               <p>Furthermore, in the Concavity of this neck is many involutions and pleats, joyned together in the manner of Roſe leaves, before they be fully ſpread or blowne, and they be ſhut together like a
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:192126:26"/>purſe mouth, ſo that nothing may paſſe forth but urine untill the time of Childing. Alſo about the middle of this purſe be certaine veins in maidens which in time of deflowring be corrupted and bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and theſe are called the Tokens of Virginity. Furthermore in the ſides of the outer mouth, are two Teſticles or ſtones, and two veſſels of ſperme, ſhorter then mans veſſels, and in time of Coyt or copulation, the womans ſperme is ſhed down in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the bottome of the matrix, alſo from the Liver there commeth to the matrix many veins, bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nutriment to the child, when a woman is with child, and thoſe veines, when the matrix is voyd, bring thereto ſuperfluities from certain members of the body, whereof are ingendred wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens flowers, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Now in the matrix, which is the field of gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, is ſowne by the tillage of man, a convena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble matter of kindly heat, which ſeed of genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion commeth from all parts of the body, both of man and woman, with the conſent of all the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, and is ſhed in the place of conceiving, and by the vertue of nature, is gathered together in the Cels of the matrix, in whom by the working of the mans ſeed, and by the ſuffering of the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans ſeed mixt together, is ingendred <hi>Embryon.</hi> And further it is to be noted, that this ſperme that commeth both to man and woman, is made of the moſt pure drops of bloud in all the body, and by <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:192126:26"/>
               <p>The Cods is a compound member, and officiall, and as a purſe ordained for the cuſtody and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of the ſtones, and other ſpermatick veſſells, it is made of two parts, the inner and the outer, the outer is compound made of skin and Lazartus, lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitudinall and tranſverſall, as the Myrach, the inner part of the Cods is of the ſubſtance as the <hi>Syfac,</hi> and in ſimilitude as two pockets drawn together, they differ not from the <hi>Syfac;</hi> and there be two, if there fall any hurt to the one, the other ſhould ſerve; the ſtones be two, made of glandulus or carnelly fleſh, and through the <hi>Didimus</hi> commeth from the braine to the ſtones ſinnewes, and from the heart Arteries, and from the Liver veins, which bringeth unto them both feeling and ſtirring life and ſpirit, and nutrimentall bloud, and the pureſt bloud of all other members of the body, whereof is made the ſperme, by the labour of the Teſticles or ſtones <hi>ut ſupra.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The groyns be the emy Junctures, or purging places unto the Liver, and they have carnelly fleſh in the plying or bowing of the thighs.</p>
               <p>The hips have great brawny fleſh on them, and from thence deſcend downwards Brawns, Cords, and Ligaments, moving and binding together the thighes with the Buttocks or hanches themſelves.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:192126:27"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> Of the Thighes, Legs, and Feet.</head>
               <p>THe thigh or <hi>Coxa</hi> is contained from the joynt of the haunch unto the knee; the leg reacheth from the knee to the ankle, and is called <hi>Tibia;</hi> &amp; the foot from the ankle unto the end of the toes; the Thigh, Leg, and Foot are compound, made as the arme and hand, with skin, fleſh, veines, arte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, ſinnews, brawns, tendons, and cords, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of in order.</p>
               <p>Of the skin and fleſh it's ſpoken of before; and as of veins and arteries, in their deſcending down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, at the laſt ſpondels they be divided into 2 parts, whereof the one part goeth into the right thigh, and the other into the left, and when they come to the thigh, they be divided into two parts, or branches; one of them ſpreadeth into the inner ſide of the leg, and the other into the outer ſide, and ſo branching deſcend down to the Leg, Ankles, and Feet, and be brought into foure veines, which be commonly uſed in bloud letting, as hereafter followeth; one of them is under the under Ankle towards the heele, called <hi>Soffeua;</hi> another under the under Ankle, and is called <hi>Sia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rica,</hi> and another under the ham, called <hi>Poplitica;</hi> the fourth betweene the little Toe and the next, called <hi>Renalis.</hi> The ſinnewes ſpring of the laſt ſpondel, and of <hi>Os ſacrum,</hi> and paſſeth through
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:192126:27"/>the hole of the bone of the hip, and deſcendeth to the brawnes, and moveth the knee and the ham, and theſe deſcend downe to the Ankle, and move the foote, and the brawnes of the foote moove the toes, as is declared in the bones of the hand; the thigh bone, or <hi>Coxa,</hi> is without a fellow, and full of marrow, and round at either end; the roundneſſe at upper end is called <hi>Verte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brum,</hi> or whirlbone, and boweth inwards, and is received into the box or hole of the haunch bone, and at the knee he hath two rounds, which he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveth into the Concavities of the bones of the leg, at the knee, called the great foſſels.</p>
               <p>There is alſo at the knee a round bone, called the knee pan; then followeth the leg, wherein is two bones called <hi>focile major</hi> and <hi>focile minor,</hi> the bigger of them paſſeth before, and is called the ſhin bone, and paſſeth downe making the inward ankle; the leſſe paſſeth from the knee backwards, and deſcendeth downe to the outer ank'e, and there formeth that ankle.</p>
               <p>The bones of the foot are ſix and twenty; firſt next the ankle bone is one called <hi>Orabaliſtus;</hi> next under that towards the heele, is one called <hi>Calca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny:</hi> and betweene them is another bone, called <hi>Os neculare;</hi> in the ſecond ward there bee foure bones called <hi>Raccti,</hi> as bee in the hands: In the third and fourth wards be fourteene, called <hi>Digi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tori,</hi> and five called <hi>Pectens,</hi> at the extremity of the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:192126:28"/>Toes, next to the nailes: And thus be there in the foot 26 bones, with the leg from the ankle to the knee; 2 in the knee, and one round and flat bone, and in the thigh one; in the whole, thigh, leg, and foot, thirty bones: Thus are we marvelouſly and curiouſly wrought in the nethermoſt parts of the earth.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="recipes_and_secrets">
            <head>Choyce and ſelect Receipts and Secrets for all manner of Diſeaſes, Gun-ſhot, and preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatives againſt the Plague.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>What Wounds are.</head>
               <p>WOunds are in Latine called <hi>Vulnera,</hi> and of the Vulgar, <hi>Vulner:</hi> They are ſimple and compound; the ſimple are thoſe that are onely in the fleſh; the compound are thoſe where are cut ſinnews, veins, muſcles, and bones; and theſe are of divers and ſundry kindes, and the difference a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them is by the variety of the place where they are, and the difference of the weapon where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they are hurt; for ſome go right, ſome over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thwart that offend divers places of the body: the ſimple are of ſmall importance, if they keep them cleane and cloſe ſhut, nature will heale them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:192126:28"/>any kind of medicine; but thoſe where veins are cut require Art, wherewith they muſt ſtop the bloud, and not ſuffer the wound to remain o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, but ſow it up very cloſe, ſo that the vein may heale; and thoſe where ſinnews are cut or hurt are of great importance, and ſhould be healed with great ſpeed, ſo the ſinnews may joyne with more eaſe: but thoſe where bones be hurt are of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt importance; for if the bone be ſeparated from the other, it muſt be taken away before the wound can be healed. And thus much for what wounds are, and their kindes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Syncope paſſion, or ſwounding through the cauſe of wounds.</head>
               <p>GALEN ſaith, that Syncope is a ſudden decay of ſtrength, through immoderate evacuation, and vehement dolour, continuall watching and paine, intemperateneſſe of the principall parts, or vehement perturbations of the minde; but Syn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cope which followeth in wounds ſpringeth of great effuſion of bloud, or elſe of vehement dolour, and paine; the comming of it is perceived by the weakneſſe, pulſe, palenefle of face, cold ſweats a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the neck and temples; it is not lightly to be regarded becauſe it commeth ſuddenly, and as the image of death, therefore the wounded man is to be comforted by all means poſſible; if you per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:192126:29"/>this accident come, give the Patient a piece of fine white bread, dipped in the beſt Wine you can get, into which Wine put Roſe-water &amp; <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Chriſti,</hi> and Burrage water, and give him of the Wine to drink, and comfort him with ſweet ſmels, and chafe his temples with Roſe-water, and if he begin to ſwound, caſt cold water on his face, chafe and rub his temples with your bands, and pull him by the noſe, thereby to revive and quicken his ſpirits.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Luxation, or Diſlocation, and their differences.</head>
               <p>LUxation is a going out of a joynt from a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall or proper place, whereby the voluntary motion thereof is hindred; there be two diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences of luxations, according to the bigneſs ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; for if the bone be quite out of his ſocket or place, then it is properly called a Luxation: but if it be onely a little removed, then it is named a wrench. A joynt may be foure manner of wayes diſlocated or wrenched, <hi>viz.</hi> forwards, back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, higher, and lower: now to reduce them to their proper places, there are foure intentions to be obſerved, the firſt to bring the joynt to his naturall priſtine place: the ſecond is the conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation and keeping the joynt ſo put in, that it ſlip not out againe: the third to defend the member
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:192126:29"/>from accidents, as dolour, inflammations, flux of humours, and the like: the fourth to put away thoſe accidents if any do follow.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How the luxated joynt is to be reduced to his naturall and proper place.</head>
               <p>FIrſt extend the member decently, untill ſuch time as the place betwixt both bones is empty and void, then the bone which is out of his place is to be put and placed in his native ſeat, that the emptines of the ſocket may be filled againe with the bone; this extenſion muſt be done tenderly, with as little paine as poſſible; neither is there one way onely of extending and ſtretching out the luxated member, for ſometime it may be done with the hands onely, ſometime with bands, and ſometime with Inſtruments apt and fit for that purpoſe, as appeareth in <hi>Hypocrates lib. de luxatis &amp; fractis.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How the member brought to his naturall place, may be conſerved in the ſame.</head>
               <p>VVHen the member is brought to his natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall place, you muſt with all diligence labour to confirme the part, and keep the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber from ſlipping out againe; therefore annoynt the place with oyle of Roſes, and apply unto it a
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:192126:30"/>fine old linnen cloath wet in oyle of Roſes, alſo uſe cloaths wet in the whites of Egges, and apply them to the joynt; wet your rollers in water and vinegar mixed together, and roll the member therewith, and if neceſſity require, uſe ſplints of Leather, or paſted paper, and apply them about the joynt; but be carefull the part be not too hard rolled, for feare of inflamation; lay the member in his naturall figure, and unleſſe ſome great and ill accident happen, open not the member before the tenth day at the leaſt; uſe not hot cloathes or medicines for feare of inflammation, but rather ſome refrigerative cerate: and labour to defend the member from a flux of humours, by ſtrengthening it with apt and convenient medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines hereafter mentioned, keeping the Patient to thin and ſmall diet purging and letting bloud if need require.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Cure of broken and fractured bones.</head>
               <p>TO the uniting of every fracture is required foure things, firſt the joyning or putting to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether of the broken bones into their proper place: Secondly, to keep and conſerve them ſo placed without motion: The third is to conglutinate and joyne together the parts of the broken bone by ingendring of <hi>Callus:</hi> Fourthly to correct thoſe
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:192126:30"/>accidents which follow the fractures of bones: firſt to unite the fractured bones, if the member where the bone is fractured doth extend it ſelfe and ſtand upwards, &amp; pricketh, ſhewing an inequality when it is touched: theſe be ſure ſigns that the bone bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken is out of his natural place; wherfore the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber is decently to be extended, &amp; that part of the bone that is depreſſed to be gently lifted up, and that which ſtandeth upward to be put downe, untill the ends of the fractured bones do meet, and bee united, and brought to their naturall proper place; but it is not poſſible this can be done without ſome force and ſtrength; ſo that if the member be ſmall, and of no great ſtrength, as the finger or other like member, one man may well ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend it, and ſtretch it out, by applying one hand on the one part, and the other hand on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, untill both ends of the bone fractured doe meet and joyne together: but if the member be great, having ſtrong nerves, and tendons, then one man is not ſufficient, and you muſt diligently take heed, that the member be not too immoderately extended or drawne out, for that doth bring vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment paine, and conſequently Feavers, Convul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, Palſey, and ſuch diſeaſes, and oftentimes by this means the Fiberes and threads in the heads of the muſcles be broken: therefore let one man lay his hands on the member above the fracture, and the other on the nether part of the member
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:192126:31"/>under the fractured bone, ſo ſtretch and extend the member, till both parts of the bone do meet, then forme it together, till you bring it to its na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall forme and figure, and when the bone is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in his place, then ſhall the Patient feel eaſe of his paine.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To keep the bones that they fall not out againe.</head>
               <p>THe broken bone being thus reduced, and brought to his proper figure, the next thing to be obſerved is to keep in the ſame that it ſtart not out againe; therefore all means poſſible are to be uſed to keep the members without motion, and to uſe apt and convenient ligature and rolling: But before you roll the member, firſt mix the white of an Egge and oyle of Roſes together; and wet therein a ſoft linnen cloath of ſuch bigneſſe as may compaſſe not only the place where the bone is fractured, but alſo ſomewhat of the ſound parts above and below. Then this being applied to the affected part, you ſhall binde and roll the member, diligently regarding that you compreſs not the member, by too hard rolling, ſo that nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment cannot come to it, and alſo paine there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by may cauſe flux of humours and inflamation; neither muſt you binde it to flack and looſe, for then the broken bones will ſeparate againe, and
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:192126:31"/>go aſunder; but obſerve a meane herein, that you binde not the member too ſtreight, nor too looſe, but follow diſcretion between both, and the fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the patient; and as touching your rollers, you muſt have 2 made of ſoft cloth, whoſe breadth and latitude muſt be ſuch, as in rolling there be no looſeneſſe, wideneſſe and plaites. The beginning of the rolling muſt be upon the Fracture, and ſo rolled about three or foure times, and then rolling upward untill you come to the ſound parts, which muſt alſo be ſomewhat rolled; by this means the bones united ſhall more firmely remaine together, and the flux of humours be ſtayed that they cannot come to the affected part.</p>
               <p>The beginning of the ſecond roll muſt alſo bee upon the fractured place, going alſo three or four times about it, and ſo continuing downwards, untill you have compaſſed the ſound parts: which done, you muſt with the ſame roller aſcend up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards againe, untill you come ſome what above the firſt roller, therefore the ſecond roller muſt be halfe as long againe as the firſt, which ſuffereth not any flux of humours to infeſt, or annoy the part affected.</p>
               <p>Theſe rollers ſhould be wet in water and Wine mixed together before you uſe them, and if there be any vehement paine or inflamation, then the member ſhould be wrapped about with fine wool well carded, or elſe with ſtuffes well in <hi>exicratum;</hi>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:192126:32"/>And the ligature or binding muſt not be hard, but ſuch as may keep the united bones together; fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore there muſt bee uſed both to defend the member from accidents, to keep it together, and to confirm and conſolidate the ſame certaine plaiſters or cerats, which muſt be put upon the two rollers, and as it were the third ligature or roll, amongſt which is uſed <hi>Ceratum Humidum,</hi> made of Wax melted in oyle of Roſes, but if there be beſides the fractured bone any ſolution or hurt in the fleſh, then uſe not either Cerote or oyle, for that will make the ulcer filthy and ſtinking, but inſtead thereof uſe Plumaciols that be long, dipt in red and ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ck wine.</p>
               <p>Now the better to keep the member, placed in his naturall place from dolour and paine, there muſt be uſed certaine ſplints, to be put about the ligature at the firſt dreſſing: theſe ſplints muſt be equall, ſmooth, even; not crooked, or rugged, and in the midſt thicker then in the other parts, the better to ſtrengthen the member where the bone is fractured: the way of applying theſe ſplints is thus, there muſt be cloathes three or four fold dipt in Roſe-water, and lavd upon the roller according as the member requireth, then the ſplint involved and wound about with wooll, cotten muſt be placed round about the member, a fingers breadth aſunder, and binde them mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately and gently, that you compreſſe not the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:192126:32"/>member, and take heed that none of the ſplints touch any joynt, if any be neare the fractured bone, for that will make ulceration, and inflammation in the the ſame joynt. Therefore if the fracture be neare to any joynt, you muſt in that place make your ſplints ſhorter, ſmaller, and lighter, and if no dolour, inflammation, itching, nor ulceration commeth to the fractured part, then you may let the ſplints remaine on till the 12 or 15 day or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the 20 day, but if any of theſe happen, then you muſt unrole the member the third day, and foment it with luke warme water, whereby the paine is ceaſed and the itching put away.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To Conglutinate and Joyne together the fractured bones.</head>
               <p>THe fractured bones being thus put in their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall places, out of the bone muſt grow the nouriſhment to Conglutinate and cauſe them to grow together; and this is called <hi>Callus</hi> which like glew doth Cement them together: wherefore ought to be made grow, by all meanes poſſible. This <hi>Callus</hi> is ingendred of Groſſe and Earthly parts, for ſuch is the nouriſhment of the bones. After the minde of divers it beginneth to grow about the tenth or fourteenth day, when it bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to grow you ſhall perceive by theſe ſignes. The dolour and paine is aſlwaged; the inflammati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:192126:33"/>ceaſeth: and the tumor vaniſheth, and the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber cometh againe to it's naturall colour. Now the principall way to ingender <hi>Callus</hi> is apt and convenient diet, at the beginning of the Fracture <hi>Hippcerates</hi> counſelleth to uſe thinne and ſlender diet, to obſtaine from fleſh and Wine the ſpace of ten dayes. But when ye come to ingender <hi>Callus,</hi> you muſt licence the patient to uſe a more large di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et, and meates that make good juice, and that groſſ and ſomewhat viſcous. Therefore Frumenty is much commended; alſo the heads &amp; feet of beaſts, which nouriſh and bee of viſcous Iuice. Alſo give him to drinke good red wine when he goeth to meate, but that muſt be taken moderately: the big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of <hi>Callus</hi> muſt not be either bigger or leſſer then is requiſite, for being bigger it bringeth paine to the muskels, and if it be leſſer it is una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to defend the fractured bones. How to keep it that it be not too bigge not too little followeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To remove the accidents which may happen to fractured bones.</head>
               <p>THe accidents hindring the cure of the Fractu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red member, for the moſt part are extreame paine, inflamation, itching in a wound, immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate drynes or moyſture, <hi>Gangrena,</hi> hardneſſe, and the quantity of <hi>Callus</hi> too much, or little. Theſe bee the cheife enemies that hinder natures worke
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:192126:33"/>Therefore if theſe accidents doe infeſt and beſeige the Fractured member, after it be bound, rolled and dreſt, you muſt with ſpeed looſe the Ligature and take away the roller, and then the member being bare and naked, foment it with the Oyle of Roſes, vinegar, and other medicines mentioned be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and doe not uſe againe either ligature or ſplints before the paine bee aſſwaged and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flammation ceaſed, but onely to ſtrengthen and keepe the member together; but theſe accidents being expelled, then uſe ſplints and roling, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and if this itching happeneth, then foment the place with water temperately hot, and apply to it <hi>Vnguentum Album</hi> or <hi>Vnguentum Populeon,</hi> and binde the member as aforeſaid. Further if there happen to the member any wound either at the breaking of the bone; or elſe made by the <hi>Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgeon</hi> to take out the ſhivers of the bone mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſting the muſkels: or if there be any flux of bloud you muſt labour to ſtaunch it with convenient re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies, as are herein ſet forth, if any inflammation follow, it muſt be repelled if the fleſh be broken and contuſed, then ſacrifie the parts for feare leaſt <hi>Gangrena</hi> ſhould follow, which if it ſhould or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny putrefaction, you muſt endeavor to cure it as is ſet out in the enſuing medicines; and if none of theſe happen, then uſe the like medicine to the cure of the wound as you do to freſh and greene wounds. Further if the wound bee immoderately dry whereby the growing of <hi>Callus</hi> is hindred,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:192126:34"/>ſhall be convenient the third or fourth day to fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the place with water: and when as the fleſh doth riſe in a tumour, then ceaſe the fomentation unleſſe it be to evaporate and digeſt the multitude of matter, then ceaſe not till the tumor goeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way; and if moiſtneſſe follow in the fractured member and hinder the ingendring of <hi>Callus</hi> you ſhall put it away by convenient ligature and ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and moderate exſiccation, now that the <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> may be ingendred of convenient ſubſtance, neither too big nor too ſmall; you muſt take heed to the diet, fomentation, and plaiſters; if you would increaſe it, uſe plaiſters which doe moderately heale, but if it be too big then uſe me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines aſtringent, and a compreſſing ligature and plate of leade alſo fomentations made with oyle ſalt-peter, and ſalt water made hot. But if the <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> be not growne at the accuſtomed time which appeareth if the member affected be leaner, ſmaller and ſlenderer then it was naturally; then you muſt apply unto the member hott atractive medecinet let the Patients diet be more large, and cauſe him to embrace mirth, and bamſh heavyneſſe, and ſuch paſſions of the minde as may bring the body into a melar cholick diſpoſition. And thus much touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing broken or fractured bones, luxations and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>located joynts.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:192126:34"/>
               <head>A ſecret powder to ſtay the flux of bloud in a wound.</head>
               <p>℞ <hi>Aluminis Succarini, Thuris, Arſenici,</hi> ana ℥ j. <hi>Calcis vini</hi> ℥ vj.</p>
               <p>Make them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in fine powder, and put unto them one pinte of ſtrong vinegar, and boyle them on the fire, ſtirring it, till the vinegar be conſumed, then ſet it in an oven, or in the Sun, till it be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly dry, then make it in powder, and when you will uſe it, take of this powder three ounces, Bolear moniack halfe an ounce, <hi>Pulvis Alcami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticus</hi> one ounce; mix all theſe together, and make them into very fine powder: and thus you have the powder prepared and ſublimed to reſtrain any flux of bloud, when you uſe it, take 4 ounces of this powder, and incorporate it with whites of Egs; then make a boulſter or ſtuffe of Tow as large as the end of the member you take off, or place where the wound is; dip the Tow firſt in vinegar, and preſſe it out againe, then ſpread your medicine on the Tow, and after ſtrow a little of this dry powder upon it, and ſo make many little bolſters of Tow, to lay upon this, as need doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire for to reſtraine bloud.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:192126:35"/>
               <head>Of Wounds made with Gunſhot.</head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>1.</hi> That the uſuall Gunpowder is not venemous.</head>
               <p>COncerning the nature of Gunpowder, many have affirmed it to be venemous, and ſo conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently the wounds made with powder muſt have the cure of venemous wounds; I doe not deny but there may be Gunpowder venemous, but the uſuall powder is not, and that I ſhall ſhew, for it is made of Zulphur, Saltpeter, and Coale, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of which are venemous; ſo that if the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples be not venemous in themſelves, neither can the compound be ſo: <hi>Dioſcorides</hi> writing of Zulphur, ſaith that Zulphur doth heat, diſſolve, and concoct ſpeedily; it is good againſt the cough and ſhort breath, taken in an Egge, or uſing the fume of it; it taketh away leproſie and ſcabs, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing tempered with vinegar, and healeth the itch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the body; theſe be the words of <hi>Dioſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rides</hi> touching Zulphur: Of Nitre he ſaith (which is Saltpeter) it hath the ſtrength and uſtion of Salt; it helpeth the Collick, if it be taken with Commine in hydromell, or new wine boyled, or any thing that doth breake winde, as Rue or Dill; it is mixed with Emplaiſters, which do extract &amp; diſſolve; it doth extenuate and put away the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proſie,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:192126:35"/>uſed with warm water or Wine, it opens fellons mixed with ℞ozen, or Turpentine. <hi>Galen</hi> ſaith, all kindes of Zulphur are hot, and do reſiſt the venome of poyſonous Beaſts, being uſed with old Oyle, Honey, and Turpentine. Or Nitre, or Saltpeter he ſaith, it is a meane between Aphro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitum and Salt, it doth dry and digeſt, and being taken inwardly, it doth cut and extenuate groſſe and ſlimy humours more then Salt: Aphronitrum (unleſs great neceſſity doth enforce it) is not to be taken inwardly, becauſe it hurteth the ſtomack, and doth extenuate more then Nitrum, therefore both <hi>Dioſcorides</hi> and <hi>Galen</hi> found Zulphure and Nitre ſo far from any venemous quality, as they uſed them as approved and excellent medicines againſt venome. So that unleſſe any will be ſo ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous as to affirme the Cole to be venemous, the ſimples entring into the compoſition cannot make the powder venemous.</p>
               <p>And many times, Gunpowder inſtead of other medicines hath been uſed in wounds to dry and exſiccate, to the great comfort of the Patient; and therefore it is not in mixture or compoſition vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous but medicinable, and hath in him the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues obſterſive and deſiccative, neither in thoſe that are ſhot with this powder doe there follow any of thoſe Accidents which are inſeperable in venemous ſhot; and the cure of theſe wounds a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greath with thoſe that be contuſed or broken,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:192126:36"/>without the Addition of any medecine or <hi>Alexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pharmacon</hi> againſt venom, and are to be numbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red amongſt greene wounds, ſuch as are carled bruiſed, Contuſed, or Cruſhed wounds. And now to the Generall cure of wounds made with Gunſhot.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of healing wounds made with Gunſhot.</head>
               <p>TO the cure of ſuch wounds properly belong two things; the one is to deliver and cleanſe the wound of all ſuch things as are not agreeable to nature, which are not onely ſhot, iron ſplints or ſhivers of wood, cloth, duſt, oyle, or ſuch like, but alſo the clods of bloud, matter, bruiſed fleſh, and ſuch like, which you ſhall endeavour to take out with inſtruments for that purpoſe, or if the wound be ſo narrow that it cannot be taken out with an inſtrument, then you muſt labour to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large the wound either with tents, as the roote of <hi>Gantian</hi> pith of elder, or a peece of ſponge, or if otherwiſe then to make inciſion with a paire of Caſsers or ſheeres made for that purpoſe; there are alſo divers inſtruments when the wound is enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to take out ſuch things, as Tongs, Nippers, Terrebils, Crowbills, which a Chyrurgeon muſt alwayes be furniſhed with. Then to endeavour to cute the wound as you would a bruiſed, cruſhed, or contuſed wound, and to take away the bruiſed
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:192126:36"/>aſmuch expedition as poſſible with conveniency, without ſharpe and biting medecines, therefore you ſhall lay to the contuſed place, or wound of <hi>Mercury precipitaete drachme</hi> 1. or as much as you ſhall ſee cauſe, and mixe it with ſimple oyle, oyl of Roſes, butter, or freſh Barrowes greaſe, and droppe into the wound one droppe of this oyle following.</p>
               <p>℞. <hi>Refinae abjectinae</hi> ℥ v. <hi>Olei roſarei</hi> ℥ ij. <hi>ſena: Hypericouis</hi> v. drachms, <hi>ſem. Momoraicae,</hi> iii. drachms.</p>
               <p>The ſeeds muſt be bruiſed and put in a double veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell with the oyles, and let them boyle halfe an houre, then ſtraine them and keepe them to thy uſe. This oyle doth concoct and digeſt and preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth the ſound fleſh from corruption and putre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>A plaiſter good to extract ſuch things as are fixed in wounds.</head>
               <p> 
                  <hi>℞.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>Apoſtolicon deſcript. Nicholai <hi>4 ounces,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Magnetis orientaelis <hi>2 ounces.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <item>Pelipodij.</item>
                           <item>Dictamialbi</item>
                        </list> ana <hi>halfe an ounce.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Pinguedinis leporinae <hi>2 ounces.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Olei canabis <hi>1 ounce.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Terebinthinae</hi> halfe an ounce.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Of theſe make an Emplaiſter which is marvelous
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:192126:37"/>drawing our rotten bones, thornes, or the like.</p>
               <p>But in poyſoned ſhots, the medicines before re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſed, are not ſufficient, butyon muſt give the Patient ſome Antidote or <hi>Alexipharmacon</hi> againſt venom or poyſon both inwardly and outwardly: inwardly you ſhall give him every day this poti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>℞.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item> Vini cretiei, Sublimatae rutae ana ℥ <hi>4</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <item>Tormentillaei</item>
                           <item>Dictami </item>
                        </list>ana <hi>2.</hi> drachms.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Theriacae opt.</hi> 1. <hi>drachme,</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list> let them be boyled till a 3. part be conſumed, ſo reſerve them for vſe.</p>
               <p>Outwardly, into the wound you ſhall put oyle of violets warme, which oyle muſt be made of Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeede oyle; you may alſo wet your tent in that oile, and mixe it with your other medecines that you apply to the wound.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To cure a ſimple wound in the head made with gunſhot.</head>
               <p>Firſt conſider whether the wound be ſimple or compound, if the wound be ſimple, the cure is eaſier and without danger if the patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t have not a body repleat with evill juice or have taſted of that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tagion called <hi>morbus gallicus,</hi> if the woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded patient be ſo affected, though the wound be ſmall &amp; ſimple, yet trifling wounds in ſuch bodies are not cured
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:192126:37"/>without much diligence; wherfore in ſuch bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies you muſt labour to cleanſe the body thereof by bloud letting, purging, by ſweating, and good diet, ſo that the body being rectified, the cure of the wounds ſhall be the more ſpeedy and eaſie.</p>
               <p>Now to the cure of ſimple wounds in the head.</p>
               <p>Firſt let the haire be ſhaven round about, and apply this unguent following.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>℞.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item> Precipitati optimi <hi>2. drachms</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <item>Butiri ſalis experti,</item>
                           <item>Oleireſarum</item>
                        </list>ana <hi>drach. 1.</hi> ſs.</item>
                     <item>Croci <hi>2.</hi> graines.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Mixe theſe and make an unguent, which you ſhall lay on ſoft linnen cloth and apply to the wound, lay on the wound alſo <hi>Bolus armenius,</hi> tempered with oyle of Roſes and the white of an egge like an unguent to defend the parts from ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents.</p>
               <p>And this ſhall ſuffice for the firſt day: you may alſo at the beginning uſe in ſtead of the ſecond un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guent this comfortable cataplaſme following;</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>℞.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <item>Olei myrtillorum</item>
                           <item>Roſarum</item>
                        </list> ana. ℥ <hi>ij</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <item>Banlaſtiaum</item>
                           <item>Roſarum rub:</item>
                           <item>Boli armeni.</item>
                        </list>ana ℥ <hi>1</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Sanguis draeconis <hi>1. drachm.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Mirrhe <hi>halfe a drachme.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:192126:38"/>
               <p>Make of all this a Cataplaſme according to Art and apply it the ſecond day you ſhall uſe ſuch me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines that doth digeſt and moderately dry the wound, of which ſort this is one.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>℞.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>Terebinthinae lotae <hi>1. ounce,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Mellis roſarum <hi>2 ounces.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Butiri ſalis experti <hi>3 drachms.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <item>Farinae hordei,</item>
                           <item>Ariſtolochiae rotundae</item>
                           <item>Radicis ireos</item>
                        </list>ana <hi>1. drachme.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Aloes <hi>halfe a drachme</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Mixe theſe and make them in an unguent and uſe it untill ſuch time as there appeare ſignes of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction in the wound; then uſe no more butter in the wound but this powder following.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>℞.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item> Sarcocollae <hi>1. drachme</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Cocticum radicis papaver is <hi>halfe a drachme</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <item>Farrinae orobi</item>
                           <item>Mirrhe</item>
                        </list>ana <hi>drachme 1</hi> ſſ</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Make this in powder and temper it with the other unguent, and uſe this untill the wound be perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cured; and this is the cure of a ſimple wound in the head.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>Of wounds compound in the head through ſhot.</head>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:192126:38"/>
               <p>IN the cure of compound wounds of the head you muſt firſt uſe inſition; with ſome inſtrument ſharpe and flat raiſe the ſkinne and fleſh from cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium, and if you ſee any ſhort or peece of bone, which may eaſily be taken out, you may do it with ſome convenient inſtrument; but if it will not bee without dificulty, then wett your ſtuffs in aſtrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent wine, and vinegar mixt with <hi>Bole armonicke</hi> and <hi>Sanguis araconis,</hi> and lay it to the wound; then the next day following uſe this receipt for 3. or foure dayes, for feare of inflammation to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>℞.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>Boli armeni <hi>2. ounces.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Albumem ovorum <hi>2. ounces</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Olei Reſacei omphacitis <hi>3 ounces</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Croci <hi>3 graines</hi> miſce.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Then you may uſe this digeſtive following, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the thing fixed will eaſily be taken out.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>℞.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>Terebinthinae lotae in vixo <hi>3. ounces,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Ovorum vitella <hi>2.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Olei roſati ℥ ij</item>
                     <item>Alloes <hi>2</hi> ſcruples ij</item>
                     <item>Croci <hi>4</hi> graines miſce <hi>ſ: A.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <p>IN other things it differeth not from the cure of ſimple wounds, But if any veine under <hi>Crani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um</hi> bee broken, and maketh effuſion of bloud, or if <hi>dur a mater,</hi> or <hi>Pia mater</hi> be rent or torne, if <hi>Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium</hi>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:192126:39"/>be bruiſed, and thereby the braine ſuffer, you muſt with all expedition ſet a trapan on <hi>Cranium</hi> and give the wound vent, and take out the bloud and matter or what elſe doth depreſſe the braine, and when you are conſtrained hereunto, make tents of cotten or lint, and put into the Patients eares, and command a man to compreſſ with his hands the patients eares, leaſt the noiſe make him too much affraid and faint harted and dippe your tents in ſtipticke wine or oyle of Roſes. And wet ſtuffs in oyle of Roſes and lay them on the place, and lay upon the ſame cloth bole <hi>Armonick</hi> mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the white of an egge and apply it to the wound to prevent inflammation; and if there fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth any corruption to any part of the braine then uſe <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nguentum Egiptiasum</hi> which is moſt excellent in this caſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>Of wounds in the breaſt with gunſhot.</head>
               <p>ALthough the wounds in all parts of the body are all one in effect yet they differ in the cure according to the place wounded. Therefore if a wound be in the breſt and pearſe not through, you may cure it like other wounds and the firſt two dayes <hi>Vnguentum ex precipate,</hi> or ſome other of the like effect, alſo uſe ſome medicines which wil gently exicate and mundifie as <hi>mell roſarum ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plex,</hi>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:192126:39"/>And after the fourth or fift day uſe <hi>abſterſive</hi> me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines make after this manner.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>R.</hi> 
                  <list>
                     <item>Mellis roſarum <hi>1. ounce</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <item>Terebinthinae</item>
                           <item>Butirirecentis</item>
                        </list>ana <hi>2 drachmes.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <item>Farine berdei'</item>
                           <item>Ariſtolochiae rotundae</item>
                        </list>ana <hi>1 drachme</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Mix theſe together and dip your tents in them, but on the wound lay this medicine following.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>℞.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>Album vnius ovi</item>
                     <item>Olei roſati <hi>1 Ounce.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Boli Armeni <hi>1 ounce. and halfe miſce.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>The reſt of the cure of theſe wounds doe not dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer from other wounds.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>Of wounds with gunſhot in the belly.</head>
               <p>WOunds in the belly or flank that peirce not through &amp; hurt not the ſpine of the back, are cured as ſimpie wounds in the fleſh, but if the ſhot have peirced through the belly and wounded either the ſtomack, Liver, ſpleene, kidneys, inteſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines, bladder, or any of the great veynes or arte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, then there is no hope of life to be looked for; but if the ſhot have pierced the belly, and yet wounded none of the forenamed members; then the shot
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:192126:40"/>being taken out there is ſome hopes of recovery.</p>
               <p>Therefore you muſt labour to take out the ſhot with a probe fit for that uſe, but if you cannot without much labour doe it, it is better that it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine within, then to provoke mortall accidents, by laboring to take it out; for the wound may bee very well cured, and the bullet remaine within: And if blood bruiſed or matter be in the belly, uſe wine warmed and make injections, and uſe this incarnative following.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>℞.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <item>Thuris</item>
                           <item>Alloes</item>
                           <item>Farinae hordei</item>
                        </list>ana <hi>1 drachme</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <item>Terebinthinae</item>
                           <item>Millis.</item>
                           <item>Succi myriophili</item>
                        </list>ana <hi>2 drachms.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Mixe the flower with the juice, and diſſolve and melt the honey and the turpentine at the fire; then put altogether, and make an unguent: with this ſpread your plaiſters and dip your tents in; and when the fleſh doth grow and the wounds fill, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply ſuch medicines as be aſtringent, and that doe dry: and if need be open a veine in the arme, and alwayes keep the belly folluble.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:192126:40"/>
               <head>Of wounds in the legs and armes made with gunſhot.</head>
               <p>THe cure is after the method ſet out before, firſt with your probe ſearch out the ſhot, and with your crowbill take it out; but if the ſhot cannot eaſily be found, then proceede on to the cure of the wound and let it remaine within; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtill and power into the wound the unguent made with butter, <hi>precipitate</hi> and <hi>Egyptiacum,</hi> and let it peirce into the wound, then make tents and dip them in the ſame, and put them into the <hi>Orifices</hi> of the wound, and when the wounde is well mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dified, uſe ſome incarnative, as this following.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>R</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>Terebinthine, <hi>2. ouces</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Mellis <hi>1. ounce.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <item>Alloes</item>
                           <item>Thuris</item>
                           <item>Farinae hordei</item>
                        </list>ana <hi>1. drachme,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Ariſtolochiae, <hi>halfe a drachme.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>And you muſt have a care that you make your tents dayly ſhorter and leſſer, as the wound heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth; but if through the violence of the ſhot, any bones be fractured and broke, then you muſt uſe a double cure: Firſt, you muſt labour to take out the ſhot, next to remove the contuſed and broken fleſh, and to procure the generation of new, and then you muſt come to the unition of the fractu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:192126:41"/>bones, and keep the ſame without motion, as is ſet out before in the cure of fractured bones and diſlocations, ſaving that you ſhall not uſe ſuch li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatures and ſplints in this kind of wounds, but uſe an inſtrument to lay the fractured arme or lege in, and cover the member with ſoft cloathes to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend it from the injury of the aire.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>Of burnings with gunpowder.</head>
               <p>THe cure is all one with other burnings of fire, but becauſe thoſe that are much uſed to ſhoot in guns are ſubject to the flame of powder, I have placed it heer, if the skin be not ulcerate, you may apply oyle of bitter Almonds, oyle of Olives, or juyce of Onyons, but if there be ulcerations, uſe this Unguent following.</p>
               <p>℞. <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Olei olivarum,</hi> 2. pound.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Secundae Corticis ſambuci.</hi> 4. ounces.</item>
                  </list> Boyle theſe on the fire, then ſtrain them out ſtrongly, after adde to them
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ceruſsae</hi> halfe an ounce.</item>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Plumbi uſti</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Lithargyri</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                        <hi>ana</hi> 3. drachmes.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Mix them, and make thereof a liniment, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply it: Thus much of gunſhot.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="recipes">
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:192126:41"/>
            <head>Receipts for ſeverall Diſeaſes.</head>
            <head type="sub">Here followeth choyce and ſelect Receipts.</head>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>An excellent preſervative againſt the Plague.</head>
               <p>TAke Aloes Epatica, or Sicatrina, Cynamon, and Mirrhe, of each of them three Dragms, Cloves, Mace, Lignum Aloes, Maſtick, Bole Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monick, of each of them halfe a Drachme, ſtampe them well together in a clean morter, mingle them together, and take of it every morning two pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny waight in halfe a glaſſe of white wine, with a little water, and drinke of it in the morning, it is excellent againſt all infection of the Ayre and Plague.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>Remedies againſt the Plague.</head>
               <p>IN the time of Peſtilence in no wiſe ſuffer too great thirſt, and if you do thirſt drink but mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurably, and uſe cooling drinkes, ſuch as Tyſan water mingled with Vinegar, or water of Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, Lettice, Roſe-water, Scabious, Turmentill, or Dittany; alſo when you go to bed, ſhut your doores and windowes cloſe, and have a pan of coales, whereon caſt powder of Laurell leaves
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:192126:42"/>dryed, Roſemary and Frankinſenſe; alſo uſe in your chamber fire of Juniper wood, Frankinſenſe, Storax, Calamint, and Labdanum; like wiſe have ever ſome Pomeander or good ſcent about you.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>A Drinke for the Plague.</head>
               <p>GIve the Party (finding himſelfe ſick) before he ſleepe, ſix ſpoonfuls of <hi>Aqua vitae,</hi> and put therein a ſpoonfull of beaten gunpowder, and let him drink it, and ſweat upon it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>A Cordiall Water.</head>
               <p>TAke a gallon of Strawberries, and put them into a pint of <hi>Aqua vitae,</hi> let them ſtand for foure or five dayes, ſtrain them gently out, and ſweeten the water as you pleaſe with fine Sugar or Perfume.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For burning or ſcalding.</head>
               <p>TAke green Geeſe dunge, and fry it with freſh butter and ſheeps ſuet, and ſtrain it through a cloth, and lay it on the fore.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For ſtinging of Adders and Snakes.</head>
               <p>TAke Draggons and drink it, alſo ſtamp Drag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons and lay it to the place, where the ſting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:192126:42"/>is, it will both draw out the venom, and heale the ſmarting and pain.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For the Scurvy.</head>
               <p>TAke of white-wine a quart, of running water or Ale, which you like beſt, a quart, Colts<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foot four or five leaves, Engliſh Licoris ſcraped and ſliced two or three ſticks, of Hyſop two or three ſlips, Raiſins of the ſun ſtoned ten, of Figs ſliced two or three, of Anniſeeds brayed in a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a ſpoonfull, of Elecampane a root or two, boyle theſe together to the halfe, then skim and ſtrain them in a fair cloth, and ſet the liquor upon the embers, and therein put an ounce of white ſuger candy beaten; take about a ſpoonfull here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of morning and evening, and every two houres as much. <hi>Probatum eſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For pain in the head, and to cauſe ſleep.</head>
               <p>TAke two handfuls of Dog-bryar leaves, four ſpoonfuls of wine vineger, as much red Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water, as much breaſt-milke, a Nutmeg ſliced ſmall; infuſe theſe in a diſh upon a chaſing-diſh with coales, and apply them to each ſide of the head, upon the temples when you go to reſt; in caſe the Roſes be not to be had, red Roſe-cakes, or red Poppy-cakes will ſerve the turn.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:192126:43"/>
               <head>For a Canker, or any other heat in the mouth.</head>
               <p>TAke red Sage and Rue, of each a handfull, of Sorrell, Groundſell, of each a ſmall quantity; cut the Hearbs ſmall, and ſtampe them in a wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en veſſell, then take roach Allome the quantity of a Walnut, of white Copperas as much as a Hazell Nut, and burn them together: Take alſo as much Copperas and Allome unburnt, ſtamp theſe with the Hearbs very ſmall, then boyle them in a pint of running water, with three ſpoonfuls of Engliſh hony, till halfe be conſumed, then let it run tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough a ſtrainer, into an earthen veſſell; when it is cold put it in a glaſſe, and when you uſe it, you muſt gargle with it three times a day; you may lay ſome of the Hearbs that remaine in the ſtainer, to the ſoreſt places, if you ſee cauſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For the pin and web, or any other Rheume in the eyes.</head>
               <p>TAke two new layd Eggs, make a hole in the crowns, and put the whites into a ſawcer, then put away the yolkes, and take one of the ſhels and waſh it with faire water, and put halfe the white into it, then put in as much white Coppe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras as a Peaſe, and ſo much Roach Allome, then
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:192126:43"/>fill the egge-ſhell up with the reſt of the white, then lute it up with a little dow, and wrap it in a wet paper, and rake it up in Embers till it be very hard, then ſtrain it thorow a ſtrong cloth; drop one drop of this water into your eye, lying on your back, morning and night, and alſo at foure of the clock, if need be.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For a woman that hath not her termes.</head>
               <p>TAke a ſmall quantity of the beſt <hi>hiera picra,</hi> every morning in a little warm poſſet drinke; if the party be of a weake conſtitution, then every other morning, about two houres after let them drinke ſome warm phyſick broth, and beware of taking cold; if need be let blood in the foot.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>A Powder for the green ſickneſſe.</head>
               <p>TAke a quarter of a pound of Sugar, Steele ℥ i. of Pearle, Cloves, Mace, and Nutmegs, <hi>ana</hi> halfe an ounce, beat them very ſmall, and mingle them together, and take in the morning faſting as much as will lye on a ſix pence, and ſo much again at four of the clock in the afternoon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>A Purge.</head>
               <p>TAke of the beſt Sena, ſix Drachms, of Rha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barbe two Drachms; <hi>Cremor tartari</hi> halfe
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:192126:44"/>a Drachme, of ſweet Fennell-ſeed as much, and a little Cynamon; infuſe all theſe one night in half a pint of white wine, in the morning let it boyle a walm or two, ſtraine it and put to it of the beſt Manna ℥ i. diſſolve it over the fire, then ſtraine it, and put to it one ounce of the ſollative ſirrup of Roſes, and ſo drink it; faſt two houres after from meat, drink, and ſleep, and then drink nothing but thin broth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For the Ptiſick, or ſhortneſs of breath.</head>
               <p>TAke a pint of Hony, clarifie it, and put to it ℥ ij. of flower of Licoras, a quarter of a pound of Currans, two ounces of ſweet Fennell-ſeed bruiſed, flower of Elecampane roots two drachms, ſtir all theſe together into the hony over the fire. then take it off, and eate a little of this in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and at any other time, when you ſee occaſion. <hi>Probatum eſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>An excellent Drinke for the Ptiſick and Conſumption.</head>
               <p>TAke two quarts of running water, put into it two handfuls of unſet Hyſop, two handfuls of tops of Roſemary, a handfull of Scabious, a little Lungwort, and Mayden-hayre, nine or ten Figs ſliced, a few Elecampane roots, ſtir all theſe toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:192126:44"/>boyle it to a quart, and ſweeten it with Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar-candy, drinke hereof three times a day, a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle warme, morning faſting, three in the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon, and laſt at night.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For the Dropſie.</head>
               <p>TAke ſweet Fennell-ſeeds, Anniſeeds, Parſly-ſeeds, Coriander-ſeeds, of each an ounce, Rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſins of the ſun ſtoned one pound, blew Figs halfe a pound, French Barley two ounces, <hi>Capillus vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris</hi> one handfull, Hartongue, Polipody-roots, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verwort, Lungwort, <hi>ana</hi> halfe an handfull, red Sage, Penny Royall, Violet leaves, each one hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, nine tops of Roſemary, inward barke of green Elder one handfull, Liquoras two ounces, boyle all theſe together in a gallon of ſpring water, to a pottle, then ſweeten it with Sugar-candy, and drinke of it when you pleaſe: After this take half a peck of Sage of virtue, and red Sage together, and two handfuls of Rue, and ſtill them together, and ſo drink them altogether.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>A Plague Water.</head>
               <p>TAke a pound of Celandine, Roſemary, Balm, Rue, Wormwood, Draggons, Scabious, Pim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernell, Egrimony, Bettony, Angelica, Cardus, Marigold leaves and flowers, Burrage-leaves and
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:192126:45"/>flowers, Featherfue, <hi>Roſa ſolis,</hi> Pellitory of Spain, Pellitory of the wall, red Sage, and Sage of Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, Setwell, Mother time, and Devils bit, Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentill, of every of theſe a pound, or leſſe, as you ſee cauſe proportionably; Tormentill roots halfe ſo much as of the Hearb, put all theſe together in a great pot, and let them ſoke in white wine three dayes and three nights, ſtopping the pot very cloſe and ſtirred two or three times a day, being ſet in a very coole place, then take out the Hearbs and ſtill them, and keep the water in faire glaſſes, and ſet the ſame in the ſun; and if any happen to be ſick of this diſeaſe, give them ten ſpoonfuls of this water bloud warm, ſo ſoon as they feele them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſick, and then let him walk an houre if he be able; if he be not of himſelfe, then let him be led about by the armes an houre, let him not eate or drink in the mean time, and then have him to bed; if he vomit it is the better, and if he take it before he ſleepe he ſhall eſcape <hi>(Deo Iuvante)</hi> the older the water is, the better it is: This water muſt be ſtilled in May, if the Hearbs can be got ſo early; and it is good againſt the Ague, or any infectious diſeaſe that is in the ſtomack, being taken before the fit do come.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For heat in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine.</head>
               <p>TAke the rinds of Hazell, ſteepe them in Ale or Beere, and drinke it for your firſt and laſt
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:192126:45"/>draught every day, and at any other time, if you pleaſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>DIſtill Purſlaine in a common ſtill, and drink of that water a quarter of a pint every morning.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For a ſtrain cauſing one to ſpit bloud.</head>
               <p>TAke a pint of good Sack, and ſet it on the fire, and put into it a good piece of fine Sugar, let it ſo ſtand till it be ready to burn, (burn it not) then brew into it the yolkes of four new layd egges, ſtrain it, brewing it continually till it be thick like a Cawdell, then drink a draught thereof firſt and laſt, both morning and night; Sirrup of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrey is likewiſe very good for the ſame purpoſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>A Bag for purging Ale.</head>
               <p>TAke of Egrimony, Speedwell, Liverwort, Scurvy-graſſe, Watercreſſes, each a good hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, of Monke, Rhabarb, and red Madder, each halfe an handfull, of Horſe Rhadiſh roots ℥ iij. Licoras ℥ ij. Saſſafrace ℥ iiij. Sena ℥ vij. ſweet Fennell-ſeeds two drams, four Nutmegs, pick and waſh your Hearbs and roots, bruiſe them all in a morter, and put them all into a bag made of bol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; ſo hang them in three gallons of middle Ale,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:192126:46"/>and let it worke in the Ale, and after three daye you may drink of it as you ſee occaſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For to ſtay vomiting.</head>
               <p>TAke Roſes and boyle them in good ſtrong Vinegar, and make a Plaiſter thereof, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply it to the ſtomack.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>A ſecret Powder for wounds.</head>
               <p>TAke Hipericon leaves and flowers, Millſoyle and Viticella, and ſtamp them together, and ſtrow it upon the wound, and round about the wound when it is dreſſed, and it doth defend it from Accidents.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>Of the Sciatica.</head>
               <p>THe Sciatica is a Diſeaſe ſo called, becauſe it cometh in that place of the body called Scio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and is cauſed of an evill quality, and groſſe humors that are ſtayed in that place, becauſe they cannot paſſe down: The Cure thereof is with Gliſters, Vomits, Purgations, and Unctions, becauſe the Gliſters do evacuate thoſe places next unto it, and ſo eaſeth the humor; the Vomit cleanſeth the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack, the Purgation doth evacuate the body downwards, and the Unctions diſſolve the wind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:192126:46"/>&amp; eaſe it; ſo that by theſe means, you may help the Sciatica.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>Againſt a ſtinking mouth.</head>
               <p>YE muſt waſh your mouth with water and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negar, and chew Maſtick a good while, and then waſh your mouth with the decoction of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſeeds, Mints, and Cloves ſodden in wine.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For a ſtinking breath.</head>
               <p>SEeth two ounces of Commin-ſeeds bruiſed in a pottle of white wine unto a quart, then keep it, uſing to drinke a little thereof at night warme, the ſpace of fifteen dayes, and it will help.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To make an aking tooth fall out of himſelfe, without any inſtrument or pain.</head>
               <p>TAke wheat-flower, and mix it with the milke of the Hearb called in Latine <hi>Herba lactaeria,</hi> in Engliſh Spurge, which is an Hearb well enough known, and thereof make as it were a paſte or dow, with which you ſhall fill the hole of the tooth, and leave it in a certain time, and the tooth will fall out of himſelfe; alſo if you waſh your mouth once every month with wine, wherein the root of the ſayd Hearb hath been ſodden; you ſhall never have pain in your teeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:192126:47"/>
               <head>An excellent purging Ale called the Ale of health and ſtrength.</head>
               <p>TAke Saſſafrace-wood halfe an ounce, Sarſapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilla three ounces, white Saunders one ounce, Mace a quarter of an ounce, <hi>Lignum Rhodium,</hi> China root, each halfe an ounce, <hi>Lignum vitae</hi> a quarter of an ounce; cut the woods as thin as may be into ſmall pieces, and bruiſe them in a morter, and put to them Cowſlip flowers, and Romane Wormwood, each an handfull, Sage, Roſemary, Bettony, Mugwort, Balm, and ſweet Marjoram, each halfe a handfull, a handfull of Hops, boyle all theſe in ſix gallons of Ale, till it come to foure; then put the Woods and Hearbs into ſix gallons of Ale of the ſecond wort, and boyle it likewiſe till it come to foure; let it run from the drugs, and put your Ale together, and uſe it as you do o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Ale, put it in a ſweet veſſell till it be ripe, and then drink it at your pleaſure.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>A Medicine for the Gout to be taken in order.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>1.</hi> The Pultis.</head>
                  <p>TAke of Manchet about three ounces, the crum only thin cut; let it be boyled in milke till it come to a pulpe, then adde unto it a drachme and a halfe of the powder of red Roſes, of Saffron ten
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:192126:47"/>graines, oyle of Roſes halfe an ounce; let it be ſpread upon a thin cloth, and applyed luke warm, and continued for three houres ſpace.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>2.</hi> The bath for the Gout.</head>
                  <p>TAke of Sage leaves halfe an handfull, of Hem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock roots ſliced ſix drachms, of Briany roots halfe an ounce, two handfuls of red Roſe leaves; let them be boyled in a pottle of water wherein ſteele hath been quenched till the liquor come to a quart, after the ſtraining put in halfe a handfull of bay-ſalt; let it be uſed with ſcarlet wool, or ſcarlet cloth, dipt in the liquor hot, and renewed ſeven times in the ſpace of an houre, or a little more.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>3.</hi> The Plaiſter for the Gout.</head>
                  <p>TAke the Plaiſter of Diacalcytis as much as is ſufficient for the part you mean to cover; let it be diſſolved with oyle of Roſes in ſuch a conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence as will ſtick, and ſpread it upon a piece of Holland, and ſo apply it.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For a ſtraine.</head>
               <p>TAke Powder of Corrall, and Powder of Rock-amber beads, each halfe a drachme, make them up into paſte with a little gum-draggon and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:192126:48"/>of red Roſes; this you muſt eate morning and evening, and beware of violent ſtirring, wine, and women, and meats with Pepper.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For a Flux.</head>
               <p>PUt one ounce of whole Pepper into a quart of new milke, boyle it unto a pint, and drinke halfe a pint thereof every morning, and faſt three houres after it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For a Pin and Web, or any other Rheume in the Eyes.</head>
               <p>TAke two new layd eggs, make a hole in the crowns, and put the whites into a ſawcer; then put away the yolkes, and take one of the ſhels and waſh it in faire water, and put halfe the white into it; then put in as much white Coperas as a Peaſe, &amp; as much Roch Allome, then fill up the egge with the reſt of the whites, roſt it in embers, and afterwards ſtraine it, drop a drop of it into your eye, lying on your back morning and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>Another for Rheume in the eyes.</head>
               <p>TAke white Archangell flowers, and put them into ſallet oyle, and heat them upon a chafing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh of coales, and lay them to the nape of the
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:192126:48"/>neck, as hot as you can ſuffer them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For blear'd and watry eyes.</head>
               <p>TAke a quarter of a pint of the pureſt running water, and put it into a violl glaſſe, and put thereto four ounces of the beſt white Copperas, being firſt beaten into very fine powder; then put thereto three or four ſpoonfuls of red Fennell-water, or for want thereof as many of the ſprigs of red Fennell, growing next the root; then lute up the violl cloſe, and ſet it in a skillet of faire water, and warm it ſo til it begin to boyle, then take it out, and ſo keep it for uſe; let the patient morning and evening have a drop dropped into the eye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For heat in the Eyes.</head>
               <p>TAke the white of a new layd Egge, beat it very well, then let it ſtand and ſettle, and take a ſpoonful of the cleareſt thereof, and as much breaſt-milke, and ſo much red Roſe-water, as both of them, mingle them well together, put them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a glaſſe, and when you uſe it, warme a little thereof bloud-warm, and dip two or three rags folded three or four times double, being very fine, and bind them on the eyes when you go to bed, and in the day time waſh therewith your eyes, as often as you pleaſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:192126:49"/>
               <head>A water for ſore Eyes.</head>
               <p>TAke ſix drachms of Tutia, made into fine powder, as much Aloes in powder, as much fine Sugar, a pint and an halfe of white wine, as much white Roſe-water, put all theſe into a pottle glaſſe, ſtop it very cloſe, and ſun it a month, ſhake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it very wel twice or thrice a day, and ſo keep it for your uſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>An Electuary for a Conſumption.</head>
               <p>TAke Elecampane roots one pound, waſh and ſcrape them clean; cut them in little ſquare pieces, then take of Rhadiſhes a quarter of a pound, ſlice them thin, and as many Wardens as the weight of both theſe; ſlice them thin likewiſe, mingle them together, laying them in Lanes in a Pipkin, and put between every of them ſome ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, lute up the Pipkin cloſe with paſte, and bake it in an Oven with houſhold bread: A pint of hony may be enough for this quantity; when it is cold beat it to a pulpe in a ſtone mortar, and take it as an Electuary morning and evening.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>A Julip for a Conſumption, or any weak body.</head>
               <p>TAke a Capon that is fleſhy, and not fat, dreſſe him clean, cut him into about ten pieces, waſh
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:192126:49"/>him in white wine, cut every piece by it ſelfe, and put into every piece a ſmall skewer, that the fleſh may not touch the bottome, then put them into a jugge, with a narrow mouth that will hold about a pottle, then put to it twenty Raiſins of the ſun ſtoned, four Dates quartered, two large Maces, a ſprig of Roſemary, ſtop it up cloſe with a Corke, then lute it with paſte, and tie a cloth over it, that no ayre get out or in then ſet the jugge in a pottle of water, and ſet bricks about it that it may not ſtir, ſo let it boyle ſix houres at the leaſt; keepe your pot full of water to the neck of the jugge, by having other water ready heated to fil it, then take it out of the pot, and when it hath ſtood halfe an houre, poure out the Julip; if there be any fat in the top take it off, put to this ten graines of Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber-greeſe in powder, ſtir them wel together, and ſo put them up in your glaſſe, and take three ſpoonfuls of this at a time warmed when you go to bed; if the Patient be too hot put leſſe, or leave quite out the Amber-greeſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For a Cough, or ſhortneſs of breathing.</head>
               <p>TAke a quart of running water, boyle therein a handful of unſet Hyſop, til it come to a pint, ſtraine it, and put thereto a quarter of an ounce of Licoras ſliced, halfe a handfull of Raiſins of the ſun ſtoned, two Figs, two Dates, ſweet
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:192126:50"/>Fennel-ſeeds, and Anniſeeds halfe an ounce, boyle theſe til almoſt halfe be conſumed, then let it run thorow a ſtrainer, and ſweeten the liquor with white Sugar-candy, and drink of it bloud warms firſt and laſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>A Sirrup for a Conſumption and Cough.</head>
               <p>TAke two handfuls of Elecampane, ſlice it thin, boyle it in faire water halfe an houre, ſhifting it two or three times, then take two handfuls of Colts-foot, two handfuls of Liver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wort, one of Harts-tongue, and two handfuls of Egrimony, one handful of Mayden-haire, a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of an handful of Mayden-hyſop, an ounce of China root ſliced, two ounces of Licoras ſliced, a ſpoonfull of Anniſeeds, a good handfull of Raiſins of the ſun ſtoned, foure or five Figs ſliced, two ſpoonfuls of French-barly bruiſed, and boyled in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to two or three ſeveral waters; put all theſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a pottle of running water, boyle them until more then halfe be conſumed, and ſtrain the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor from the drugs, and put in your Elecampane boyled before, and a pound and an halfe of Sugar boyle it to a ſirrup, and keep it in a gally pot to your uſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:192126:50"/>
               <head>For the Chine Cough.</head>
               <p>TAke a handful of Rue and ſtamp it, then min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle it with Engliſh hony, and make it into a Conſerve, give it mornings and afternoons, and at night to bed ward, as much at a time as a Nut.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>ROaſt an Egge rear, dreſſe it, and put into it as much flower of Brimſtone as will lye up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a two pence, mix it wel together, and let the Patient ſup it up every morning faſting.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For the Spleene.</head>
               <p>TAke of Couch, or Graſſe roots, Succory roots, and Fennel roots, of each halfe an ounce, of the Barke of Caper, and Barke of Tamarisk, each two drachms, Currans and Capers waſht from the Salt, each three drachms, boyle theſe in the belly of a Chicken, with a branch of Time, and put in the bottome of a white loafe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For a Flux.</head>
               <p>TAke Barke of an Oake from the Tanners, grind it to powder, and ſearce it, put it into
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:192126:51"/>new milke, and boyle them very wel together, eate of this pap every morning, and what other times you pleaſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>Another for the ſame, being alſo good for a weak back.</head>
               <p>TAke ſtale bread, or ſhip-bisket, grate it, and put it into a quart of new milke, with a good ſtick of Cynomon, and a good piece of I ſinglaſſe, boyle it to a pint, and thereof morning and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning you may take what you pleaſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For a weake back, or the whites.</head>
               <p>TAke an ounce of Cynomon, an ounce of white Comphry roots, one ounce of Polipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian of the oak, three ounces of white Sugar-can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, make all theſe into powder, mingle them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and take as much at a time thereof as wil lye upon a ſix penny piece, every morning for the ſpace of five dayes, and ſo likewiſe in the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon, and drink a draught of red wine within an houre after every taking.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>A Plaiſter for the ſwelling of the ſtones.</head>
               <p>TAke Cow-dung, and ſeeth the ſame in milke, then make a Plaiſter thereof, and lay it meetly hot upon the ſwelling.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:192126:51"/>
               <head>Another for the ſwelling of the ſtones.</head>
               <p>TAke Comminſeed, Anniſeed, and Fennugreeke, of each a like portion, ſeeth them in Ale, and ſtamp them, and temper them with freſh May but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or a little oyle Olive, and apply it to the ſore.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>Another for the ſame in the beginning of the griefe.</head>
               <p>IF there be much inflamation in the Cods, you may make an Oyntment of Planten, the yolke of an egge, and oyle of Roſes, ſtir them wel a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, and apply it to the griefe twice or thrice in a day; if the pain be great, and the Patient of a good age, and of ſtrong complexion; if the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes will not help, make a Plaiſter after this ſort, <hi>viz.</hi> Take Henbane leaves a handful, Mallow leaves a handful and an halfe, ſeeth them wel in clear water, then ſtamp them and ſtir them, and with the broath, Bean-flower, Barly-flower, oyle of Roſes and Camomile ſufficient, make it up, and put it on the ſwelling lukewarme; Henbane is good (as <hi>Avicen</hi> ſaith) to diſſolve the hardneſs of the ſtones by a ſecret quality.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:192126:52"/>
               <head>A Pultis for a ſore breaſt.</head>
               <p>TAke new milke and white bread grated, Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, and red Roſe leaves, each an handful, then chop them and boyle them together til it be thick, then put in Hony and common Turpentine, ſpread it on a cloth and apply it to the ſore.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>TAke a quart of faire water, halfe a pint of oat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meale, two handfuls of Smalledge, halfe a handfull of red Nettles, boyle all theſe well toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, being firſt chopt, and put in a quarter of a pound of Sheeps ſuet minced, ſtir them well on the fire, and apply part thereof as hot as the Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent can ſuffer it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For an Ague in the breaſt, as alſo to dry up the Milke.</head>
               <p>TAke good <hi>Aquavitae,</hi> Linſeed oyle, warme them in a diſh, and dip therein two clothes fit for the breaſts, and apply them as hot as can be endured, lay alſo a little lump of Flax tow under each Arme, being well dryed and warme, and dreſſe the breaſts therewith morning and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:192126:52"/>
               <head>For a ſwell'd face.</head>
               <p>TAke Roſemary leaves, mince them, boyl them with milke and oatmeale to a Pultis, then put thereto a ſpoonful of hony, apply it as oft as there is cauſe, and as hot as the Patient can ſuffer it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For any ordinary ſoreneſſe.</head>
               <p>TAke a pint of Ale yeſt, three or four handfuls of groundſel, houſhold leaven as much as an egge; ſet the yeſt upon the fire, and then crum the leaven into it, and let it boyle a little while, and then put in the hearbs and the roots, and let it be boyled thick, and lay ſome of it on a cloth every morning and evening, and this will both draw, break, and heale.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For a Fiſtula.</head>
               <p>TAke a handful of Sage, waſh it, pick and ſpread it, boyle it in a pint of milke, til it be tender, then take a penny worth of Flax ſeed, beat it to powder, and when the Sage is tender, thick the milke with the Flax-ſeed, when it is boyled put thereto a penny worth of oyl of Roſes, uſe this two or three dayes twice a day.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:192126:53"/>
               <head>For a Felon or Boyle.</head>
               <p>TAke halfe a pint of new milke, and put ſome grated bread into it, boyle them together, then put thereto a handful of Smalledge, as much Southernwood chopped fine, ſo boyle them to a Pultice, and when it is boyled, ſtir into it almoſt a ſpoonful of Caſtle Sope ſcraped.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For a Burn or Scald.</head>
               <p>TAke three handfuls of the green rinds of El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, as much green Gooſe dung, beat theſe, and boyle them a pretty while in a pound of freſh butter, ſtrain it out very hard, and keep it in an earthen pot, ſtir it til it be almoſt cold; and when you uſe it melt thereof, and anoynt the ſore with a feather, and lay a Primroſe leafe next the ſore.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>TAke Barrows greaſe, red Sage, Sengreene, chop them and boyle altogether, then ſtrain it and uſe it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For the Mother.</head>
               <p>TAke a great red Onion, and cut a round hole therein, and fil it with black Sope, and roaſt it
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:192126:53"/>in Embers til it be ſoft, and apply it to the Navel as hot as may be.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For the ſame.</head>
               <p>GIve the Patient a good draught of fair water and wheat flower mingled together, bow the Patient forward, and burn Partridge feathers before them in a chafing-diſh with coals.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To cure Cornes in the feet, and the cauſe of them.</head>
               <p>THe matter whereof Cornes are ingendred is a certain hot humour, whereof nature ſtriveth to be disburthened and diſcharged, and is properly rearmed a Callowes matter, and this humour na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture endeavouring to expell, forceth it out unto the lower parts of the body, even unto the very extremity of the toes, where it cannot paſſe any further by reaſon of the hardneſſe of the skin, whereby it often ingendreth a hard tumor in the skin, which many times doth increaſe, and grow in hardneſs, cauſing ſuch pain, that it doth not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hinder their going that are troubled therewith, but alſo many times breaketh their ſleepe in the night: This kind of tumor is commonly called <hi>Callo,</hi> or Cornes, and infinite number of people are troubled with this Malady; and many have
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:192126:54"/>pretended much for the cure of them, but very few have perfectly arrived at it; they may be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well eaſed, but the perfect cure of them is ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, if at all compleated; the beſt way is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to pare them with a ſharp knife unto the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome, where you ſhal find a certain matter; but if you find none, pare them until the fleſh be ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and then dreſſe it with the oyle of Sulphure, or artificial Balſome, and it will much help it; likewiſe the leaden plaiſter formerly mentioned in this booke is very profitable for eaſing Cornes, being plaiſter wiſe applyed thereto; the juyce of Houſe-leeke if it can be conveniently applyed hath been approved very effectuall for this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>An excellent Oyntment for the Stone and Chollick.</head>
               <p>TAke Broom-buds ready to blow clean picked from the ſtalkes, halfe a pound, and beat them very ſmal in a morter, then mix them with May butter clarified, as much as ſhal be ſufficient to make it into an Oyntment, and keep it cloſe ſtopt in a veſſel eight dayes, then ſeeth it and ſtrain it, and therewith anoint the Patient very warme evening and morning.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:192126:54"/>
               <head>For winde or chollick in the belly.</head>
               <p>TAke a Roſe-cake and toaſt it at the fire with vinegar thrown upon it, and lay it as hot to your belly as you may ſuffer it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For inflamations in Wounds.</head>
               <p>TAke of the juyce of the hearb called Pimper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel, and of Sempervive, of each halfe a pound, of oyle Olive one pound, put them all into a veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel to boyle until halfe be conſumed, then put thereto of butter foure ounces, and of Valerian halfe an ounce, and make thereof an oyntment, and uſe it as you ſee occaſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>Againſt the ſwelling of the Leggs.</head>
               <p>TAke the juyce of Walwort, Wax, Vinegar, and Barly meale, of each like quantity, boyle it, and make a plaiſter, and bind it upon the ſore.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>An excellent Preſervative againſt the Plague.</head>
               <p>TAke Aloes Sicatrina, Cynomon, and Mirrhe, each three drachms, Cloves, Mace, Lignum A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loes, Maſtick, Bole-armonick of each halfe a
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:192126:55"/>drachme, let them be ſtamped very ſmal in a clean morter, then mingle them together, and after keep them in ſome cloſe veſſel for your uſe; take of this medecine every morning two penny weight in halfe a glaſſe of white wine, with a little Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron water, and drink it in the morning faſting betimes, when you feare any infectious ayre, and by Gods help it will defend you.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>An excellent Plaiſter to diſſolve Tumors, which King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eight uſed for the ſwelling in his Legs.</head>
               <p>TAke the roots of Marſh Mallows, waſh and pick them clean, then ſlit them and take out the pith, then cut them in ſmall pieces and bruiſe them, then take the quantity of a pound of them, and put them in a new earthen pot, and adde thereto of Linſeed and Fenugreeke, each two oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces bruiſed, then put thereto Malmſie and white wine, each a pint, and ſtir altogether, and let them ſtand infuſed two or three dayes, then ſet them over a fire, and ſtir it till it grow thick and ſlimy, then take it off, and ſtrain it thorow a new Canvas cloth, then take oyle of Roſes a quart, and waſh it in white wine and Roſe water very well; then take the oyle clean from the water and wine, and ſet it over the fire in a braſſe pan, alwayes ſtirring it, and put thereto the powder of
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:192126:55"/>Lytharge of Gold, and Lytharge of Silver, each eight ounces, of Ceruſe ſix ounces, or red Corrall two ounces, of Bole Armonick and Draggons bloud, each one ounce; make theſe into very fine powder, and ſearce them, then put them into the oyle over the fire, alwayes continuing your ſtirring it, then put in of the Mucylage made of the Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low roots before, ten ounce, by little and little at once; and when it is boyled enough, which you ſhall perceive by the hardneſs or ſoftneſs thereof; if you drop a drop of it on the bottome of a cleane pewter diſh, if it be hard, take it off from the fire, and when it is neer cold make it up in roles, and keep them in Parchment for your uſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>A marvelous remedy to cure the Peſtilence, Carbuncles, and ſuch like.</head>
               <p>TAke the ſeed or berries of Ivy, that groweth on trees or wals, and gather the ſayd berries very ripe, dry them in the ſhadow, and keep them in a box of wood as a precious thing; and if any be infected with the Peſtilence, take of the ſayd ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and beat them to powder, and give the Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent of the ſayd powder as much as will lye upon a groat in a glaſſe of white wine, then cover him ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry hot in his bed, and let him ſweat very well, then let him change his ſhirt and the ſheets if you can conveniently; ſome have taken of this pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:192126:56"/>over night and been perfectly well in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>How a man may preſerve himſelfe in time of Peſtilence againſt infectious Ayres.</head>
               <p>BEcauſe the evill humors that be in mans body, make it more apt and eaſie to receive the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption and infection of the Ayre; it is good to keep the ſtomack and the head clean purged, not to overcharge it by eating and drinking, but ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine from all exceſſe thereof, and alſo from all groſſe meats, and to purge himſelfe often gently with ſome eaſie purgation, as of Caſſia, Rhabarb, Maſtick pils, Aloes, or the like: It is alſo good to eate in your pottage things that purge the bloud, as Burrage, Bugglas, Succory, Lettice, and ſuch like; and above all, not to keep your ſtomack o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercharged, nor too empty, and in the morning betimes to take ſome of theſe preſervative medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines as Rue, Figs, &amp; Walnuts, which is very good againſt all infections, or elſe take ſome Confect, as the pill of Citron Confect, and after meales to uſe the ſeeds of Citron Confect in Sugar, which is very good againſt all manner of venome and poyſon: And likewiſe at your meales to eate the white and inſide of a Citron with a little Sugar, and to eate it with meat as men eate Lemmons in the morning, at noon, and night. It is alſo very
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:192126:56"/>good to bath and waſh your hands, your temples, your pulſes, and your noſe with vineger roſer, or with other vineger, whereunto you may adde a little Camphire, Roſe water, <hi>Lignum</hi> Aloes, <hi>Xile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>balſamum,</hi> if you can get it, if not, uſe a little Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomon inſtead thereof: It is alwayes very good to keep ſuch kind of vineger by you in ſome viol, for to uſe it when time ſhall require, for it is a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good preſervative; and if you cannot have the vinegar compound as is preſcribed, then you may uſe vineger of compound wine; alſo it is very good to carry about you ſome good perfume, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in your Gloves, or Handkercheife, or to hang it about your neck; your houſe ought to be kept as clean as poſſible, not ſavouring of piſſe, or ſuch unſavoury ſmels; keep it ſhut, and often waſhed, and beware ye keep no foule and ſtinking clothes in your houſe. you may alſo often burn in your houſe the wood and leaves of a Bay-tree, of Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary, Juniper, and Cyprus, uſe it often, likewiſe Pitch, Roſin, and Olibanum, burning it in the midſt of the houſe or chamber, principally at night and in the morning: Likewiſe Orenge and Lem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon pils, Storax <hi>calamita,</hi> and <hi>Labdanum,</hi> be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good for this purpoſe. As concerning the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the mind, ye muſt conſider, that Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, Anger, Sadneſs, or Melancholy, do corrupt the bloud and other humors, weaken the heart and ſpirits, deprave and hurt nature, therefore e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:192126:57"/>man ought to avoyd them as much as is poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible; alſo if a man be over much merry, or given to pleaſure, it dilateth and enlargeth the pores and paſſages of the ſeed of man and the heart, ſo that he is thereby the more inclined, and more apt to receive the evill ayre and venome, penetrating in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his body, alſo a man muſt beware of drinking much wine; thsrefore it is good to uſe tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and moderation in all things, and above all things let a man alwayes have a ſure hope and confidence in God, ever be ready and diſpoſed to dye when he ſhall pleaſe to call us, not ſo much eſteeming this mundane or worldly life, or fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo much death, which is no other thing then an iſſue or departing out of this troubleſome life full of miſeries and calamities, and an entrance in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an ever bleſſed and eternall life, repleniſhed with all joy, ſolace, and pleaſure, which God hath prepared for all them that love him through Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To breake the Stone.</head>
               <p>TAke the ſtones of a Cock of a year old, d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> them and beat them into fine powder, and give it the party diſeaſed to drinke in white win<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> alſo the ſtones of a Colt made into powder, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> drunk in white wine, is good for the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:192126:57"/>
               <head>A very approved good exciccative Plaiſter for all kinds of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcerations, as well of the legs, as other parts of the body.</head>
               <p>TAke of Lytharge in powder one pound, of oyle of Roſes one pint, of white Wax ℥ ij. of Mirrhe and Olibanum, each ℥ i. of white wine and of Urine, of each halfe a pound, of white wine vineger a quarter of a pound, of Nightſhade and Plantain, of each halfe a handfull: Put the hearbs in a morter with the vineger, and ſtampe them together, and wring out the juyce, and put unto it the vineger and wine aforeſayd; and thus you muſt make your Plaiſter, melt your oyle and wax together in a faire pan, and let it boyle, then by little and little put in your Lytharge, alwayes ſtirring it, afterwards put in your juyces by little and little, keeping it ſtirring till you have put in all, and be ſure it be well ſtirred that it ſettle not to the bottome, and ſo let it boyle ſtirring it well till the juyces be conſumed; then laſt of all, put in your Mirrhe and Olibanum in fine powder, and ſtir it till it be cold; if it be too hard make it ſoft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er with oyle of Roſes, if it be too ſoft boyle it harder according to art, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:192126:58"/>
                  <head>The virtues of this Plaiſter.</head>
                  <p>THis is a ſpeciall Plaiſter for all kinds of Ulce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, and old feſtred ſores, as well of the legs as of any other parts of the body, for it hath great virtue alterative, reſolvative, and excicca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ive provided alwayes the body be throughly and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally purged, as often as need ſhall require.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>A good Cerate called <hi>Hydrelaeon Galeni.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke of Lythargy of Silver one pound, of clear fair water, of pure oyle each two pound; the Lytharge is to be made in pure fine powder, and the other to be ſtirred together in a morter o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſtone, then boyle them on a ſoft and ſmall fire o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> coales; the medicine ſhould properly be made in the ſun, that it be the whiter, and the fire vaniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, you muſt ſtill adde freſh coales untill you have boyled theſe together to the thickneſs and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of a Cerate, then preſerve it for theſe uſes: It doth refrigerate, and therefore is profitable in Ulcers and Tumors, for it ſuffereth not any hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour to flow unto them, and that which is alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy come it expelleth, it healeth itchings o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Wounds, Botches, and malignant Ulcers.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:192126:58"/>
               <head>Another for Rhumatick Paſſions and greene Wounds, it doth exciccate and dry.</head>
               <p>TAke Lytharge of Silver one pound, of pure oyle, and of the beſt white wine, of each one pound, mix them and boyle them to a Cerate as the former.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>A precious Oyntment good for all kind of Scia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticaes, dry itches, ſtraines of ſinews or vains, for any burning with gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powder, ſhingles, bliſters, venoms.</head>
               <p>TAke Organy, Mints, Time, Hyſop, Spike leaves and flowers Wormwood, Fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fue, O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pen, Sage, Vervain, Coſtmary, B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ttony, Mary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gold, Stems and flowers, each a good handfull, and of Valerian two good handfuls, take the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereſt part of the leaves from the heart ſtalkes, ſtamp them very ſmall, and ſeeth them in a clean pan with two pound of Barrows greaſe finely tryed, and four ounces of Dears ſuit ſtir it dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently the ſpace of an houre, then ſtrain it into a clean pan, let it ſtand all night, the next morning let out the water, underneath the oyntment take<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing none but the pureſt of it, ſet it on the fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, melt it, skum it clean, put thereto foure
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:192126:59"/>ounces of Deeres ſuet, then take it off, and let it ſtand all night as before, then warm it a little, and take it out on a clean boord, and cleanſe the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of it, and keep it for your uſe, it will laſt ſeven years.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For Aches, Bruiſes, Gouts, Stitches, Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, Cramps, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>TAke Sage, Rue, of each one pound. Worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood and Bayes, each halfe a pound, Sheeps ſuet three pound, all theſe muſt be ſtamped toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther till none of the ſuet be ſeen, but all one; then put thereto of oyle olive a pottle, and worke it well together, and after put it into a fine Baſon and cover it cloſe, and let it ſtand eight dayes and then take it out altogether and breake it into a braſſe pan, making a ſoft fire under it, ſtirring it till the herbs becom crackling, and hard, and then take it off, and when it is cold ſtraine it and put to it an ounce of oyle of ſpike, and anoint the greife therewith warme.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For the falling ſickneſſe.</head>
               <p>TAke the hinder part of a skull, beat it to pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and give it the party in Sirrup of violets aſmuch as a peaſe at a time.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:192126:59"/>
               <head>To draw out the Ague from any ſore or in the legs.</head>
               <p>TAke wormwood and henbane, each a handfull, ſhred them into a quart of milk, put in a hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of red roſe leaves, and as much beaten oate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meale as will make it a pultis, a good quantity of ſwines greaſe, and when it is well boyled apply it to the ſore very hot.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For an old ſore running with thinne matter.</head>
               <p>TAke running water and white wine vinegar each a pint, boyle them halfe away, then boyle therein a new peice of holland, thus bath with this liquor a place a hands bredth above the ſore, and lay the cloth on the ſame place; do it morning and evening.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For ſwelling in the knees or any other place that commeth of winde.</head>
               <p>TAke a quantity of ſacke, put therein ſome roſemary and a little pepper groſely beaten, put them all into a ſtone jugge, ſtop it cloſe and let it boyle ſoftly untill halfe be conſumed, then bath the place therewith that is grieved, as hot as
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:192126:60"/>may bee, then dipp a linnen ragge and binde it on the place, two or three times a day and keepe it warme.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To diſſolve any knob or hard ſwelling.</head>
               <p>TAke of the whiteſt Frankinſenſe, and the white of an egge, beat them to a ſalve, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For the Gout, and all manner of Aches and Bruiſes, an Oyntment.</head>
               <p>TAke Violet leaves and flowers, Primroſe leaves and flowers, Cowſlip leaves and flowers, Elder leaves and flowers, white Lilly flowers, St. <hi>Johns</hi> Wort, Ragwort, Mugwort, Sage, Neppe, Smalledge, Marjoram, Lavander, Southernwood, Roſemary, Roſe leaves blown, Rue, Lavander-Cotton, Featherfue, Tanſie, Lovage, Mints, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>momile, Time, Clary, Oake of Jeruſalem, Penny-Royal, Safron of the Willow, Hyſop, Balme, white Mints, Marygolds, Pyoney leaves, Bay-leaves, Dill: Take of each of theſe Hearbs a handfull, and bruiſe them in a morter, and put them in a pan, with a pottle of ſweet ſallet oyle, and a quart of white wine, then ſet it over the fire, and let it boyle ſoftly untill the wine be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed, ſtirring it all the while, then take it from
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:192126:60"/>the fire, and let it coole, when you anoynt here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, you muſt chafe it in by the fire, and apply next unto the place a piece of bladder, that the cloth drinke not up the oyle.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For a Ringworm in the neck.</head>
               <p>TAke Hounds tongue, that is white and dry, ſtamp it, and put it in an earthen pot with wine untill it be thick, ſpread it, and apply it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For the Sciatica.</head>
               <p>TAke a quart of the oyle of Trotters, and put thereto three handfuls of Neppe, two hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuls of Camomile, boyle them all on a ſoft fire, till it be very green, then ſtrain out the Hearbs, and put into it an ounce of Ginger finely beaten and fearced, and ſtir it together as it cooleth, and chafe the place that is grieved againſt the fire with this Oyntment both morning and evening.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For a Sore feſtred with bloud.</head>
               <p>TAke Lithurge of Gold four ounces, oyle Olive, yong Swines greaſe, each of them two ounces, green Copperas a quarter of an ounce, Ceruſe halfe an ounce, ſeeth them altogether on the fire conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually ſtirring them, and in the boyling put into
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:192126:61"/>it three ounces of white Wax, and when it is boyled to a pure white, take it off, and ſtir it till it be cold, there anoynt your hands with oyle and worke it up in Roles, wrap it in oyled Papers, and keep it in a cloſe box.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>A green Salve to heale any Sore.</head>
               <p>TAke Bores greaſe white waſhed and well drayned halfe a pound, of the leaves and flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of St. <hi>Johns</hi> Wort, and Knot-graſſe, each a handfull, of Aſhen leaves two handfuls, beat them firſt very ſmall, and then mingling them with the greaſe, beat them again, and boyle them a good ſpace, ſtirring them, then put in two oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of yellow Wax, and a ſpoonfull of Turpentine, ſo let theſe boyle a little, and then make it up.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>A Salve for a new wound.</head>
               <p>TAke Elecompane leaves, Engliſh Tobacco, the great Orpin, <hi>Jacobs</hi> Ladder, of each halfe a handfull, beat theſe in a morter very fine, then put to them above halfe a pound of barrows greaſe, beat them well together, untill the greaſe be very green, and then ſet them on a ſoft fire, a good ſpace, ſtirring it continually; then put to them yellow Wax and Rozen, of each one ounce, Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentine one ſpoonfull, Camphire and Allome, of
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:192126:61"/>each a little quantity, boyle them together, then take them off and ſtrain them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>A Medicine for the Ague to apply to the Wriſts.</head>
               <p>TAke nine leavs of red Sage, as much Rue, and about twenty leaves of ſtock Gilly flowers, cut all theſe very ſmall upon a trencher, then take two pieces of Calves leather, about four ſingers breadth, and ſpread the ſame with Venice Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentine, and upon the Turpentine ſpread the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſayd Hearbs, and upon the Hearbs you muſt ſcrape a Nutmeg, ſo lay it to the wriſts, an houre before the fit, and when you perceive the fit come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, let the party eate a toſt, ſopped in <hi>Aqua vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae</hi> and Pepper.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For the green ſickneſſe approved.</head>
               <p>TAke one ounce of the filings of ſteele, and ſteep it four dayes in the beſt wine vineger, then ſet it before the fire to dry, and then beat it to pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and ſearce it very ſmall; then take two oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Anniſeeds, and beat them, and ſearce them ſmall, and one ounce of fine Sugar, beaten and ſearced, then mingle them together, and put into it a ſpoonfull of powder of red Corrall, there muſt be thrice as much Anniſeeds and Sugar, as there
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:192126:62"/>is ſteele. They muſt take it in a morning faſting, as much as will lye upon a knives point at three times, and as much more two houres before ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and uſe ſome moderate exerciſe after it till they ſweat, after this take a Purge.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>A purging dyet Ale for the Dropſie, Scurvy, and to open the Liver and Spleen.</head>
               <p>TAke Dock roots, Madder roots Horſe-Radiſh roots, Smalledge roots, Polipody of the Oak, <hi>Sarſaparilla,</hi> Caper and Tamarak roots, of each two ounces, Egrimony Mayden haire, Ceterack, Tamarisk, Scurvy graſſe, Brook-lime, Water-creſſes, green Wormwood, each one good hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, <hi>Seua</hi> ſix ounces, Hermodactils, M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>choacan, Rhabarbe, Agarick, each one ounce, Anniſeeds, ſweet Fennel-ſeeds, Saſſafrace, and Liquoras, each one ounce, Cynomon, Ginger, Mace, each halfe an ounce, put all theſe in a bag, with two <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>adds of ſteele, and hang it in four gallons of new Ale, letting them worke together, with a pint of the juyce of Scurvy-graſſe, drinke hereof mornings and evenings.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>A Drinke for the Rickets.</head>
               <p>TAke a handfull of the barke of Ivy, as much of the barke of Ath, a good handfull of Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marisk,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:192126:62"/>put it into two gallons of Beere, and when it is a fortnight old, let the Child drinke it with meat, and at all times for ſix weekes, or two moneths, ſpring and fall; put in likewiſe Rhabarb one ounce ſliced, to this quantity of drink.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For the Plague.</head>
               <p>TAke three pints of Malmſey, or elſe Muska<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine, and boyle therein Sage and Rue, each a handfull, till a pint be waſted, then ſtrain it, and ſet it over the fire again, and put to it three penny worth of long Pepper, and halfe an ounce of Ginger, and a quarter of an ounce of Nutmegs, all beaten together; ſo let it boyle a little together, then put therein four penny worth of Mithridate, two penny worth of Treakle, and a quarter of a pint of Angelica water; take of this a ſpoonfull in the morning or evening and ſweat upon it, if the party be infected, it's effectuall; likewiſe for the ſmall Pox, Meaſles, Surfets, and ſuch like di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For old Wounds, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcers, Cankers, Scabs, Itch, or Fiſtulaes.</head>
               <p>TAke Virginia Tobacco ſtalkes one pound, ſpring water a gallon, boyle it to three pints, put it in a bottle, the longer you keep it the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter;
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:192126:63"/>the way to uſe it is, to wet a Linnen cloth in the water a little warmed, and ſo bath wel the wound or place, and then lay the wet cloth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; although this medicine be but cheape and homely, make uſe of it, and you wil confeſſe it a ſecret worthy your acceptance.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For the Megrim.</head>
               <p>TAke Bettony, Vervaine, Camomile, Feather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fue, Wormwood, Roſemary, each alike, put them into a bag, and ſeeth them in white wine, and lay them to the head as hot as you can ſuffer it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To procure eaſie delivery in Women.</head>
               <p>TAke Pippins, and cut them in thin ſlices, and fry them in a ſmal frying pan with oyle of ſweet Almonds, and let them eate thereof in the mornings, and at four of the clock in the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon, uſe it conſtantly til you are brought to bed, and anoynt the Belly and Matrix with oyle of ſweet Almonds, and <hi>Sperma caeti,</hi> mingled toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and warmed once every day, or more if you can conveniently.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>An Oyntment for Rheumatick Eyes.</head>
               <p>TAke Hogs Lard wel tryed ℥ ij, ſet to ſteep in red Roſe water ſix houres, then waſh it
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:192126:63"/>twelve times in white wine, wherein <hi>Lapis Tutiae</hi> and <hi>Lapis Caluminaris</hi> have been quenched; then adde the <hi>Caluminaris</hi> and <hi>Tutia,</hi> being heat red hot and quencht in white wine, as before ſix times, <hi>Ana</hi> ℥ ij. <hi>Lapis haematis</hi> ℈ ij. Aloes twelve graines, ſeed Pearle prepared ſix graines, mix it very well together, and adde a little Fennel water, as much as ſhal be neceſſary to make it liquid e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough. Anoynt the eye-lids herewith, it wil take away ſpots, or any thing that groweth about the eyes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For a Quinzie.</head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Album Grecum</hi> in powder, and a hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of Rue beat ſmal, boyle them in ſweet ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let oyle, til they become thick, then ſpread it on a cloth plaiſterwiſe, and apply it to the ſore from eare to eare.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>Againſt the trembling of the Heart, and Convulſion fits.</head>
               <p>TAke powder of Gold one penny worth, ſix penny weight of Amber, ſix penny weight of Pearle, ſix penny weight of Corrall, Bezoar five grains, halfe an ounce of Pioney root, twelve pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny weight of the skul of an Anatomy; make them all into powder, take as much as wil lie on a ſix pence in a ſpoonful of endive water every
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:192126:64"/>morning, and drinke a good draught after it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To boyle Turpentine, for the running of the Reynes.</head>
               <p>FIrſt waſh it, then boyle it in Plantane, or red Roſe water, til it come to the conſiſtence of Wax, then make it into pils, whereof take three or four when you go to bed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To prevent miſcarrying, and ſtop the Reds.</head>
               <p>TAke Clarret wine a quart, Mouſeare, Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards purſe, <hi>Ana M.</hi> 1. boyle it all together with a ſtick of Cynomon, and ſweeten it with Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, and drink a draught often warme.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To ſtay vomiting bloud by reaſon of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward bruiſe.</head>
               <p>QUench ſteele in milk, and drink it often, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ke <hi>Sperma Cati</hi> in any warm drink once or twice.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To breake a Boyle or Felon.</head>
               <p>TAke a great Onion, cut off the top, and take ſo much out of it as you may fil it up with halfe a ſpoonful of Treacle, and cover it with the piece again, bind it with a thread and roaſt it in
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:192126:64"/>the Embers in a brown paper, and when it is roa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, breake it and mingle it together, and apply it to the Boyle or Sore which you would have bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For a Child broken in the belly.</head>
               <p>TAke Polipody of the wall, Juniper Berries, Comphrey roots, the skin of the yolke of an egge, dry all theſe, and beat them to powder, then put therein a pint of good Ale, and give it every morning.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For the falling ſickneſſe.</head>
               <p>TAke Gold, Pearle, Corrall, Bezoar, and Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, <hi>ana</hi> ℈ 4. ſingle Pioney ſeeds as much, and ſingle Pioney roots a like quantity, in pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and take as much of the powder as will lie on a groat, in a ſpoonfull of white endive water, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry morning faſting, until a quarter of a pint of water be in ſuch manner ſpent.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For the Collick.</head>
               <p>TAke Figs good ſtore, and new Muſtard made with Vinegar, ſtamp them wel together, and put them into a linnen bag, and as hot as you can ſuffer it lay it on, and hold it to the Navel and Belly.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:192126:65"/>
               <head>For bleeding at Noſe.</head>
               <p>TAke Hempe, or a hempen halter, and weare it about your neck.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>A Water to take away Wheales, Puſhes, Ker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nels, Swellings, Bunches, and Warts.</head>
               <p>TAke oyle of bay two pound, white Frankin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſe, Maſtick, Gum Arabick, and Turpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, each ℥ iij. beat the Maſtick, Gum, and Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinſenſe, then mingle them altogether, diſtill them in a Limbeck; and after put into that water halfe a pound of the Aſhes of Earth burned, and then diſtill it again, and keep it as a treaſure to beſtow on your beſt friends.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>A Water for the head ach, and to cauſe reſt in weakneſs, or childbed women.</head>
               <p>TAke Primroſe leaves, and Wood Bettony, each <hi>M.</hi> 1. ſteepe them twelve houres in as much new milke as wil cover them; then ſtil them together, then ſteep in this water two good handfuls of Cowſlip flowers, and one good hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of Violet flowers, and one good handful of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet Hyſop; ſo let it ſtand four houres, then ſtil i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> altogether, and give ſix or eight ſpoonfuls at a
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:192126:65"/>time, warme with a little Sugar.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>An Oyntment to ſwage a ſwelled ſore Breaſt, or any other ſwelling.</head>
               <p>TAke Egremony and boyle it in Butter, or Hogs Lard, to an Oyntment, and therewith anoynt the ſwelled breaſt; alſo Egremony boyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in milke, and thicked up with bread and a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle honey put into it, and layd to the breaſt, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwages a hard ſwelled breaſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For bleeding Gums.</head>
               <p>TAke the thin ſhaving of a piece of Spaniſh Leather, and hold between the Gums, ſtayes it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For the dead Palſie.</head>
               <p>TAke foure penny worth of the horne that groweth in the inſide of a horſe knee, dryed and beat to powder; give it with two ſpoonfuls of the juyce of the green leaves of Perewinckles in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> fit, and let them drinke a draught of Sack after it, and ſweat, do this every other day for three dayes, and tie the ſtrings of the Perewinckle about the dead member, and ſhift them every other day; theſe ſtrings cure the cramp, being tyed on the grieved place.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:192126:66"/>
               <head>For the Gout ſtitches, and to open obſtructions, moſt excellent.</head>
               <p>℞. Halfe a pound of red Sanders, and ſteep it in a pint and a halfe of white wine, let it ſteep all night, the next morning ſtrain it and drink it; do this two or three dayes together, then forbeare it as long; after take it againe, in halfe a ſcore times taking, it hath cured thoſe of the Gout, which for three years together have not been able to go; it doth worke upwards and downwards, and wil for a little time make them ſick, but is moſt harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For a Pluriſie of winde.</head>
               <p>TAke Horſe-dung, Camomile, and Parſley fry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Butter and Vineger, and apply it hot as may be ſuffered, divers times, or wet Rye meale in the parties water, and make a Cake of it; ſlit the Cake in the middle, and ſpread it with London Treacle, and apply it to the ſide.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For the Wind, Mother, or Convulſions.</head>
               <p>TAke Corral, Amber, and Jet, <hi>ana</hi> like weight beat them into fine powder, take the quantity of an Hazel Nut, and put it into a ſpoone wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſome Cawdle or Broth; take two or thre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="117" facs="tcp:192126:66"/>ſpoonfuls in a morning, and eat not in two or three houres after.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>A ſoveraigne Water for old <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcers.</head>
               <p>TAke two penny worth of pure white Coppe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras, put into it a pint of pure Spring water, ſet it on a ſoft fire, that it may only ſimper, take off the ſcum with a Feather; ſo ſoon as the Coppe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras is diſſolved take it off, and put it into a glaſſe, or ſtone bottle, the longer it is kept the better it wil be.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe this defenſive Plaiſter.</head>
               <p>BOle Armonick, the white of an Egge, and white wine Vineger, and to keep the Orifice open, put into it Gentian Wood.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For heat in the Back.</head>
               <p>TAke juyce of Lemmons and Vineger, and dip a cloth in it, and apply it to the back often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For the head ach.</head>
               <p>TAke oyle of Wormwood, ſtrong Vineger, and Roſe water, and mingle them together, and boyle them, and lay them as hot as you may ſuffer it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:192126:67"/>
               <head>To dry up a Sore that iſſues with water.</head>
               <p>TAke Ale or Beer, and boyle in it Sage til it be ſtrong, then put in a ſmal quantity of Allome and Hony, and bath the part ill affected, and lay of the Sage leaves that were boyled on the ſore place.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For the Mother.</head>
               <p>TAke about Michaelmas time the ripeſt and rankeſt Nettle ſeeds you can get, dry them in the Sun, or in an Oven, and ſo keep them cloſe in a paper, and when the Patient feeles the Mother to riſe, take a ſpoon heaped of theſe ſeed, beat in a morter, in white wine or Beer, and let them drink it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For the Piles.</head>
               <p>℞. White Starch in powder, and put on the Piles, or a great Onyon roſt it, ſpread it flat, and ſpread it over with Mithridate, and apply it warm.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For the Rickets.</head>
               <p>TAke ſallet Oyle one pint, Cammomile with the flowers three handfulls, ſtrip it from the ſtalkes, boyle one handfull firſt, in the Oyle and take it up, then the ſecond and the third, then put
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:192126:67"/>the Cammomile into a bags; and anoint the ſides ſtriking it downwards with the Oyle, then lay on the bags warme, anoint it twice a day where the knots are, and lay ſpeedewell in their drinke continually, then take a purge of Rhabarb, five or ſixe graines in powder, in poſſet uſe it nine dayes together, then ceaſe a fortnight and uſe it againe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>An oyntment for the Rickets.</head>
               <p>TAke Roſemary, Bayleaves, Cammomile, tops of Lavender, Alehoof, unſet Hiſop, unſet time <hi>ana</hi> Mr. ſhred together; and beate in a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and boyled together in a pound of freſh butter an houre, then ſtraine it out, and with this anoynt the Child, his ſides, knees, and downe to his feet, Evening and Morning, a quarter of an houre, this muſt be made in May. Take cloves of Fox ferne root <hi>alias oſmond</hi> bruiſed and boyled in milke, take it in the morning faſting, and faſt an houre after it, and make the root in powder and give it in Beere.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>Sirrup for the Rickets.</head>
               <p>TAke running water, one quart, Mayden haire, Sage of Ieruſalem, Coltsfoot each one ounce, Licoras ſliced, Anniſeeds bruiſed, <hi>ana,</hi> halfe an ounce, boyle all theſe to the halfe, then ſtraine it, put to it fine Sugar, a pound and a half, pearle pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:192126:68"/>℥ iij boyle altogether, then ſtraine it and give your Childe one ſpoonefull firſt and laſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>Pils to ſtay vomitting and cleanſe the ſtomacke.</head>
               <p>TAke Alloes <hi>Siccatrina,</hi> adde to it Nutmeg grated, two or three drops of Sallet Oyle, as much <hi>Aquavitae,</hi> and a little Sirrup of Roſes when it is diſsolved together, put a droppe of Oyle on your fingers, make it in Pils, whereof take two in a morning.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>The Palſie oyle to make to anoynt twice a day for any ach or benummedneſs.</head>
               <p>TAke Neats-foot oyle, Roſemary tops, ſweet Marjoram, of each two handfuls, Lavander tops or leaves, before it ſhoot to blow two hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuls, red Sage, Camomile, Wormwood, Time, and Hyſop, each one handful, chop them ſmal and put them to the oyle, and let them boyle apace til the Hearbs be changed, and the Oyntment of a fair green colour, then ſtrain it out, and keep it in a Glaſſe cloſe ſtopt for uſe, it wil-laſt ſeven yeares in its ful force and vertue; if you cannot have the Lavander green when you would uſe it, you may take it dry, and likewiſe the other hearbs, but then you muſt take the greater quantity; I made this Oyntment at Michaelmas laſt, for one who
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:192126:68"/>was ſuddainly ſtroken in her limbs, ſo that ſhe was not able to ſtand, and was afflicted with violent pain; it was on the Sabboth day ſhe was taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout ten in the morning, I prepared the Medicine by two in the afternoon, wherewith ſhe was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noynted, and (by Gods bleſſing) was very wel by night, and ſo hath continued. Δόξ τῳ Θεῷ. It was at <hi>Wokingham,</hi> where I was unprovided of the Hearbs, in my own Garden, where I had not much reſidence (though too long for my purſe) and I was enforced to buy them at a Gard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, who ſhewed me an exact <hi>Wokingham</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and as moſt of that Town do, he made a vertue of my urgent neceſſity, and made me pay ſawce for my Hearbs, although you would judge them but of ſmal price; this I record here, only to learn others to beware of <hi>Wokingham,</hi> leſt they pay for it as deare as I have done.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For the Stone in the Kidneyes, and them that make bloudy water.</head>
               <p>TAke milke and make a clear Poſſet, wherein boyle a handful of Plantain, a ſtick or two of Licoras, a ſlice or two of Comphrey root, drinke thereof firſt and laſt, and ſometimes drinke the juce of Plantain by it ſelfe, or in Beer. Take alſo Pils of Turpentine waſht in Plantain water, and made up in Pils with Gum Arabick, and wrapt up
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:192126:69"/>in Sugar or Conſerve of Roſes, and ſwallowed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For a Burn or Scald.</head>
               <p>TAke thorne Apple leaves, ſtampe them or cut them ſmal, and boyle them in Hogs Lard to an Oyntment. <hi>Probatum.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>Jay powder for the falling ſickneſs.</head>
               <p>TAke a Jay, pul off the Feathers, then take out the guts, and fil it ful with Comminſeeds and Anniſeeds, and then bake it til it is dry to beat to powder, with the head on and legs, drinke this in Porrage or Ale.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>
                  <hi>Flos Unguentorum,</hi> or the flower of Oyntments.</head>
               <p>TAke Rozen, Perozen, each halfe a pound, <hi>Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banum,</hi> Deeres ſuet, or Sheeps ſuet, and white Wax, of each four ounces, Maſtick and Mirrhe, of each an ounce, Venice Turpentine two ounces, white wine a pottle; your Wax and Suet being finely ſhred, muſt be firſt molten upon a ſoft fire, then put in your Rozen and Perozen, and ſtir them wel til they be melted, then ſtrain the ſtuffe into a hot pan, then have ready your <hi>Olibanum,</hi> Maſtick, and Mirrhe, ground ſmal and finely ſearced, and
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:192126:69"/>let it all melt together, your whitewine being ſomething warm, poure in by little and little, then take it from the fire, and put in the Turpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, and ſtir it, and laſt of all the Camphire in powder, and ſtir it til it be cold, and make it up in Roles, and keepe it in red Leather to your uſe, as the beſt and moſt precious Salve that can be made.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Virtues of it.</head>
                  <p>THis Medicine is good for all manner of Diſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, following, <hi>viz.</hi> for all wounds, and it is moſt cleanſing, and wel ſoken, and gendreth fleſh, and ſuffereth no corruption in a wound, nor no e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil fleſh to be gendred therein; it is good for the head ach, and ſingings in the brain, for all manner of Impoſtumes, for ſounding in the eares, and for ſinews that are ſprung or cut, and draweth out a broken bone, or thorne, or any thing that is in a wound; it is good for biting or ſtinging of a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemous Beaſt, and it healeth all manner of Bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches without, it is good for a Feſter, Canker, <hi>noli me tangere,</hi> it draweth out all ach of the Liver, Spleen, or Reines, healeth the Emrods, and is a good Seare-cloth for Gouts, and peſtilent Diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:192126:70"/>
               <head>The manner how to cut the Plaiſters of this Medicine to cure theſe Diſeaſes under written, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>For the Navell three inches ſquare, to ſtay the Flux of the Belly.</p>
               <p>For the Reines ſix inches long, four inches broad, to ſtay the Flux of the Reynes.</p>
               <p>For the Stomack four inches broad, ſix inches deep, it muſt be cut three ſquare, for wind or pain in the ſtomack.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For ſhortneſſe of breath or Ptiſike.</head>
               <p>TAke eight or nine heads of Garlicke, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the conſtitution of the party, peele and cut off both the ends of each Clove, and put it into a pipkin; with a quarter of a pound of but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter unſalted, boyle it untill the Garlicke turnred, then run it thorow ſuch a thing as a milke ſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, then put it into a pipkin: againe, with a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of a pound of butter more unſalted, and the beſt honey one pound, boyle it till the skim is wel riſen, then take it off and skimme it, and ſtrow in an ounce of the powder of Elecompane roots, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> let it boyle three or foure walmes, take it off the fire, and ſtirre in the powder of ſix penny-worth of ſaffron, from the firſt to the laſt, you muſt ſtirre
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:192126:70"/>it while it is boyling except the time, while the skim of the honey is riſing, eate the quantity of a ſmall nutmeg hereof, evening and morning.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For ſcabs in Childrens heads.</head>
               <p>TAke freſh butter, and boyle in it ſoote of a Chimney (where is no Seacole burned) till it be blacke, and therewith anoynt the head, it will heale it though there be holes you may turne your finger in the head.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For a ſwellyng or bruiſe.</head>
               <p>Take Elder ſtampt aod fryed with Chamberly, and freſh buttr, and layd all over it, taketh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way a ſwelling or bruiſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For the Lungs, and Gonorrhea.</head>
               <p>TAke Crawfiſhes, and boyle them in milk, and eate them, and drinke the milke firſt and laſt, and in the afternoone ſweetned with Sugar.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For a perrillus Cough.</head>
               <p>TAke Sage, Rue, Commin, and powder of pepper and ſeeth them in honey; and make there of an electuary and uſe thereof a ſpoonfull, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:192126:71"/>and morning.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>Stinging of an adder or ſnake.</head>
               <p>DRinke the diſtilled water of Draggons, or the juyce, alſo ſtampe dragons and lay to the place. &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To procure eaſie delivery.</head>
               <p>TAke Hyſop, Vervaine, and betony, of each one handfull, ſtampe them very ſmall, and ſtraine them in good ſtale Ale; and let the Patient drinke a good draught thereof, and it will helpe her pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently without danger.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To heale a ſcald or burne.</head>
               <p>TAke barley meale, with the Juice of red fennel, make a plaiſter thereof and lay it on the ſore, and it will draw out the corruption and heale it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>Flux of Bloud to ſtay.</head>
               <p>TAke Willow leaves and barke, and boyle it in wine, and drink it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <pb n="127" facs="tcp:192126:71"/>
               <head>For noyſe in the eares, or tongue ſwelled.</head>
               <p>BOyle Figs in Water, and let the Patient drinke thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To purge the head with Ceny.</head>
               <p>TAke Cene in powder ℥ i. Ginger ℥ i. twelve Cloves, Fennel ſeeds ℥ ij. Cinamon, &amp; tartar, each halfe a drachme, beate them all into powder, take thereof in white-wine a drachme before ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For itch, ſcabs, and the like.</head>
               <p>TAke fumitory and boyle it in a quart of ale, then infuſe in it. Sena. ounce, Raiſins of the Sun ſtoned, Anniſeeds bruiſed, and a little ginger, drinke it with ſirrup of Roſes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>A Balſome for wounds, ſwellings, venom, bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, and Apoſtumations, oldſores, fretting ulcers. &amp;c.</head>
               <p>TAke Oyle olive one quart, St. Iohns-wort, betony, Centory and ſelfe heale, each two handfulls, ſtampe them and mixe them well, and ſo let it ſtill in a glaſſe all Summer, and then ſtraine the Oyle from the hearbs and ſoe keepe it
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:192126:72"/>for uſe: Adde to it Tobacco flowers.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To heale watring Eyes.</head>
               <p>TAke red Roſe water, two ounces, and put it into a bowle glaſſe, then take male Frankin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſe, put it on the point of a Knife into a Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of Uirgins Wax, untill it begin to melt, then ſtill dip it in the water, at leaſt a hundred times, untill it turn thick, like Balm, diſtrain it through a fine linnen cloth, and anoynt your eyes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To expell Rheume in the face.</head>
               <p>TAke the white of an Egge beat to an Oyle, and skimmed, then temper it with the Wool of a Conies skin to a plaiſter, warm it on coales, and apply it to the temples, and the grieved place, and bind it on faſt with a cloth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For the Chollick, or griping in the belly.</head>
               <p>TAke the ſeed of <hi>Carduus benedictus</hi> ſtamped and drunke in Poſſet Ale, or any other drinke, doth help the griefe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For the Paſſion of the Heart.</head>
               <p>TAke juyce of Bugloſſe two ounces, cleanſe and purifie it at the fire, mix it with two
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:192126:72"/>drachms, of white Sugar-Candy, and let the Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent drinke it every night going to bed ten nights together.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To purge choller.</head>
               <p>TAke ſirrup of Violets with Agarick infuſed in Barly water, or broth of a Hen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>A Purge for the Kings Evill.</head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Lignum vitae</hi> four ounces, infuſe it in Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers in four quarts of ſpring water twenty four houres, then adde to it Poſipodian foure oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, <hi>Sena</hi> two ounces, Anniſeeds and ſweet Fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel ſeeds, <hi>anae</hi> halfe an ounce, Burrage, Bugglos, and Fox-Gloves, each a handfull, boyle it a way to the halfe, then give four or five ſpoonfuls to a childe every morning for eight dayes together ſweetned with Sugar.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For the Dropſie.</head>
               <p>TAke Broome. Bettony, Balme, <hi>anae</hi> three hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuls, put it into three gallons of Ale Wort, when it is ready to be ſtopt up; let it ſtand a weeke, and then drink it conſtantly a weeke toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or a fortnight.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:192126:73"/>
               <head>An excellent Medicine for the Dropſie.</head>
               <p>TAke Horſe-Radiſh roots fliced long wayes thin, two ounces, ſweet Fennel-ſeeds bruiſed ℥ ij. Smalledge and Fennel roots ſliced, each one ounce, the tops of Time, Winter Savory, ſweet Marjoram, Water Creſſes, Nettles, of each one handfull; boyle theſe in three pints of water and three pints of wine, a quart of Canary, and a pint of Muskadine cloſe covered til halfe be conſumed; ſo remove it from the fire and let it ſettle three houres, then ſtrain it, and into every draught put in an ounce of ſirrup of the five roots, it muſt be taken twice a day, in the morning, and at three in the afternoon, and faſt an houre after it; if the Patient have the ſcurvy alſo, adde to the draughts two ſpoonfuls of the juyce of ſcurvy graſſe, when the Patient is ready to drink it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>The Oyntment for the Dropſie.</head>
               <p>TAke Walwort, and Elder leaves, ſweet Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joram, and Water Creſſes, Penny Royal, each one handfull cut and bruiſed, and ſet them to ſeeth in aquart of ſweet ſallet oyle, halfe an houre, then let them ſtand in the veſſell three dayes, then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain heat them and ſtrain it hard out, and put into it as many more of the ſayd Hearbs, and ſeeth them
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:192126:73"/>as before, and ſtraine it; do ſo the third time, and keep it as an excellent Oyntment; let the ſwoln body be annointed therewith once in three dayes, and that in the morning by a good fire, ſtroking it downwards an houre together.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For a ſore breaſt in great anguiſh.</head>
               <p>TAke Dung of Geeſe the neweſt you can get, and the like of Doves, and a little Leaven, and a little Time; ſtamp them together, and lay them to the breaſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For a Bruiſe.</head>
               <p>TAke Red-Nettles, and a quantity of Bay-ſalt, bruiſe them together, and lay them to the ſore, or bruiſe: this muſt be applied incontinently af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter one is bruiſed, and often changed, it will aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwage the paine, and heale the bruiſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To ſtay bleeding at the Noſe.</head>
               <p>TAke the bone in a Carps head, and beat it to powder, and take a little of the bloud of the party, and beat it to powder, then mingle it toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and put it in a little Ale or Beer, and let them drink it once or twice.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:192126:74"/>
               <head>For the ſame.</head>
               <p>LEt the Patient drink Wine-vinegar, and dip a Napkin in Wine-vinegar, and apply to his pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy Members.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For a cold Stomack, and hot Liver.</head>
               <p>TAke halfe a pinte of White-wine, aſmuch Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitory water, let them halfe one walme to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and ſweeten it with Syrrup of Violets, take of it as you ſee cauſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For the Falling-ſickneſs.</head>
               <p>TAke Piony roots in Powder, in Ale, drink it both morning and evening, take the Jay-pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der alſo in Porrage, and drink Ale before it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>An excellent Oyntment for the Spleene, or Spraine, or for Winde, or Stitch in the ſide, &amp; good for any inward bruiſe, to annoynt outwardly.</head>
               <p>An old Judge going off his Horſe back, broke a veine, and ſpit bloud, and piſt bloud, and this oyntment cured him, by annoynting him.</p>
               <pb n="133" facs="tcp:192126:74"/>
               <p>TAke S. Johns wort two handfuls, ſweet Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joram, Sweet Bazil, Mints, or Speremmts, Flowers of Lavender ſpike, and red Roſe leaves, each one handfull, Maudlin and wild Time, each halfe a handfull compound them well together in a ſtone Mortar, then put into them a pinte of the beſt Sallet Oyle, in a veſſell cloſe ſtopt, and ſet it in a place where it may have moderate heat fourteen dayes, then ſtrain it and put into it halfe a pinte of Malmſey, Nu megs halfe an ounce, large Mace halfe an ounce, and a pretty quantity of Cynamon, boyle all theſe together till the liquor be nigh halfe ſpent, and ſtraine it out, and ſo uſe it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For paine in the Head.</head>
               <p>CHew Mace in your mouth, and hold it that the Fume may aſcend, and ſmell to Spikenard.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For the ſame.</head>
               <p>TAke Vervaine, Vinegar, and Honey, mingle them well together, and drinke it often times faſting.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For the Megrim.</head>
               <p>SEeth a little quantity of Aloes and Maſtick in white Wine, and drink thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <pb n="134" facs="tcp:192126:75"/>
               <head>Againſt Drunkenneſſe.</head>
               <p>TAke before you drink twelve ſpoonfuls of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tony Water, and after drinke as much as you will.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For a Worme in the Somack.</head>
               <p>TAke Nepp, ſtamp it and mingle it with white Wine, and give the Patient when he is grieved.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For ſcalding, burning, itch, ſcabs, ſcald head, or any heat.</head>
               <p>TAke butter unwaſht, melt it ſcalding hot, then powre it into faire ſpring water, and with a ſpoone labour it and waſh it, untill the butter grow cold, then gather the butter together, and powre out that water, and put freſh water to the butter, till you finde the butter very white, then worke the water out of the butter, then worke in the powder of brimſtone finely beaten, untill the butter be ſtiffe, and looks yellow with it, then take Camphire, and the ſeed of Pompeyons clean picked and husked, grinde the Campheire and them together, and worke it to the butter, and ſo uſe it; but if you will skin any burne with it, adde to it the powder of a rotten poſt, elſe not.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <pb n="135" facs="tcp:192126:75"/>
               <head>For the Piles approved.</head>
               <p>TAke a little piece of ſcarlet and burne it, and beat it to powder, and ſearce it, and put to it a little Honey, and annoint the party therewith, alſo take Horehound, and Hagtaper in powder fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting foure or five mornings together.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For a Chin-cough.</head>
               <p>TAke the Burre of an Eglantine tree, and dry it in powder, and drink it in poſſit drinke.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>The moſt excellent Plaiſter, called Leaden Plaiſter.</head>
               <p>TAke two pound and four ounces of Oyle-olive the beſt, good red Lead 1 <abbr>lb</abbr>. white Lead 1 <abbr>lb</abbr>. beaten to duſt, Spaniſh Sope ℥ xij. incorporate them in an earthen pot, and when the Sope com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth upward, put it upon a ſmall fire of coales, continuing it an houre and an halfe ſtirring it with an iron or ſtick, then drop of it upon a trencher, if it cleave not it is enough, ſpread it on cloaths, or lay it on a board till it cooles, then rowle it up, it will laſt twenty yeares, the older the better.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="136" facs="tcp:192126:76"/>
                  <head>The vertues of this Plaiſter.</head>
                  <p>THe ſame laid on the ſtomack provokes appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite, and takes away any griefe in the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack, it is a preſent remedy for the Collick, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing laid on the belly; and upon the back it's good for the bloudy Flux, Gonorrhea, and all weakneſs in the back; for Women with child to weare all the time they are with childe, if they finde any weakneſſe; it healeth all ſwellings, bruiſes, and aches; it breaks Felons, Puſhes, and other Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtumes, and healeth the ſame, draweth out any rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten humour, not breaking the skin, and applyed to the Fundament, healeth any diſeaſe there grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; the ſame laid to the temple is good for the Evelo, head-ach, and the eyes eaſeth Corns, the Gowt, and for a ſtraine. <hi>Prohatum.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For a bruiſe on the Stones.</head>
               <p>TAke mud of a Grind-ſtone, and Oyle of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes tempered together, and ſpread on a cloath, and apply it to the place grieved.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For the Dropſie.</head>
               <p>TAke Hyſope, Thime, Water-creſſes, and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamint, each two handfuls, Fennell one hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:192126:76"/>Raddiſh roots foure or five taken out of the ground freſh, and ſlice them thin, Licoras, Anni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeds, and Comminſeeds, each two ounces, boyle all theſe together in a pan or pot, with the quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of three Gallons of faire running water, till a third part be conſumed, then put in a pottle of Sack, ſtrain it all through a linnen cloath, then put it into a glaſſe or ſtone bottle, cloſe ſtopt, drink of it every morning, and at foure of the clock in the afternoone, and as you find good of it, continue it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To coole the Liver.</head>
               <p>TAke Barley water, caſt away the firſt, and in the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d boyle Cinquefoil, Burnet, Strawber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryleaves, Burrage, Sorrell, Egrimony, each one handfull, boyle it from a Pottle to three pintes and ſomething more, ſtraine it, and adde to it two ſpoonfuls of Syrrup of Violets, and one ſpoonfull of Roſe-water, drinke it morning and evening, it cooles the Liver, and makes the body ſoluble.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For diſplacing the Mother, or Whites with a Serringe.</head>
               <p>TAke Cynamon bruiſed one ounce, Pomegra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate flowers halfe an ounce, red Roſe leaves a quarter of an ounce, boyle theſe in a pinte and a halfe of red Roſe water, till halfe be conſumed,
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:192126:77"/>then addered Wine halfe a pinte, and ſtraine it for your uſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>A Receipt of pills.</head>
               <p>TAke white Amber, maſtick, each one drachim, Aloes the beſt, two drachmes and a halfe, aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick two ſcruples, <hi>Ariſtolechia</hi> the round and true, one ſcruple, make them all in fine powder, and with a little Iuyce of Bettony or ſirrup make them in pils, make five of a drachme and take two three or five going to bed.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The virtue of theſe pills.</head>
                  <p>THey preſerve the ſtomack from inward hurt, and ſuffer no ill humors to putrifie in it, for they cleanſe, mundifie, and ſtrengthen the heart, ſtomack and head, make the party cheerefull, they purge the veines, and matrix, and helpe the eyes, they are ſafe without any danger.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For aſore throat.</head>
               <p>TAke plantaine, and boyle it in running water to a pultis, and clap it hot to the throat with a cloth, this cured one that could hardly ſpeak, ſcarce ſwallow, and made him avoyde peeces of ſtinking fleſh out of his throat.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <pb n="139" facs="tcp:192126:77"/>
               <head>An oyntment for a joynt Ague.</head>
               <p>TAke Colewort leaves, chopt and boyled in butter to an oyntment, ſtraine it and anoynt the place ill therewith, or boyle Ale to an oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and anoynt the place with it, the ſame is good for Chilblanes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To skin nipples.</head>
               <p>TAke yong Bayleaves, bruiſed and layd on the nipples, skinnes them; alſo <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nguentum Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bum</hi> is good for the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For the ſame.</head>
               <p>TAke pure fine Sugar, and burnt allum and plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine water, and a little red Roſe water, boyle altogether to a ſirrup, dip fine ragges in it and lay about the nipples till it be whole, likewiſe take butter and wax, and lay it on the nipples being melted together.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>Unguentum Album, <hi>to make.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke hogs Lard and waſh it in Plantaine wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or red Roſe water, and mingle them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with white Ceris and white leade.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <pb n="140" facs="tcp:192126:78"/>
               <head>A gargle for the throat for flegme.</head>
               <p>TAke Muſtard a ſpoonefull, three or foure ſpoonfull of white Wine, mingle them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, uſe it every morning for flegme, likewiſe Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neger and Water is good for the ſame; but if it bee for the Palſey, take Muſtard, white Wine, Vineger and Honey, and gargle at night going to bed warme.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For the Morphew.</head>
               <p>TAke Pippins, and Elder berries baked toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or you may ſtill it, and drinke the water, becauſe you cannot have the berries at all times.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To help fainting fits in lying in.</head>
               <p>BOyle Harts horne and Safron in Ale or Beere, and put a little Sugar to it, and drinke it, adde to it a little winter Savory.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For the Palſey, and to ſtay Rhume.</head>
               <p>TAke a quart of Ale, boyle in it Lavender, and put to it a little butter and Sugar, this drinke morning and evening.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <pb n="141" facs="tcp:192126:78"/>
               <head>For the Yellow Jaundies moſt excellent in great extremity.</head>
               <p>TAke Engliſh Safron two penny worth in fine powder, two penny worth of Turmerick in powder, and two penny worth of Mace in pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, mingle it with as much fine Sugar as you like to your taſte, eat every morning and evening as much in the pap of an apple as three Nuts, if you take a purge of Rhabarb after, it is good, or uſe Rhabarb in powder with the reſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For one that piſſes bloud.</head>
               <p>TAke Oyle of ſweet Almonds new drawn, and put a little fine Sugar into it, or white Sugar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>candy, and take of it firſt and laſt, likewiſe Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentine waſht in Plantaine water, and made up in Pills, with red Roſe leaves, and a little Corrall; firſt purge the Reines with Caſſia and Rhabarb.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>A Clyſter for the bloudy Flux.</head>
               <p>TAke three pints of skimmed milk, put it in a Baſon, then take three gags of Steele, and heate them red hot, and quench them in the milke 3 times, then take a ſpoonfull of old conſerve of red Roſes, beat it into the milke, and then take
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:192126:79"/>the yolke of one egge and beate it and ſtirre it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the milke, then ſtraine it and give aſmuch as will agree with the conſtitution of the partye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>An approved Searecloth for aches.</head>
               <p>TAke Burgundy pitch, halfe a pounde, white Virgins wax one quarter of a pound, white Frankinſenſe, two ounces, let the Frankinſenſe be beaten, and ſearced very ſmall, then take the wax and the pitch and melt them, in two ſeverall pipkins, and when they are melted powre the wax into the pitch, then ſtrow in the Frankinſenſe, ſtirr them well together, powre all into a baſon of faire water and worke it up into Rowels, with your hands anoynted with butter for ſticking.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To comfort the hart.</head>
               <p>TAke two handfulls of Burrage leaves, and two handfulls of Bugloſſe, one handfull of white Endive, halfe a handfull of Roſemary, halfe a handfull of time, aſmuch of Savory and Hiſope, boyle all theſe in three pints of faire Water till halfe be waſted, then put in one pound and an half of Sugar, and a few whole Cloves, halfe an ounce of Cynomon, a quarter of an ounce of Ginger, finely beaten, then boyle it till it come to the thickeneſſe of life Honey, and ſo reſerve it in gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:192126:79"/>pots: and take aſmuch as a Haſell nut every morning and when you pleaſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For a Conſumption.</head>
               <p>TAke a fat ſow Pigge, dreſſe it, and put it into a ſtill, with a handfull of Speeremints, aſmuch red Fenell, and as much red Nepp, Liverwort, and Clary, each halfe a handfull and new Oates, new dates the Stones and pith taken out and well waſhed in two or three waters, halfe a quarter of an ounce of Mace, two ſticks of Cynomon bruiſed, diſtill altogether with an eaſie fire, and put it in a ſure glaſſe, and ſunne it nine dayes and drinke of it at your pleaſure. For the winde or gripings in the belly, take Anniſeeds, ſweet Fennell ſeeds each one ſpoonefull, Licoris, Pepper, Elecompane roots, each one drachm, a ſmall quantity of Saffron all in powder, a quarter of an ounce of nutmegs grated, too grains of musk, waigh all theſe ingredients to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and put to them their double weight of fine Sugar, then incorporate them with aſmuch damaske Roſe water as will make them liquid; then put it up in a Galley Pot and take a ſmall quantity therof, on the point of a knife in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning or at any other time when the winde offends you, it muſt be tempered cold and not boyled.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <pb n="144" facs="tcp:192126:80"/>
               <head>For a ſcald head.</head>
               <p>TAke a penny worth of lampe Oyle, and halfe a pint of faire water, and boyle it well toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and when it is cold, put thereto a halfe pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny worth of quickſilver, and temper it well toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and anoint the head.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For the black Jaundies.</head>
               <p>TAke Gentian, long Pepper, Calamus Aroma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticus, Avenus, Lycoris, Rayſins, Corants, white Spaniſh Sope, of each three ounces, two ſpoonfulls of muſtard, boyle all theſe in a quart of wine till the third part be waſted, and let the Patient drinke it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>For St. Anthonies fire.</head>
               <p>TAke and roſt Sorrell in a wet linnen cloth, the ſpace of halfe an houre underthe hot embers, hen ſtamp it with fine Clarified Honey, and lay it to the ſore, it ill heale it perfectly.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="145" facs="tcp:192126:80"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Of the twelve Signes.</hi> The diviſion, nature, and expoſitions of the twelve ſignes of the <hi>Zodiack,</hi> according to the twelve months in the yeare.</head>
            <p>THE Ancients have given the Signes of Heaven certain names of living Creatures and briefe Characters, to prevent tediouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in the often writing of them; they are Charactered thus: ♈ ♉ ♊ ♋ ♌ ♍ ♎ ♏ ♐ ♑ ♒ ♓</p>
            <p>Theſe twelve Signes are divided into four parts, according to the foure quarters of the yeare; the three firſt Signes containe the Vernall, or Spring Quarter, and the ſanguine Complexion of m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n.</p>
            <p>The 4.5. &amp; 6. Signes, the Summer Quarter, and is hot and dry of the Chollerick Complexion.</p>
            <p>The ſeven eight and nine Signes containe the Autumnall or Harveſt Quarter, and is cold and dry of the Melancholly Complexion.</p>
            <p>The three laſt or ten eleaven and twelve Signes containe the Brumall, Hiemall, or winter Quarter,
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:192126:81"/>&amp; of the flegmatique complexion Cold and moiſt.</p>
            <p>Aries, or the Ram is the firſt of all the Signes, it is Maſculine, Diurnall, Chollerick, Fiery, and Hot, and by peculiar property dry; by his heate and quickning preſerving life, fit for the nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all things Animall and Vegetable, he is Moveable, equinoctiall. Vernall, of the fiery Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity, Orientall and the Diurnall houſe of ♂, he ruleth the head and face, the moneth of March, wherein it is good to let bloud, and purge. Vnder this Signe falleth head-each, ſmall-Pox Megrims, falling Sickneſſe, and all diſeaſes of the head.</p>
            <p>The ſecond ſigne is Taurus, or the Bull, which is Melancholly, Cold, and Dry, Feminine, Noc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnall of the earthly Triplicity, is Temperate, Profitable to the earth and Flowers, it is Meridio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall and the night houſe of Venus, it ruleth the Neck and Throat, the moneth of Aprill, in which it is perrilous to have ſickneſſe in the Throat, as the Kings Evill, Wenns, Boyles, Quinſies and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtumes.</p>
            <p>Third Signe is Geminy, which is hot and moiſt, affecting the Aire with temperature, comforting nature, producing the ſeeds to fruits, it is a Signe Sanguine, Maſculine. Diurnall, Occidentall, dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble bodied, Dexter Common, and aircall, the day houſe of Mercury, of the Airy Triplicity, he ruleth the moneth of May, wherein it is indifferent to let bloud and take Phyſicke, he ſignifies all diſeaſes
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:192126:81"/>in the ſhoulders Armes, and hands, and deſcribes a man to be upright and tall, of a Sanguine Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion, darke haire, a good ſight, a ſharp wit and judicious underſtanding.</p>
            <p>The forth Signe is Cancer or the Crabbe, cold or moiſt, Temperate, apt for the nutrition of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, having a comfortable humidity and tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rature, whereby all things both Animall and Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getable doe live and are maintained, it's a Signe Feminine, Nocturnall, Moveable, Solſtitiall, and northerne, of the watery triplicity, the houſe of the Moone. It hath the moneth of Iune, ill to take Phyſicke or let bloud unleſſe neceſſity require, it ruleth the breaſt, ſtomacke ribs, and ſpleene, ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies imperfections in the ſtomack, ptiſicke, ſalt flegme, dropſies, impoſtumes and Cancets in the breaſt, renders a man to be of a ſmall, low ſtature, round viſage, ſickely, pale, melancholly complex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion, the haire a ſad browne, little eyes, if a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, apt to have many Children.</p>
            <p>The firſt ſigne is Leo, or the Lyon, by nature hot, chollerick, of the fiery triplicity, ſo farr from tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perature, that with it, nature beginneth to move the dimunition of the leaves of the trees, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batement of fruits tending to their decay, it is maſculine, diurnall and orientall, the onely houſe of the Sun, it hath the moneth of Iuly, rules the back, ſinews, bones, and griſtles, and ſignifies the diſeaſes thereof, as trembling and paſſions of the
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:192126:82"/>heart, peſtilent feavers, the plague, and paines in the backe, and pluriſies; it repreſents perſons of large bodies, broad ſhoulders, ſomething tall ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, great head, big goggle eyes, yellow or darke flaxen haire, curling, a fierce countenance, a ruddy ſanguine complexion, it is evill in the moneth of Iuly (unles extremity force it) to give Phyſicke or let bloud.</p>
            <p>The ſixt Signe of the Zodiacke is Virgo, which is a bicorporeal or double bodies Signe; the influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence thereof upon the earth worketh cold and dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, hardly temperate, through which vegeta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, ſuffer detriment, hearbs and leaves do wither yet the coldneſſe thereof is not altogether exempt from temperature, it's of the earthly triplicity the houſe of exaltation of Mercury, it is feminine, nocturnall meridionall, melancholly, right com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and dexter. It hath the moneth of Auguſt wherein it is evill to give phyſicke, or let bloud: it ruleth the wombe, bowels, guts, liver, gall, and mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>te, and the diſeaſes thereof, as the wormes, winde, collicke, paine in the guts and miſeraicke veines. It denotes a meane ſtature, ſlender body, but decent, ruddy browne complexion, blacke haire, ſhrill ſmall voice, witty, ingenious, and ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious, a rare underſtanding in man or woman.</p>
            <p>The ſeventh Signe is Libra or the ballance which is an aireall Signe hot and moiſt, ſanguine, it im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth into the Ayre, heat, and moiſture, cauſing
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:192126:82"/>it to be hot, thicke, groſſe, mixt and verti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le to the individuall kinds of nature, as ſeeds, herbs, and bows of trees, it is a ſigne of the Ayry triplicity, Maſculine, Diuruall, Equinoctiall, Occidentall, and Autumnall; the cheife houſe of Venus hath the moneth of September, in which it is good to take phyſicke, to purge the body and let bloud, it go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verneth the reines, loynes, and haunches, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes are attributed to it as the ſtone or gravell, in the reynes and kidnyes and bladder, corruption of bloud or ulcers in the reines and kidnyes, impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumes, or ulcers there, or in the loynes or haunches and weakneſſe in the backe; it repreſents a body ſtraight, tall, and ſlender, a ſmooth, yellow, long haire, a round face, ſanguine colour, in age ſome pimples in the face or colour very high.</p>
            <p>The next in order is Scorpio, the eight Signe in the Zodiacke, it imparteth to the aire coldneſſe and moiſture, exempt from all temperature, brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging rather corruption then generation. It is a Signe of the watry triplicity, feminine, nocturnal, ſeptentrionall, fixed right and flegmaticke; the houſe and joy of Mars. It hath the moneth of October, wherein it is good to take Phyſicke, and indifferent to let bloud; it rules the ſecret members and bladder, ſignifies all diſeaſes thereof, as rupturs, the piles, gonorreha, hemrods, priapiſmes, all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions and defects in the yeard, ſtones and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trix. It perſonates a corpulent ſtrong body, broad
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:192126:83"/>face, a hairy body, ſhort neck, commonly ſubtill and deceitfull men.</p>
            <p>The ninth Signe is Sagittarius or the Archer, which is hot and dry, of the fiery triplicity, void of temperature, cauſing deſtruction of ſeeds and hearbs, and hurt to many living Creatures: it is maſculine, diurnall, orientall, chollerick, the houſe and joy of Iupiter, dexter, right, common, and double bodied, ruleth the month of November, wherein it is good to take Phyſick and let bloud, it governeth of mans body the thighs, and But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tocks, to which are ſubject all fiſtulas, bruiſes, and hurts in thoſe places, denoteth peſtilentiall feavors, falls from horſes, hurts from fourefooted beaſts, prejudice by fire, bloud heated &amp;c. It ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies a handſome welfavored perſon, long face, full and ruddy ſunburnt complexion, the ſtature indifferent tall, the haire light, cheſnut coulor, or browne.</p>
            <p>The tenth ſigne is Capricorne, or the Goat, which is cold and dry, untemperate, moveable, of the earthly triplicity, meridionall, nocturnall, ſolſtitiall, hiemall, and melancholly, feminine, the houſe of Saturne, and exaltation of Mars, it hath the moneth of December, governeth the knees and caſualities incident thereunto, either by diſlo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, ſpraines, or fractures; notes, itch, ſcabs, and leproſie, it ſignifies a ſhort body, long leane viſage, blacke haire, narrow chin, ſmall necke and
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:192126:83"/>narrow breaſt.</p>
            <p>The eleaventh Signe is called Aquarius, which is hott and moiſt, of the A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ery triplicity, untempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, noiſome, and hurtfull to all ſeeds, and things vegetable, maſculine, diurnall, occidentall, ſiniſter, fixed, and ſanguine the houſe of Saturne, wherein he rejoyceth, ruleth the moneth of Ianuary where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it is indifferent to take Phyſicke, and let bloud, &amp; of mans body he governeth the legs, and ankles, and all caſualties and inſtruments incident there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, all melancholly windes in the veines and bloud, cramps, gouts and paines in the legs, it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſents perſons of a thicke, ſhort, ſtrong, body, a long viſage, blacke or ſandy coloured haire, a ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guine complexion.</p>
            <p>The twelfeth and laſt Signe is Piſces, it is cold and moſt of the watery triplicity, declining from temperature, but imparting ſome comfort to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers things vegetable, feminine, nocturnall, ſep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentrionall, dexter double bodied, common and flegmaticke, the houſe of Iupiter and exaltation of Venus; hath the moneth of February, wherein it is good to take phyſicke, to let bloud indifferent. It claimes domination over the feet, and the diſeaſes and maladies incident therunto, as the gout, cramp, and cornes, ſignifies cold and moiſt, diſeaſes, boyls, itches, breakings out; and ulcers proceeding from melancholly and putrefacted bloud, it perſonates a lecherous idle effeminate perſon, a ſhort il favored
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:192126:84"/>body but fleſhy, a large face, the body ſomething crooked, and of a pale complexion, the ſun entreth into this Sign about the ninth day of February, &amp; dwelleth therein till the tenth of March, at which time ſhe finiſheth her winter quarter and the yeare</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the ſeven Planets.</head>
               <p>THe firſt and higheſt of the Plannets is Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, which is cold and dry, yet ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times moiſt upon accident of colour pale and wan, like to lead, he ſignifies a melancholly duſky and pale complexion, blacke haire, acrooked miſſhapen body, ruleth all ſickneſſe proceeding of melancholly humors or cold rumes, as blacke jaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, quartaine Agues and the like, the magnitude of his body according to Tichobrahe exceedeth the earth two and twenty times, he maketh his pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod through the Zodiack in thirty yeares.</p>
               <p>The next to Saturne is Iupiter, his quillity is hot and moiſt, temperate, maſculine, Ayry, the greater fortune, of colour ſplendent like gold perſonates a tall ſtature, browne ſanguine complexion, a long full viſage, and ſtrong body, ſignifies diſeaſes of the liver, heart, and inflammation of the lungs, plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſies paines in the backe, and ribs, feavers, and windineſſe, proceeding from corrupted and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:192126:84"/>bloud, his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke by Tycho, exceedeth the earth 14 times, he accompliſheth his courſe through the Zodiacke in twelve yeares.</p>
               <p>The next in order ſucceeds Mars, which is a plannet, in nature hot and dry intemperate, fiery and chollericke, the leſſer infortune, of Colour red like bloud, he ſignifies a meane ſtature, yellow haire the body hairy, if oriental, otherwiſe ſmooth; and the diſeaſes of the gall, peſtilent burning fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, plague, burnings, phrenſies, and all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempers, proceeding from choller, he is leſſer then the earth according to Tycho thirteen times, fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth his courſe in two yeares.</p>
               <p>The ſun is placed in the middle of the Planets, he is hot and dry, temperate, maſculine, and diur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, the Sun ſignifies men ambitious, high min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, a ſtrong large body, yellow complexion, and yellow haire, or reddiſh, much haire on the beard, healthfull of conſtitution of diſeaſes and ſickneſſe, hee ſignifies all infirmities of the braine and heart, pimples in the face, ſore eyes, cankers in the mouth, catars, and ſoonings. The Suns body is greater then the earth according to Tycho one hundred times, he runneth his courſe through the Zodiacke in three hundred ſixty fives dayes, five houres, and forty nine minutes.</p>
               <p>Venus is a Plannet cold and moiſt, temperate, the leſſor fortune, of the colour of gold, gliſtering and bright, feminine and diurnall, ſhee repreſents
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:192126:85"/>perſons of a fair complexion, if orientall ſomewhat tall ſtature, a ſtraight handſome body, browne haire, a roling eye and blackiſh, one loving neat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, full of mirth and amorous, of diſeaſes ſhee ſignifies the french pox, gonorrhea, all infirmities of the matrix, and generative members, in the raines backe and wombe, ſhe is leſſe then the earth according to Tycho ſix times, and finiſheth her courſe in a yeare.</p>
               <p>Mercury is a Plannet, mutable and wavering, whoſe quallity for the moſt part, is in drying, and equally moiſtning, for hee dryeth when he applyes to Mars or Sol, and moiſtneth applying to Venus or Luna, and for that cauſe is ſaid to be of a chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able uncertaine nature, good with the good, and ill with the ill, maſculine with the maſculine, and feminine with the feminine, of Colour like ſilver, gliſtring but not bright, if he be well placed hee ſignifies a ſharpe pregnant wit, a ſubtill quicke apprehenſion, an eloquent orator, a great lover of learning, and liberall ſciences if he be il dignified he repreſents a great lyar, a buſie prating boaſter, a falſe tale carrier, a perſonage he ſignifies of a tall ſtraight body, leane, and ſpare, ſad browne haire; a browne or honey colour complexion, he ſignifies all diſeaſes of the head and braine, vertigoes, gid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs in the head, imperfections in the ſpeech me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory and underſtanding hee is leſſe then the earth as ſaith Tycho nineteene times, he endeth his revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution in a yeare.</p>
               <pb n="155" facs="tcp:192126:85"/>
               <p>The Moone is the laſt and loweſt of all the Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets; ſhe is cold and moiſt, moiſture being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dominant, and bearing the greateſt power, yet ſometimes ſhe is ſaid to heat: ſhe uſually repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents a man of a middle ſtature, white and flegma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick complexion, a fleſhy body; ſignifies diſeaſes of the belly, as Fluxes, and Chollick, of the blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and generative members, all diſeaſes proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of cold Rhume, Sciatica's, Gout in the Feet, and palſeys; ſhe is leſſer then the Earth 42 times, ſhe diſpatcheth her Courſe in a month.</p>
               <p>Saturn ruleth of the week daies Saturday from whence the day is ſo called; he ruleth the firſt hour of the day, and the eighth; The Sun the firſt and eighth hours of Sunday; the Moone the firſt and eighth houres of Monday; <hi>Mars</hi> Tueſday the firſt and eighth hours of that day; <hi>Mercury</hi> the firſt and eight houres of Wedneſday; <hi>Jupiter</hi> ruleth Thurſday the firſt and eighth hours thereof; and <hi>Venus</hi> hath dominion of the firſt and eighth hours of Friday.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine.</head>
               <p>IF a mans urine be white at morning, and red be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore meat, and white after meat, he is in health; if it be very thick and fat, it ſignifies paine in the head.</p>
               <p>Urine that is fat, white, and moiſt, betokeneth the Feaver quartaine.</p>
               <pb n="156" facs="tcp:192126:86"/>
               <p>Urine that is bloudy and fleſhy, denotes ſome hurt and rotten Ulcer in the bladder and reines, who piſſeth bloud without ſickneſſe, hath ſome veine broken in his Reines.</p>
               <p>Womens urine that is cleere and ſhining, if ſhe caſt oft, and have no deſire to meat, it ſignifies ſhe is with child.</p>
               <p>Womens Urine that is ſtrong white, and ſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, ſignifies infirmities in the reines, in her ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Receipts, in her Chambers full of evil hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, and conſequently ſickneſſe of her whole body.</p>
               <p>Womens Urine that is bloudy and cleere as wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter under, ſignifies head-ach.</p>
               <p>Womans Urine of the colour of Lead (if ſhe be with child,) demonſtrates the child to be dead within her.</p>
               <p>Urine one part red, another blacke, another green, another blew, betokeneth death.</p>
               <p>Urine that is black and little in quantity beto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keneth death.</p>
               <p>Urine of the colour of Lead, that ſhineth raw, and bright, if the skin in the bottome ſhine not in the bottome, it ſignifies death.</p>
               <p>Urine of the colour of water, having a darke skie, it betokens death.</p>
               <p>Urine that hath dregs in the bottome mingled with bloud ſignifies death.</p>
               <p>Urine black and thick, if the ſick loath when he
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:192126:86"/>goeth to the ſtoole, it ſignifies death.</p>
               <p>Theſe are the moſt certain and generall Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Urine; many more there are, but I omit them as the moſt falacious ſtudy that appertaines to Phyſick; and if men truſt to the urine, it will moſt uſually deceive the learnedſt Doctor that is: I knew a Gentleman that was taken with a vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Feaver, he continued three daies, the diſeaſe increaſing the patient weakening; the third day a Doctor ſaw his water (who I forbeare to name, becauſe he is ſince dead,) his Judgement was that the patient was in perfect health, and had no diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temper on him; but that morning the ſmall Pox began to appeare on his body, and he had them as full, and as tedious a diſeaſe of it as any man e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver had: another Doctor gave the ſame Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on a ſick perſons water, who died within halfe an houre following.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Bathes</head>
               <p>BAthes are naturall and Artificiall, the naturall Baths of England are thoſe of the City of Bath in Somerſetſhire, in the Weſt Countrey: The chiefeſt matter, ſtrength, and vertue of theſe Baths is Brimſtone, and the chiefe ruler in them; theſe Boths of brimſtone do ſoften the ſinnews, and do heat; they are therefore good for the Palſey, for all ſuch place, or joynts that are pulled in too
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:192126:87"/>much, or extended too far forth, they aſſwage the deſire of often going to the ſtoole, and doing little or nothing; they ſcowre and cleanſe the skin, are good for the white Morphew and black, for Leproſie, and for all ſcabs, and ſcurfs, for old ſores, for the falling of humors into the joynts, for ſhaking or trembling of any member, they aſwage ache, or the ſwelling of any member, they are good for the gout, in the hands or feet, for the ſciatica, they aſwage all pains of the liver and milt, and aſſwage the hardneſſe thereof, they ſcowre away freckles, and cure all kind of itches: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whoſoever is afflicted with any of theſe diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, may (by Gods help) be perfectly cured; but it is neceſſary they obſerve theſe Rules follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p>The Counſell of the learned Phyſitians is, that they ſhould not at any time goe into any Bath to ſeek remedy for any ſickneſſe, unleſſe it be ſuch that almoſt the Phyſitians diſpaire of the healing of it, then let no man enter into any Bath, unleſſe his body be firſt very well purged, cleanſed, and prepared, for he that entreth into the Bath with his body unpurged, may perhaps never returne home againe, or if he doe, he moſt commonly car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryeth away worſe diſeaſes then he brought to the Bath with him. Neither may you enter into the Bath the ſame day that ye come thither, but reſt and eaſe your body a day or two.
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:192126:87"/>For the time of the yeare for Bathing, the moſt fit and proper ſeaſons, are the moneth of May and September, but the ſpring is the beſt, and likewiſe for to take any manner of phyſicke, the beſt time of the morning, after the Sun be an houre high at leaſt; and before any patient goe into the Bath, if his diſeaſe will ſuffer him, let him walke an houre or at the leaſt halfe an houre, before he enter into the Bath.</p>
               <p>But you muſt at no time enter into the Bath, except you have beene at ſtoole either by nature or art; ye may take a ſuppoſitory or gliſter, and in great neceſſity pills, but he that is ſo purged muſt not enter into the Bath, for the ſpace of fourteene houres afterwards.</p>
               <p>If any be counſelled to goe into the Bath twice on a day, he muſt not enter into it, till ſix or ſeven houres after dinner, and tarry not, ſo long in the Bath in the afternoone as you did in the mornings the common time of tarrying in the Bath, is moſt commonly allowed to be an hower or more or leſſe, wherein reſpect muſt be had to the ſtrength and nature of the Bath, as alſo to the complexion, diſeaſe and ſtrength of the patient.</p>
               <p>Let no man continew ſo long in the Bath untill he faint, but let him come out before that, if he ſuſpect any ſuch weakneſſe.</p>
               <p>Ye muſt alwayes goe into the Bath, with an empty ſtomach, and as long as you are in it, and
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:192126:88"/>as long as you continew in it you muſt neither eat nor drinke unleſs great neceſſity require it, ſo that you ſoone in the Bath, or be in danger of ſooning: as ſaith Gallen, fourteen <hi>de methodo medendi,</hi> that no man ſhould eate nor drinke untill he hath flept after Bathing.</p>
               <p>When you come out of the Bath, cover your ſelfe well that you take no cold, and dry off the water from your body, with warme cloths, and go preſently into a warme bed and ſweat there if you can: wipe off the ſweate diligently, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſleepe, but ye muſt not drinke any thing untill dinner time, unleſs ye be very faint.</p>
               <p>And after that ye have ſweat, and ſlept, and be ſufficiently delivered, and cleared from the heat, that you had in the Bath, and afterwards in the bed, then may you walke a little before you go to dinner, for by meaſurable and moderate walking, the vapors and windeneſs that is contracted in the Bath is driven away.</p>
               <p>If the patient cannot walke, then let his body be gently rubbed, if his diſeaſe can ſuffer it, after this ye may goe to dinner, wherein you may uſe moderation in your diet, alwayes ariſing from the table with an appetite; beware eſpecially that you drinke not any cold drinke, and abſtaine from all things that are cold, when ye firſt begin to eate, or drink, but let your meat and drink be temperately warm, leaſt when your body is inwardly hot with
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:192126:88"/>Bathing and ſweating, the cold ſtrike ſuddenly into ſome principall member, and hurt it.</p>
               <p>They that are of a hot complexion and open bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, ought not to tarry ſo long in the Bathe as they that are of a colder and faſter complexion.</p>
               <p>It is moſt requiſite for ſuch patients as have any diſeaſe in the head, as Catharr or Rheume, Palſies, or ſuch like diſeaſes, that the water be powred ſtrongly upon the mould of the head, and upon the nape of the necke.</p>
               <p>The clay or grounds of the Bathe is good for the dropſy, and likewiſe for ſhrunken, ſwelled, and hard places; which cannot be wel healed with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther medicines: the manner of uſing it is, to lay the grounds upon the place and hold the ſame a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the fire, untill it be ſomewhat harde, and then to waſh it away with the water of the Bath: likewiſe, thoſe that cannot tarry long at the Bath, may carry ſome of the water, and grounds home with them, and uſe it there in the like manner.</p>
               <p>If you be rid of your diſeaſe, by the Bathing, give God the Glory, goe thy way, ſin no more, leaſt a worſe thing come unto thee: but if you bee not healed the firſt time, patiently waite upon God by prayer, and holy life, untill the next opportunity of uſing the meanes, and then if it conduce to Gods glory, and thy good, thou ſhalt aſſuredly bee healed, by the Grace of God, of whom commeth all health of ſoule and body.
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:192126:89"/>But ſome, and two many, if the medicine or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the phyſition doe not forthwith anſwer their expectation, will moſt impatient, and wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly, exclaime againſt and abuſe the Phyſitian, and the medicine both, as if they were to appoint God a time when they ſhall be healed, and limit the holy one of Iſraell, but <hi>nolens voleus,</hi> they muſt ſtay the Lords leiſure; and let ſuch as have beene at the Bath, obſerve the ſame diet they did when they were there, for the ſpace of a moneth, at leaſt, abſtayning from Carnall uſe of women, and if God pleaſe they ſhall have their deſire; for, <hi>Is ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus eſt qui dat ſalutem &amp;c.</hi> To him give the praiſe, to whom be aſcribed, all Praiſe and Glory, for evermore, <hi>in ſeculae ſeculorum.</hi> Amen.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="index">
            <pb n="163" facs="tcp:192126:89"/>
            <head>The Table.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Rtery. pag. 3</item>
               <item>Of the Armes. pag. 14. 15</item>
               <item>Accidents to remove from wounds. pag. 50</item>
               <item>Stinging of Adders. pag. 68. 126</item>
               <item>Purging Ale. pag. 15</item>
               <item>Ale of health and ſtrength. pag. 78</item>
               <item>Aches pag. 102. 104</item>
               <item>Agues. pag. 103. 107</item>
               <item>Apoſtumations. pag. 127</item>
               <item>St. Anthonies fire. pag. 144</item>
               <item>Aries. pag. 146</item>
               <item>Aquarius. pag. 151</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>B</head>
               <item>Of the Braine. pag. 6. 7</item>
               <item>Of the Breaſt. pag. 17. 18</item>
               <item>Of the Backe. pag. 18</item>
               <item>Of the Belly. pag. 22</item>
               <item>Of the Buttocks. pag. 30</item>
               <pb n="164" facs="tcp:192126:90"/>
               <item>To joyne broken Bones. pag. 49</item>
               <item>Bloud to ſtanch. pag. 53</item>
               <item>Wounds in the Breaſt. pag. 62</item>
               <item>Wounds in the Belly. pag. 63. 64</item>
               <item>Burnings. pag. 66. 68. 90. 126</item>
               <item>Piſſing Bloud. pag. 75</item>
               <item>Stinking Breath. pag. 77</item>
               <item>Shortnes of Breath. pag. 83</item>
               <item>Weak Back. pag. 86</item>
               <item>Sore Breaſt. pag. 58. 114. 131</item>
               <item>Ague in the Breaſt. pag. 88</item>
               <item>For a Boyle. pag. 90. 112</item>
               <item>Botches. pag. 100</item>
               <item>Bliſters. pag. 101</item>
               <item>Bruiſes. pag. 102. 104. 131</item>
               <item>Broken Belly. pag. 113</item>
               <item>Heat in the Back. pag. 117</item>
               <item>Bioſome. pag. 127</item>
               <item>Griping in the Belly. pag. 128</item>
               <item>Bloudy flux. pag. 141</item>
               <item>Black Jaundies pag. 144</item>
               <item>Bathings. pag. 158. 159. 160. 161</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>C</head>
               <item>Chyrurgery Defined. pag. 1</item>
               <item>Callus to ingender. pag. 49</item>
               <item>Cataplaſmes. pag. 60</item>
               <item>Canker. pag. 70. 109</item>
               <item>Conſumption. pag. 72. 82. 84. 143</item>
               <pb n="165" facs="tcp:192126:90"/>
               <item>Cough. pag. 82. 84. 125</item>
               <item>Chine Cough. pag. 85. 135</item>
               <item>Corns to cure. pag. 91</item>
               <item>Collick. pag. 91. 113.</item>
               <item>Carbunckles. pag. 95</item>
               <item>Cramp. pag. 102</item>
               <item>Convulſion. pag. 111. 116</item>
               <item>Choller. pag. 129</item>
               <item>Childbed. pag. 114</item>
               <item>Cancer. pag. 147</item>
               <item>Capricorne. pag. 150</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>D</head>
               <item>Diſlocations. pag. 42</item>
               <item>Dropſie. pag. 73. 108. 129. 130. 136</item>
               <item>Delivery. pag. 110. 126</item>
               <item>Drunkennes. pag. 134</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>E</head>
               <item>Of the Eyes. pag. 9</item>
               <item>Embryon. pag. 35</item>
               <item>Rheume in the Eyes. pag. 70. 80. 110</item>
               <item>Pinne and web in the Eye. pag. 70. 80</item>
               <item>Bleard Eyes. pag. 81</item>
               <item>Heat in the Eyes. pag. 81</item>
               <item>Water for ſore Eyes. pag. 82</item>
               <item>Noyſe in the Eares. pag. 127</item>
               <item>Watring Eyes to heale. pag. 128</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>F</head>
               <item>Of the Face. pag. 8</item>
               <pb n="166" facs="tcp:192126:91"/>
               <item>Feet. pag. 38</item>
               <item>Flux. pag. 80. 85. 86. 126</item>
               <item>For a ſweld Face. pag. 89</item>
               <item>For a Fiſtula. pag. 89. 109</item>
               <item>For a Felon. pag. 90. 112</item>
               <item>Falling ſicknes. pag. 102. 113. 122. 132</item>
               <item>Flos Unguentorum. pag. 122. 123</item>
               <item>Rheume in the Face. pag. 128. 129</item>
               <item>Fainting. pag. 140</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>G</head>
               <item>Of the Gall. pag. 28</item>
               <item>Gunſhot. pag. 54. 65</item>
               <item>Of Gunpowder. pag. 54. 55</item>
               <item>Burning with Gunpowder. pag. 66</item>
               <item>Green ſicknes. pag. 71. 107. 116</item>
               <item>Green wounds. pag. 101</item>
               <item>Green ſalve. pag. 106</item>
               <item>Bleeding Gummes. pag. 115</item>
               <item>Gonorrhea. pag. 125</item>
               <item>Gemini. pag. 146</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>H</head>
               <item>Of the Head. pag. 5. 6. 7</item>
               <item>Of the Heart. pag. 18. 19</item>
               <item>Of the Hanches. pag. 30. 35</item>
               <item>Hips. pag. 37</item>
               <item>Wounds in the Head. pag. 58. 59. 61</item>
               <item>Pain in the Head. pag. 69. 133</item>
               <item>Hydreleon Galeni. pag. 69. 70</item>
               <item>Trembling of the Heart. pag. 111</item>
               <pb n="167" facs="tcp:192126:91"/>
               <item>Headache. pag. 114. 117</item>
               <item>To purge the Head. pag. 127</item>
               <item>Paſſions of the Heart. pag. 128</item>
               <item>Scald Head. pag. 134. 144</item>
               <item>To comfort the Heart. pag. 143</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>I</head>
               <item>Inflammations. pag. 93</item>
               <item>Infection. pag. 95</item>
               <item>Itch pag. 109. 127. 134</item>
               <item>Iay powder. pag. 12<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>Ioynt Ague. pag. 139</item>
               <item>Iaundies. pag. 141. 144</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>K</head>
               <item>Of the Kidneys. pag. 29</item>
               <item>Swelling Knees. pag. 103</item>
               <item>Knobs to diſſolve. pag. 104</item>
               <item>Kernels. pag. 114</item>
               <item>Stone in the Kidneys. pag. 121</item>
               <item>Kings Evill. pag. 129</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>L</head>
               <item>Ligaments. pag. 2</item>
               <item>Of the Lungs. pag. 21</item>
               <item>Of the Liver. pag. 27</item>
               <item>The Legs. pag. 39</item>
               <item>Luxation. pag. 42</item>
               <item>Wounds in the Legs. pag. 65</item>
               <item>Plaiſter for the Legs. pag. 99. 100</item>
               <item>Liver. pag. 108. 137</item>
               <item>For the Lunge. pag. 125</item>
               <pb n="168" facs="tcp:192126:92"/>
               <item>Leaden Plaiſter. pag. 135</item>
               <item>Leo. pag. 147</item>
               <item>Libar. pag. 148</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>M</head>
               <item>Of the Mouth. pag. 10</item>
               <item>Secret Members. pag. 31</item>
               <item>Matrix. pag. 35</item>
               <item>Heat in the Mouth. pag. 70</item>
               <item>Stinking Mouth. pag. 77</item>
               <item>Milke to dry up. pag. 88</item>
               <item>For the Mother pag. 90. 91. 116 118. 137.</item>
               <item>Megrim pag. 110. 133</item>
               <item>Morphew. pag. 140</item>
               <item>Mars. pag. 153</item>
               <item>Mercury. pag. 154</item>
               <item>The Moone. pag. 155</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>N</head>
               <item>Of the Noſe. pag. 9</item>
               <item>Noſtrills. pag. 9</item>
               <item>Of the Neck. pag. 13</item>
               <item>Bleeding at Noſe. pag. 114. 131. 132</item>
               <item>Nipples to skin. pag. 139</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>O</head>
               <item>Old ſores to cure. pag. 103</item>
            </list>
            <pb n="169" facs="tcp:192126:92"/>
            <list>
               <head>P</head>
               <item>Poyſoned wounds to cure. pag. 58</item>
               <item>Plaiſter for wounds. pag. 59</item>
               <item>Preſervative againſt the Plague. pag. 69. 70. 73</item>
               <item>Purges. pag. 71</item>
               <item>Phyſicke. pag. 72. 124</item>
               <item>Plague Water. pag. 73</item>
               <item>Powder for wounds. pag. 76</item>
               <item>Peſtilence. pag. 95. 96</item>
               <item>Palſey. pag. 102. 115. 120. 140</item>
               <item>Plague. pag. 109</item>
               <item>Piles. pag. 118</item>
               <item>Pluriſie. pag. 116. 135</item>
               <item>Pills pag. 138</item>
               <item>Piſſing Bloud. pag. 141</item>
               <item>Piſces. pag. 151</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Q</head>
               <item>For a quinzie. pag. 111</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>R</head>
               <item>Rheume. pag. 161. 140</item>
               <item>Ringworme. pag. 105</item>
               <item>Rickets. pag. 108. 118. 119</item>
               <item>Running of the Reines. pag. 112</item>
               <item>Reeds to ſtop. pag. 102</item>
               <item>Simple members. pag. 2</item>
               <pb n="170" facs="tcp:192126:93"/>
               <item>Sinews pag. 2</item>
               <item>Shoulders. pag. 14</item>
               <item>Stomack. pag. 25. 132</item>
               <item>Spermatick veſſels. pag. 32</item>
               <item>Swounning pag. 41</item>
               <item>Scalding. pag. 68. 90. 122</item>
               <item>Stinging of Snakes. pag. 68</item>
               <item>Scurvy. pag. 69. 108</item>
               <item>Sleepe to cauſe. pag. 69</item>
               <item>For a ſtraine. pag. 75. 79. 101</item>
               <item>Spleene. pag. 85. 108. 132.</item>
               <item>Swelling of the Stones. pag. 86. 87</item>
               <item>Soreneſs. pag. 89</item>
               <item>For the Stone. pag. 91. 98. 121</item>
               <item>Sciatica. pag. 101. 105</item>
               <item>Shingles. pag. 101</item>
               <item>Feſtred Sore. pag. 105</item>
               <item>Scabbes. pag. 109. 125</item>
               <item>Stitches. pag. 116</item>
               <item>Watry Sores. pag. 118</item>
               <item>Stomack to cleanſe. pag. 120. 134</item>
               <item>Swelling. pag. 125</item>
               <item>Spraines. pag. 132. 133</item>
               <item>For the Stones bruiſed. pag. 136</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>S</head>
               <item>Seereclothes. pag. 140</item>
               <item>The 12 Signes. pag. 145</item>
               <pb n="171" facs="tcp:192126:93"/>
               <item>Scorpio. pag. 149</item>
               <item>Sagittarius. pag. 150</item>
               <item>Saturne. pag. 152</item>
               <item>Sol. pag. 153</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>T</head>
               <item>Tendons. pag. 3</item>
               <item>Thighs. pag. 38</item>
               <item>Tearmes to procure. pag. 71</item>
               <item>Toothach. pag. 77</item>
               <item>Tumors to diſſolve. pag. 94</item>
               <item>Tongue ſwelled. pag. 127</item>
               <item>Sore Throat. pag. 137. 140</item>
               <item>Taurus. pag. 146</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>U</head>
               <item>Unguents. pag. 59. 60</item>
               <item>Heat in the Urine. pag. 74. 75</item>
               <item>Vomiting to ſtay. pag. 76. 120. 121</item>
               <item>Ulcers. pag. 99. 117.</item>
               <item>Venoms. pag. 101</item>
               <item>Unguentum album. pag. 139</item>
               <item>Virgo. pag. 148</item>
               <item>Venue. pag. 153</item>
               <item>Urines. pag. 156. 157</item>
            </list>
            <pb n="172" facs="tcp:192126:94"/>
            <list>
               <head>W</head>
               <item>What Wounds are. pag. 40</item>
               <item>Cordiall Waters. pag. 68</item>
               <item>Whites. pag. 86</item>
               <item>For Winde. pag. 93</item>
               <item>Green Wounds. pag. 106</item>
               <item>Warts. pag. 114</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:192126:94"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
